so hello everyone and welcome to this course
on natural language processing so in this
course we will we will be having this course
for twelve weeks and in which week will have
five modules so today we are starting this
course and this is the first module ah first
lecture for this week and this is basically
the course introduction what what are the
different topics we will be covering this
course what are the different text books that
you might be using for this and some other
details that might be necessarily for you
ok so firstly my contact so if you have certain
questions you can only you may also write
to me on this email i d so this is my official
email id and you might also want to visit
my web page that is provided in in this link
so in this course we will have two teaching
assistants so amrith krishna and mayank singh
both are my phd students and they are working
on n l p so so idea is that they can they
will be able to help you with any of the queries
that you having during this course and they
will also help you with all the assignments
that we will providing this course so they
will so in addition to me they will also be
your primary contacts during this course
so in this course we will be following two
of the main so very very popular books on
natural language processing so so jurafsky
and martin is a very popular book so title
is speech natural language processing so so
this is your second addition but there may
be also be the third addition that is available
so you might you second additional and any
later additional for of this book for this
course
then there is a book by manning and schutze
on foundations of a statistical natural language
processing by m i t press that is again a
very very popular book and we will be using
concepts from both the books along which some
other sources in this course so you can you
can try to avail any of these two books or
both the books if possible and with with the
course some addition reading from this book
will be helpful for ah addition the the concepts
and getting a good class on the course
so in addition to the books you you will also
get the lecture slides so from the lectures
that i will be taking this course all those
slides will be made available to you and if
necessary i will also point out to some additional
ah a person and any other material that might
be helpful for you so that also will provide
on the on the course website and we also thinking
of giving you some ipython note books
so so that you can also do some sort of hands
on so these note books are so you will be
using python for doing certain text twicing
tasks and so this will we will also provide
you some basic instructions on how to start
teaching this ipython note books so they will
also very very helpful for this course because
this is n l p is mostly and hands on so its
its not very very nice just to have an l b
course to have only the theory theoretical
knowledge its important also so that given
a problem you can a start doing some processing
over that ok so in in for the evaluation so
we will have assignments that will be given
after every week throughout the course so
that will constitute twenty five percent of
the of the whole evaluation of for this course
ok so they will assignments will be on the
lectures that are that are covered in this
course also we might also give you some sort
of programming assignments time to time in
this course
so they will be all been in python plus so
there will with the final exam that will be
constituting seventy five percent of the overall
weightage that mean the after the end of this
course so what are the different topics that
we will be covering this course so this course
we have we have starting with so the basic
topics that are required for understanding
all the concepts in in n l p then we will
move to some applications so what are the
various basic topics that we will be covering
this course so we will start with the text
processing so given a text data how do you
start doing some processing over that so that
may include how do i tokenize it that is breaking
in to various words how do you i start doing
lemmatization stemming find out the route
words and so on
then we will be start with very foundational
topic on language modelling that is how do
i use the ordering information inside the
language for developing certain applications
so how can i use this statistics then we will
go to the morphology that is what to different
categories of words and given a text data
how do i start finding out different categories
of words so what are the different applications
or algorithms that i can i can use then we
will go to the to high level finding out what
are different groups in the sentence how they
are connected to each other in the topic of
syntax then we will move to se semantics where
we will have various models of semantics using
lexicon and lexical semantics and using the
distributions and distribution semantics and
we will also touch upon the topic on word
embeddings that is very very popular ah as
of now
so finally we will also cover topic mortis
so how do you find out what are the various
topics that i have covered in a given text
data and how do you i make use of this in
various applications then after cub once the
basic topics are covered we will also devote
some time especially in the last three weeks
on how do you a start applying these basic
concepts for certain applications so n l p
is very very broad topic and you will see
enumerable applications where you can apply
all these concepts but to give you an idea
so we will take three very very interesting
and important application in n l p so will
start with the topic of entity linking and
information extraction this will be the first
application that will be cover then we will
go to text summarization and classification
finally we will end up with opinion analysis
and opinion mining so this will be the the
final application that we will be cover and
we will hope that whatever basics and some
aspects of application that we cover in this
course will help you in taking any new problem
and starting to think of euron approach for
solving that ok so idea of this course is
that you you are not only aware of what are
the tools available you can use them on your
own but also you are you know what are the
basic algorithms what are the foundations
and given a new problem you can think of a
think of a approach on your own and build
your own tools so that is the the goal of
this course and as i said earlier this is
million introductory course but all the basics
that that are required for dealing with any
advanced topic will be covered
so if you take any new research topic that
is not covered in this course the idea would
be whatever knowledge is covered will help
you to at least start understanding the topic
and then go deep in to that so now so if you
works on why do we need to study n l p ok
so so what does so what is n l p so n l p
is all about processing text data so now you
see in in on on everywhere so you can find
out this abandons of text data ok now you
can also see the text is the largest human
knowledge a pastry that you that you have
so so what are the various sources where you
find all these knowledge in in text data so
you can think of all the wikipedia articles
for instance all the news articles that come
dealing ok so all the scientific articles
they are available and text format patents
all with the all the social media all they
have tweets facebook posts and everything
is also available in the text format
so now this abundance of text data and this
is all quite un structured ok so to be able
to make use of this information and build
some rise applications you should know how
to process this data and thats why n l p comes
in to picture so ya so with recently with
all the tweets facebook posts comments over
all the news articles everywhere and quora
so you have an abundance of text data and
you should you should be aware of some tools
by which you can do certain analysis of this
data so now so so this is one thing that we
have a lot of text data available this is
another another problem that so so much data
is available that is unstructured but this
is not in the single language for example
in its not in english so so this gives you
some this chart gives you some a statistics
so so what you will see here so this is from
november twenty two thousand fifteen how many
millions of users are there in on internet
and different languages you see yes english
users are the highest at the same time you
have lots and lots of chinese users and then
spanish and arabic and again you see large
number for all the rest language that are
not covered in this chart
so you will not be able to understand all
the languages so and you will needed tool
that can take any given language and try to
put it in the language that you can understand
ok so some sort of tools are are necessary
so that they can automatically find out what
is the language provided in this document
how do i ah translate to some languages that
i know and so on doing some information summarization
over there and translation ok so you need
n l p in all of these aspects so now so this
lecture i will just end with dealing saying
what is n l p ok so what is the main goal
of n l p as such what for this research field
of n l p so if you think about it so so there
is a very very broad ah scientific goal of
this field of n l p and that is can be understand
language can we have a very very deep understanding
on how human process language can we teach
computers how to understand language
so that is i will say a deep scientific goal
behind all the n l p so can we teach computers
on understanding language and they can may
be respond with humans the way humans to and
and so on so that is very very longest and
in goal of n l p so this we would says mainly
a fundamental scientific goal ok i want to
have a deep understanding of broad natural
language but with that we also be very very
practical and engineering goal and what is
that so the goal is that so yes there is lot
of text it available even if i do not know
how to make computers understand that fully
can i still make use of this data to build
some very very nice applications that that
will be helpful for people in they really
life and that you can see from you own life
so how many different applications that you
might be using ok starting from the search
that is very very very ah common application
that every one uses and so you will see in
in a lot of other applications starting from
news recommendations and and all that that
your using a new really life ok
so so this is the engineering goal for n l
p that is can i design implement and test
systems that will process natural language
and that i design for very very practical
applications that we can use in day to day
life so this is the engineering goal of n
l p and that is what we will be mainly focusing
in this course and n l p ok so all the concepts
and and algorithms that we will discuss in
this course are mainly focus to words various
engineering applications of n l p so so with
that i again welcome you for to this course
so so in the next module or the next lecture
we will discuss what what do we actually do
in n l p by taking some simple examples ok
thank you