hello everyone so welcome to the third lecture
of the first week so in the last lecture we
were discussing what do we do in n l p what
are the various applications where n l p has
been used ok and in which been use currently
in what are some of the ferric some of the
future potentials of n l p so today in this
lecture we will discuss why is n l p hard
what are the some of the difficult is that
we face while the joining algorithms for n
l p and and why do we need to worry about
various machine learning techniques and all
an n l p ok
so which is start with a very simple case
of of the kind of problems that you face in
n l p so we start with the case of lexical
ambiguities ok ambiguities as you understand
is ah implied for the same word meaning various
interpretations ok
so take take this example sentence have so
have this sentence will will will wills will
so what you see here is the same word will
has been used five times so let us try to
to find out what are the various interpretations
of meaning the same what will has been used
for will will will wills will so what what
do you say about the first will ok so the
first will is a modal verb like should would
can etcetera the second will here is an name
of a person this sometimes easy to get from
the from the english sentence because the
full always been in capitals ok then you have
the third will so this is a verb in the sentence
ok to express his will the fourth one is again
a name of a person you can see by the apostrophe
that is after this word but it can be either
the same will or a different will ok so against
a name of person but we denote is the same
will or a different will
but by the way we the way we write language
in the way we communicating language we can
say this probably is a second person because
if it by the same person i would have used
probably hinge ok and this will is a noun
the will itself ok so what you are saying
in the same sentence will the person will
will express or use wills will we are using
the same word will at least four in four different
meanings so this is one of the extreme cases
that we seen language ok but let us try to
go through some other examples so this is
another example rose rose to put rose roes
on her rows of roses ok so so here can we
try to decide for what are the various meanings
that i am flight for the same word rose
so what you say about the first rose the first
rose is the name of the person ok rose they
should be a verb in the percent past tense
to put rose rose ok so what is that this will
be an adjective and rose is some sort of the
seafood ok and then we have the the next sentence
on her rose of roses and these versus you
can find out these are the flowers and this
is arrow with you so again this see here the
same word rose if you see the way it is written
so in terms of autography the same word rose
has been use one now as a name as a verb as
an adjective and as a flower ok four different
sans age but but for the time just try to
think of some a speech recognition system
ok we are your trying to pronounce this sentence
and it has to transcript what what are the
different words that you have said in your
trends so it will have ambiguity even to find
out whether this rose means arrow e s or arrow
f s e ok this is another another problem that
this also handled by various models that we
will see in natural language processing ok
and let us take another extreme example ok
so the buffalo buffalo buffalo buffalo buffalo
buffalo buffalo buffalo ok so now in this
sent this sentence is compares only by a single
word used to a to times so can you try to
decide for this ok so let me give your hint
here so here the what buffalo has been using
two sense three senses buffalo so one is the
city in u s another buffalo is an animal and
the third buffalo is like a verb that is used
in the same sense as bully ok so now given
these three interpretations so can you try
to decide for the meaning of the sentence
ok so let us try to identify various blocks
here buffalo buffalo buffalo buffalo buffalo
buffalo buffalo buffalo ok so let me try to
give you what are the units together ok
so there are three units in this sentence
ok so now what would be the interpretation
so these are the cities ok so these are the
cities by c and the animal a a and a and these
two are verbs ok so then this would be the
interpretation of the sentence buffaloes from
buffalo new york whom buffaloes from buffalo
new york bully bully buffaloes from buffalo
new york ok probably is not the sentence that
you will encountered very often in the in
the copes but this is has to convey the point
that that in language you can you can actually
use the same word and multiple different meanings
and that creates a problem and this problem
is called as lexical ambi ambiguity the same
word in lexicon is used in multiple different
senses ok
so now let us go to the next problem or again
get to ambiguities that is a structural ambiguity
ok what do i mean by structural ambiguity
so i can have different interpretations of
the same sent sentence ok so let us see the
first sentence here so this is very very common
example that we given n l p the men saw the
boy with the binoculars ok so can you try
to see what is the ambiguity here so the ambiguity
here is whether the binoculars are with the
boy or the binoculars are with man whether
the men saw the boy with this binoculars or
whether the men saw the who was standing with
these binoculars so these are two different
interpretations of the same sentence
let us see the other sentence here flying
planes can be dangerous can you see the two
interpretations of the sentence so what is
dangerous are the planes dangerous or flying
dangerous you see flying planes can be dangerous
ok so whether the flying is dangerous or flying
planes together is dangerous so these are
the two interpretations of the same sentence
similarly you can see the third sentence here
whole found in the room wall police are looking
in to it ok so now can you see the ambiguity
in the sentence so ambiguity here is what
appeal police look looking in to or the looking
into the whole or the looking in to the matter
that there was a whole and we are looking
in to the matter ok
so this is another problem that we that we
face very very often would language that this
is ambiguous both in terms of lexical ambiguity
the same word can imply multiple meanings
or a structural ambiguity where the same sentence
can be interpreted in multiple ways ok and
then we have some other problems like languages
very imprecise and vague so what are the examples
here so so here is simple sentence it is very
warm here so can you see what is the weightiness
or imprecision here so whenever i see a word
like its very warm here i cannot tell for
sure what would be the temperature where ok
is if i am an india for me warm many a temperature
of only forty degrees celsius but if i am
in u k europe for me warm might been twenty
five degree celsius ok
and it might also depend on what was the weather
in the last month and so so this depends on
a lot of context you find out what is the
actual temperature that is been conveyed by
this simple sentence similarly if you see
the other other example ok so have a question
did you did your mother called your aunt last
night and the answer is i am sure she must
have so what is the imprecision and vagueness
here in the sentence so you see whenever i
say i am sure she would have done that that
means i do not know ok if i if i know that
i will say yes she she has called but whenever
i am see i am show she must have so probably
i do not know whether she had ok but yeah
thats what i say this is the fun part of n
l p with the that helps in consisting a lot
of jokes ok
so i have the symbol so this is a nice joke
for the class is so why is the teacher wearing
sun glasses and you can given answer because
the class is so bright and you can see the
bright might mean either the class is bright
in the sense of lot of sun light and on or
because the class is very bright in the sense
of the students being really intangible ok
fine so continuing on the same topic of ambiguities
so let us see some other examples so that
that is something that we see will news headlines
so which is the first sentence hospitals assued
by seven foot doctors so can we see the ambiguity
here in general when you when you look at
this sentence what comes to your mind probably
the doctors as seven foot ok
seven foot doctors ok of course we will a
seven feet doctors but yes this might you
want to a interpretation but what is implied
by the sentence there are seven different
doctors ok and they are all four doctors so
that is what is implied seven different foot
doctors take the next sentence here in stolen
painting found by tree so can you see the
ambiguity so it looks as if the tree found
the paintings ok but at but what it means
is that the paintings for found any other
tree ok take the third example teachers teacher
a strikes
idle kids so when you see the sentence as
it is what comes your mind teacher strikes
some kids ok but what the headline where meaning
teacher is striking ok there is some semicolon
and the kids are idle ok
so lets take lets do an simple exercise on
the on the same topic of ambiguity so i can
give a simple sentence are made her doctor
now try to find so peoples so there are three
are ten or more than ten meanings for the
sentence but try to find at least five meanings
of this sentence i made her duck ok so thats
do this exercise i made her duck so whatever
different meanings this sentence can take
ok so we need to see what is the different
interpretations each of the word can have
in this sentence ok so for example the worth
made can mean for example cook or make ok
so one interpretation can be i could a duck
for her ok so simple interpretation i cooked
a duck for her ok that is one interpretation
now in the same sense of cooking i can also
try to write a different interpretation ok
what is that so one meaning is i made her
duck another could be i made a duck that belong
to her ok i cooked a duck belonging to her
so that is her duck it may not i might not
a cook for her i might a cook for myself but
i cooked that that belong to her i made her
duck now made can also mean mean is simp simple
making so you can think of an artificial duck
like a toy and i can say i made the artificial
duck she owns ok of course we can also have
the second interpretation here i can i i made
the artificial duck for her or belonging to
her
but let us take this interpretation now what
are the other two interpretations you can
think of ok so now try to think of the other
meaning of duck kind of be use as a work ok
so if your listening to some cricket commentaries
sometimes so batsman duck whenever they bou
bouncer and sometimes ok so that means loading
once head so one interpretation can be i made
her lower her head that can be another interpretation
now can you think of any different interpretation
from all the for that we have see hint will
now so the hint is that try to going the herry
about a mode ok so this is something like
i waved my magic wand and converted her into
duck this thats a possibles would interpretation
i waved my magic wa wand that turned her into
a duck ok
so you see the simple sentence i made here
duck can have at least these five different
in depressions so so these of the five interpretations
that we saw so now what is in the language
that gives rise to all these different interpretations
ok so let us try to look closely ok so this
ambiguity is pervasive everywhere so how so
one thing is about the syntactic category
what is the role of a word in a sentence so
you see the word duck here it can mean either
a noun or a verb so can you label the sentences
here where duck has been uses a noun so this
is noun this is noun this is noun this is
verb this is noun ok so fine so these are
two interpretations duck can be noun or ever
ok
then there are there is a there is a case
with her the word her can either be a possessive
of her or dative for her so can you see the
the two examples here the two interpretations
which were made because of these so this was
dative i did it for her or this is possessive
belonging to her so these are again two interpretations
for for this this ambiguity in language then
we so make can mean either to create or cook
this so this for cooking and this was also
making what is then if you go to grammar the
same work make can be either transitive that
means it will be a na it will be a verb with
a single noun as direct objective it can be
ditransitive that means a verb that is having
two different non objects or action transitive
it has a direct object plus a verb
so in these five interpretations can you try
to mark them where the verb make was uses
transitive ditransitive and action transitive
so here i have the same work make which is
having and object and a verb ok i made her
lower her head or i made her do something
ok so this is action transitive ok what is
ditransitive so where there are two objects
of the same work so i cooked a duck for her
so this as two different objects and what
is the single transitive i could they duck
belonging to her this is a single object ok
so here there are two different objects so
this is ditransitive and this is transitive
so in language the same verb may can be use
any of these three different vague and that
gives me three different interpretations ok
so so now suppose you go to phonetics ok so
i am is speaking this sentence i made her
duck what are different interpretations you
can think of so i am so what happens in speak
a speech recognition i am a spin something
and you have to transcript ok so whenever
i see i made her duck you might thing of all
these possible transcriptions so like i am
eight or duck i am aid her duck all these
are possible ok but the problem that n l p
decisions will face is going there are many
different possible interpretations which going
to choose in a given context ok so let see
something from the ambiguity now so i have
the simple sentence i saw the men with the
telescope and we saw earlier it can have two
different parses so parses i mean different
ways in which the words can be connected in
this sentence
so we will have a complete topic on parses
is give we will discuss there in detail but
i guess you can see at least the the idea
from the last example so now suppose i try
to increase the length of the sentence i saw
the man on the hill with the telescope and
immediately you can find five different parses
of the scientist ok this is doesn't stop here
so let me have bit this sentence i saw the
man on the hill in texas with the telescope
ok so now it has fourteen parses if i say
i saw the man on the hill in texas with the
telescope at noon it has forty two parses
and if i say i saw the man on the hill in
texas with the telescope at noon on on monday
it look one thirty two parses ok and you can
actually the laid these numbers to something
call a catalan number ok
so as you keep on increasing the number of
in the sentence the number of interpretations
in which they can be connected in the sentence
increase ok so now so why is language ambiguous
ok this can be a nice question that why is
language ambiguous at all so we need to understand
what is the goal of language as such so language
is used for communication ok so the goal in
in prediction or communication languages to
to be able to communicate ideas ah clearly
ok but at the same time i should there are
certain certain restrictions or that then
that that a post like i should have shorter
linguistic expressions ok so think of the
previous example that we saw in the last slide
the same sentence was having one thirty two
different interpretations
now what if i if if i need to have a different
sentence for each of this one to thirty two
a different interpretations that will make
by language expression really large and also
the language will become very complex so what
happens in language some sort of ambiguities
allowed but is ambiguity is some that is easily
resolvable ok so you cannot have an ambiguity
there is not resolvable at all so by some
sort of knowledge that you have human being
ah tries to resolve it ok but in in in the
case of n l p we try to we have we have this
starts for developing algorithm that kind
resolve this ambiguity ok so yes language
relies mostly on the peoples ability to use
their knowledge and some inference capabilities
to properly to resolve these ambiguities ok
so now so just a brief discussion on what
is the difference between a natural language
and a computer language as such so one of
one primary difference is the is is the ambiguity
ok in programming language is do not have
any ambiguity in so whenever you write a program
with will mean only one particular thing these
no ambiguity their but that is not the same
there is not true for the case of language
in natural language ok so so all the programming
languages are formal and they are designed
to be unambiguous so that you can have very
very efficient passing for that ok so they
can always you defined by a grammar that process
a unique parse for each sentence or each programming
construct in in the language ok that is not
true for the natural languages
so so you can have parsing in ne ne linear
time ok now why else is n l p hard ok so this
carton gives you some idea that i do not understand
the a word young people say these days ok
so so that so i am talking about social media
here so see you i will text you later ok the
the sentence see you i will text you later
now your writing is c u i will text u you
later ok so now now the the problematic hand
is to understand that that you have actually
meaning the sentence and find out a starting
from c u mean this c from you the you mean
this u and so on ok so so this is also called
the non standard use of english and that is
very very problem with the use of social media
all the s m s and other other plate forms
ok so let us see this particular tweet ok
so great job justin bieber we are so proud
of what you have accomplished you taught us
to never say never and you yourself should
never give up either ok so in this sentence
sees a tweet ok so what are the things that
you do not see in formal language so one example
here is mention the use of mention at justin
bieber so this mention is again wherever is
specific to tweet a and your using hash text
never say never is a single harsh text ok
what is so we are seeing constructs like this
you have is take is written as you have you
v e and to is remains two so this is again
non use of english that makes n l p difficult
ok then there are many other problems like
segmentation issue so i have the simple sentence
the new york new heaven railroad so based
by segment this particular sentence
especially new york new haven should i segmented
like that new york new haven or new york new
haven the second is the correct segmentation
ok so there are two possible segmentation
of the same sentence so problem would another
would be to find out what is the correct segmentation
given this sentence then there are other cases
like the case of idioms in in language ok
so so what happens in the case of idioms you
cannot construct the the meaning of the page
by looking at the meaning of the individual
words and trying compose them together so
if i see a idiom like dork horse i cannot
take the meaning of a horse which is dork
and make the meaning of this idiom dork house
is something else is a so this is some sort
of idiom that is conveyed for the person who
is not well known but he suddenly becomes
a dork a dork horse
so the he is suddenly excelling in in certain
field ok similarly you see this idiom ball
in your court ok doesn't mean the ball is
in your court that means the matrix at your
hand and now its similarly this idiom again
is again very much used burn the midnight
oil there is not mean that i am burning the
oil that midnight but what it means is that
your doing hard work ok then there are various
ah new words that have that have been floated
a new usages that are coming up ok so they
also called new logiest so for a one a particular
example so these are examples are taken from
social media is un friending ok i have some
face book friend and i am un friending ok
so this has become is is is a verb itself
retweet ok re tweet has been used a lot as
a work similar googles skype photoshop all
are very much used in as for i am googling
ok and all
so that creates another problem for n l p
that is new words are coming up and different
and and new a new usages to you do not have
a close vocabulary and vocabulary and your
vocabulary keeps on increasing then you you
you keep on getting new senses of the words
ok so this see this particular example thats
segued ok so n pointing here to the word sick
so what is the usual meaning of sick that
you see sick i will something that is not
hell the that is some one who is hill but
in this particular sentence thats sick dude
sick mean sick means something that is cool
and that we coming up with social media ok
similarly you see the word giants what is
the particular meaning of giants seasonally
we see giants as some sort of demons that
that we have in in storage
but recently some some new meaning of giants
is coming up so that you can think of like
some sort of giant multi nationals and all
that ok giant manufactures and then there
is a problem of entity names ok so take this
sentence where is a bugs life playing you
cannot understand the meaning of the sentence
un less you know that this particular utterance
a bugs life is single entity and then you
try to understand the meaning of the sentence
similarly the second sentence let it be was
recorded you need to understand that let it
be is single entity here ok so what we do
in n l p to handle all that so we need to
have some knowledge the language how the sentence
is a constructed what kind of words are their
and so on
we need to knowledge about the world ok and
many to have the way in which begin combined
various knowledge resources in an efficient
manner ok so how is it generally done so most
of the times we do it by using various probabilistic
models ok so this is the single simple example
here so i have word like image on in french
and may translated in english and there are
multiple interpretations so i want to use
a model that page the probability that image
on goes to house is high and i should choose
this particular interpretation ok similarly
for the next sentence suppose this is for
this speech recognition system whenever i
am saying saying i so a wend and they are
two interpretations i saw a wend or eyes ah
of n i should be able to say that the first
interpretation is more probable to occur in
the language then the second temptation ok
and and we will deal deal with this a lot
so many a times we have to extract lot of
text features that does most of this job ok
so fine so in this lecture we covered some
aspects of wild languages hard so in the next
lecture we will start talking about some of
the very very basic empirical large that we
see in language and we will start with doing
some basic pre processing ok