ok so welcome back for the forth lecture of
the first week so in the last lecture we discussed
why is then we had and we we took examples
of various cases of ambiguities in the language
and some non standard disease also ok so we
will actually go into a text corpus and try
to study some very simple empirical laws that
are very very universal about language ok
so now before going to that i will i will
try to make a simple distinction clear to
you so what are the difference between function
words versus content words in language so
whenever you see a language in it's vocabulary
there are various kinds of words and they
can be called either function words or content
words what are the difference between those
ok
so function words are mainly used to make
the sentence grammatically so things like
where is determine us a and ah and pronouns
and all are function words content words are
various nouns and verbs that convey what are
the important concepts in the sentence ok
so content words are mainly used for determining
the structure of the sentence so now this
is in this is your example to give you an
idea about what are content words and what
are function words
so you see here the same sentence as we written
in two different ways in the in one of the
cases we have replaced the content words by
some garbage words so this may dove words
that are not in the language
in the other in the other example we have
the function words by some arbitrary words
that are not in the language ok so can you
try to find out in which sentence we have
replaced the function words with something
else so we will see here in the second sentence
so we have removed the word like the and replaced
with words like glop ok and and so on in the
first sentence we have replaced all the nouns
like angry and investigator with winfy prunkilmonger
that is is research to the garbage word that
is not the language now
now try to see the two sentences and in which
sentence you can see the structure of the
sentence clearly and in which of the sentence
you can understand the topics of the sentence
clear and you will find out that in the second
sentence you know all the topics so we are
talking about some investigator government
and infuriated and all that ok the information
you cannot get from the first sentence when
in the first sentence you can understand the
extraction of the sentence the some x some
noun from something and a verb and again a
verb all which a noun and a adverb ok and
you do not know what are these nouns and adverbs
but you know what is the extraction of these
sentence do a certain filers in the in the
sense of various nouns and verbs
so in general function words in a language
are closed class words what i mean by that
there are very specific grammatically categories
that can be called as function words and they
they they are generally closed we do not have
newer and newer functions what coming into
a language ok some examples of function words
are like prepositions pronouns auxiliary verbs
conjunctions grammatical articles and various
particles in the language ok so now let us
take a take a corpus and try to see what are
the distribution of words that we encounter
in the corpus
so here we have taken tom saw sawyer so that
was a noble written by mark twain and what
we are doing in the slide we are just reporting
which of the words occur with what frequency
so this is a sorted list a starting from the
highest frequency to the to some top fifteen
twenty words and what is the grammatical category
ok so the top word you see here is the so
that occurs with the frequency of three thousand
three hundred thirty two and this is very
very common across different language corpus
ok so if you pick up any arbitrary language
corpus you will feel that the distribution
roughly is
so now till we have a look at this list and
find out what is special about this list what
is the category of words that you see here
so so so remember we talked about two categories
function words and content words can you try
to find out which of the category you see
here so we see most of the words here are
function words ok so the and a to of and you
can see also by the grammatical categories
that is also written here so so one thing
like that we see in this distribution is that
this list is dominated by the little words
of english that are that are very important
grammatical roles for for the sentence ok
now what is one exception that you see to
this so we call them function words that we
let me say a determine us prepositions complementizers
like the word that here so now what is one
exception that we see in this list so that
exception is probably the word tom so tom
is very specified to per topic of this text
ok so this is about tom sawyer so you see
the word tom also as a very high frequency
and this makes into the list of top frequent
words ok so so again if you take an arbitrary
text and try to find out some top frequent
words mostly they will be function words also
sometimes known as where is this top words
plus you can find some appearances of words
that come with the topic of that text so in
this that is a word tom
so let us try to see something else how many
words are there in this text what are the
various ah technical terms why which these
are indicated so for that we will talk about
the type token distinction so type token astrology
philosophical distinction between a concept
concept is a type and a particular instances
of the concept ok so concept is type and instance
is a concept are tokens
so what do i mean by typing token when it
comes to a language ok so a language if the
same word occurs multiple times ok so i call
them the same type the same type same concept
but different tokens ok so if i write the
same word say will will the same word twice
i say this is a single type this is only one
type but there are two tokens so each individual
occurrence is a different token but they have
the same type so in other sense by type i
mean some sort of unique words in my vocabulary
and token means the number of words they are
not unique so if the word occurs five times
i will count it as five different tokens but
the same type
now so once we have understood what is a distinction
between type and token there is a particular
concept that is called type token ratio that
is you should describe some text ok so what
is type token token ratio very simple the
ratio of the the number of types that is number
of different unique words to the number of
running words so all the tokens so you find
out the number of types in the text divided
by the number of tokens in the text and you
get the ttr type token ratio ok
so what this ratio indicates that tells on
an average how often a new word appears in
the text ok so if type divide by token that
is my type token ratio if it is high that
means in the text lot of new words are keep
on coming because the number of types is very
close to the number of token but if this is
small that means the small words are getting
repeated again and again in the corpus ok
so suppose we take two different text corpus
one is mark twains tom sawyer another we take
complete shakespeare work and we try to find
out what is the ttr for each of this so our
mark twains we find that there are seventy
one thousand three seventy word tokens and
eight thousand eighteen word types so how
do we complete ttr you just find out we just
divide types by tokens so eight thousand eighteen
divide by seventy one thousand three seventy
that will give me the ttr that is close to
point one one two
now if you take the shakespeare work you find
similarly there are eight eighty four thousand
plus tokens and twenty nine thousand plus
types and type ttr comes to be much more than
that of tom sawyer point zero three ok suppose
i take four different types of media so four
different types of media like conversations
if two people are conversing academic prose
will be scientific articles and books news
and fiction i take four different sorts of
media in which ah language is communicated
now can you try to have a have a guess which
one will have the highest ttr and which will
will have the lowest ttr
so so let us go to the definition of ttr so
if high ttr it will be tendency to use the
new words what what about low ttr if you have
low ttr that is tendency to use same word
repeatedly so now now given that so i have
four different ah media one are conversation
then i have academic prose then i have news
and fiction now which one do you think will
have the tendency to repeat the same word
again and again so we think over it in conversation
we try to repeat the same word again and again
so whatever you are conversing i will try
to take it from there and repeat it
so conversation have the tendency to use the
same word repeatedly so that means they will
have the lowest ttr ok on the other hand it
has been found in news you have tendency to
use newer words so news this is the highest
ok so can you can you guess which of the remaining
one will have the second lowest ttr where
the same words have been used repeatedly and
and that is actually the academic prose because
academic prose is very very formal so they
are very very particular kind of words and
verbs that that we use ok so that's why ttr
is again found to be low in academic prose
ok
so ttr is scores the lowest value in the case
of conversations and highest value in news
and the academic prose as the second lowest
ttr ok and this also make sense now one thing
you must be conscious about that ttr in in
itself is not a very valid measure of finding
text complexity ok you might say that ok if
ttr is high text might be complex but this
is not a valid measure in itself so why is
that so so think of this scenario if you are
using more and more text what would happen
to your ttr ratio ok suppose your text contains
you are taking a running text so till here
you have thirty thousand tokens
now you go forward in your text and you go
to sixty thousand tokens now what would you
guess can you see the ttr at this point it
will always be lower than the ttr at this
point yes because whatever words were there
in the corpus most the words have already
been introduced in the in the first half second
half most of the words will be again getting
repeated ok so the number of tokens will increase
linearly with the size of text but number
of words in a vocabulary do not ok
so that's why if i take say a tom sawyer versus
shakespeares works you will see the ttr is
high in tom sawyer than shakespeare work because
they since having a much larger number of
tokens so when it in itself it cannot be a
valid measure so when you take into account
the size of the text so another way in which
this is computed is by taking a running average
ok so you take a running average on some consecutive
thousand word chunks so what i mean by running
average suppose i have a text that as five
thousand tokens
so now you first compute ttr for the initial
thousand tokens one to thousand ok get a ttr
for that now you take start from two to thousand
one i didnt have ttr three to thousand two
compute ttr and then take an average so you
compute ttr on moving window of thousand length
thousand and then you take an average
so that is considered to be a better of a
ttr ok so now so you see that we will talk
about some empirical laws so for that let
us try to have a look at some of the frequency
distribution that we see in tom sawyer ok
so remember we we said that the ttr on tom
sawyer is roughly point one one so what does
it indicate it says that on an average here
what is repeated nine times yes try to token
ratio is one by nine roughly
now what is that mean does that mean that
each word occurs nine times in the text or
is it something different so what we see saying
saying here that words do not have a very
even distribution it is not happen that each
word occurs nine times in the text so what
is the usual kind of distribution that we
see in the corpus ok
so on the left in the left hand side of the
slide so you see i have two columns first
column gives me the word frequency second
column gives me frequency of frequency what
do i mean by frequency of frequency how many
words in this corpus have that frequency ok
so take the first row that means there are
three thousand nine hundred ninety three words
in the corpus that occur only once they have
frequency one and there are twelve hundred
ninety two words in the corpus that occur
twice and so on
similarly there are hundred and two words
in the corpus that occur more than hundred
times ok so now once you see this statistic
then immediately see that the distribution
is not very very uniform ok so what are the
two different observations that we have here
ok so first observation that we make are most
words are real so which are the real words
the words that occur with frequency one or
two so we see here roughly fifty percent of
the word types remember in tom sawyer roughly
eight thousand what else where their so roughly
fifty percent of them occur only once so there
were frequency of one and they are also called
happax legomena ok so that is a greek term
for read only once they occur only once in
my corpus
what is the other observations that we have
hundred words account for fifty one percent
of all the tokens of all text so you had only
hundred and two words here that were higher
frequency greater than hundred but the together
account for fifty percent of two of the corpus
so this is again a strange so now this particular
observation gives the first empirical law
that we will study that is called zipfs law
ok so very very popular law in in the case
of language corpus how the vocabulary is the
distribution behave ok so you see zipfs law
what do we need to do first take a large corpus
ok now take find out what are the individual
word types and count the frequency of each
word type ok
now what you need to do you list the word
types in their decreasing order of frequency
ok so for example suppose in the previous
case we found there are various types like
the an and tom and so on in the corpus i will
find out the frequency so this occurs with
four thousand frequency this occurs with thousand
this occurs with say two thousand and this
occurs with thousand five hundred and so on
there are various first occur occurring the
different frequencies
now the first thing i will do i will try to
sort them in the decreasing order so first
i will have the then i will have and then
i have tom then i will have an and so on all
that the words in the vocabulary so they will
have their frequency this is four thousand
one thousand sorry two thousand one thousand
five hundred and thousand now i will give
you then the ranks ok because i have already
sorted in decreasing order i put the rank
so there is this rank one rank two rank three
rank four and so on ok
so now what is zipf law say so zipf law gives
me a relationship between the frequency of
a word the f in this list and the rank of
this word ok in this sorted list and what
is the relation that zipf law gives a relation
is very very easy so relation is the frequency
is inversely proportional to the rank of the
word ok so inversely ratio between the frequency
and the rank so that is i can say that if
i multiple f dot r i will get some sort of
the constant f dot r is a constant this is
for our arbitrary example that we took in
this case we can even see that this holds
so four thousand into one is so this is four
thousand this is again four thousand this
is four thousand five hundred and this four
thousand they are roughly the same ok so what
it means suppose i make a list like that and
i have two words
so i have a word with as a rank of fifty and
remember that as a rank of one fifty and i
find it's frequency f one it's frequency f
two so i can see that f one is three times
f two so f one is three times f two ok so
the fiftieth most count word should occur
with three times the frequency of the one
fiftieth most convert ok this is what zipf
laws tells me we can write it in also a different
manner so we talked about frequency we can
also talk about probability ok so let p r
denote the probability of a word with rank
r
so what is pr pr is nothing but frequency
of the word word of rank r divide by the number
of tokens that i seen the corpus that's how
i will compute the probability of that so
n is the total number of word account says
tokens ok so what does zipf law tell so it
says frequency is inversely proportion to
r i can also write f divide by n with some
a by r ok so what i have done i taken the
constant k i have written that it as a times
n ok n is a number of tokens in my vocabulary
n a is from other constant and it's fixed
given a corpus and using in the constant so
now what why we are doing that because it
as been seen in that in the corpus a's when
we take a valid close to point one ok this
is generally more fix than the value of k
ok
so now going back to the a jumble of tom sawyer
let us take some words their frequency and
their rank and see whether the relation that
f dot r is roughly constant holds to it ok
what you are seeing here so we have arrays
words like the and he there and so on we have
written their frequencies and their ranks
and what is f dot r so what the what we are
seeing here f dot r if you start form the
forth word say he this remains roughly in
the same range ok is start it remains in eight
thousand to some ten thousand four hundred
and two hundred ok it does not the range does
not vary a lot
so that is very nice empirical evidence that
zipf law holds and let us see we will see
in various corpus that f dot r remains constant
from most of the words that you will see ok
so now so zipf law is one of the very very
important law so that we have just see but
zipf as given some other laws also there are
not so popular but still we will is try to
have a look quick look at this so one of the
laws is relating the number of means a word
as with it's frequency so what this law says
so the number of meanings m that a word as
obeys the simple law that m is proportion
to the a square of roots it's frequency
so that is as i as we have words with higher
and higher frequencies the number of the different
sansage or the meanings will which they can
be used also increases ok so now if i use
it with the first law so what do we get so
the first law says that frequency is inversely
proportional to the rank this is law one and
the second law says the meanings are directly
proportional to the as a square root of frequency
this is law two if we combine these two laws
together we can get meaning r inversely proportional
to the rank of that ok so that means if i
if i put the words in the decreasing order
of your rank so you are starting from rank
one to rank two and so on
so now so they mean number of meanings will
also keep on decreasing so these clause hold
an average ok what is the empirical support
so as i were saying the hold on an average
so if we saw the words that are having rank
roughly close to ten thousand so they have
roughly two two point one meanings if their
words that are having rank roughly five thousand
they are found to have roughly three meanings
and the words that are having having rank
plus two thousand they were having roughly
four point six meanings ok and you can do
the math and you will find out this roughly
ah this roughly follows whatever we have seen
in this law ok
and these are the law by zipf that tries to
correlate the length of the word that means
the number of characters the word as with
the the frequency of the word and it says
the frequencies of the word is inversely proportional
to it's length ok and in can you try to see
that in the case of english so the very very
long words are very very really used so their
frequency is very very small but some of the
very small words like examples like function
words they are used very very often and that
also make sense because language is used for
having some efficient communication ok so
you cannot have long words that are very very
common then you will have to write a lot ok
so the words that are very very common are
generally short ok
so we talked about zipfs law now so for doing
the processing of language what is the impact
of zipfs law so we said there is a good part
in the and there is a bad part so what is
a good part so in the language we saw that
so remember there were two important observations
that we made from a zipf law what was those
so one observation was that fifty percent
of the vocabulary that means the types occur
only once so they are very rare rare words
and this is most words are rare words this
fifty percent of the words occur only once
and what is the their observation you say
that roughly hundred roughly words account
for fifty percent of the tokens ok so that
is from common words are very very common
they occur they occur a lot so words are very
common ok they of fifty percent of your text
so now given these observations what do you
think is the good part what is a bad part
when it comes to an end ok so so this is a
bad part ok why is it the bad part so what
it says is is that a fifty percent of my words
in the vocabulary they can only once so it
is not easy for me to gather some statistics
to do some meaning analysis so there are only
once let's all the knowledge i have about
these words ok so that's why this is called
the bad part i cannot do lot of modeling for
these words and the other part that hundred
roughly hundred words account for fifty percent
of token it's we call sometimes the good part
why because for most of the analysis you can
always remove these words and so will reduce
you total number of tokens by half so we will
have to process roughly half of the text because
how the text is simply these stop words and
the function words ok
so that's what i we mean meant here the good
part is that the stop words account for a
large fraction of text thus they eliminate
if i eliminate the stopwords it reduces the
size of my text roughly by half and the bad
part is most of the words are extremely rare
and it is very very difficult to gather data
to some meaningful analysis with each words
ok so now so we will talk about one more law
here so that is the relation between the size
of my vocabulary and the number of tokens
in my text ok so so that is how does the size
of my vocabulary go with the size of my corpus
ok so we talked about type token ratio so
that is one sort of analysis that we can do
but that does not give me a particular law
so what will be the rough distribution their
rough relationship between them ok
so we have heaps law they tries with the relationship
between the size of my vocabulary that we
call as v and the number of tokens n what
this law says that it gives a symbol relationship
it says the size of my vocabulary is some
constant times k n is a number of tokens to
the power beta and the ranges are also observing
the corpus so k has been found to be roughly
in the range of ten to hundred although this
can vary this is our roughly this as been
found to be in this range and beta is very
close to the square root so it is found in
the range of point four to point six
so what it says so vocabulary generally grows
as for the a square root of the number of
tokens so that also make sense remember we
are talking about what if i keep on teaching
my vocabulary i will tend to use the sorry
keep on teaching my tokens i will tend to
use the same word again and again so number
of unique tokens or unique types in each roughly
to the square root of my ah corpus size ok
so what is some sort of empirical evidence
for that so so here so there are four different
corpus that has been taking care of taken
taken so like moisture wsj and there are some
other different new corpus and what what this
plot shows on the x axis you have the words
in collection in millions
so how many words in my collection so there
are ten million twenty million thirty million
forty million on the y axis it is showing
the number of words in a vocabulary in thousand
so twenty fifty thousand hundred thousand
hundred fifty thousand and so on and the plot
so the relationship between the vocabulary
and the number of tokens and you see at the
plot shows roughly is square root behaviour
ok and this as been found to to match with
whatever he proposed so this is again an empirical
law that is very very universal to the language
ok so that's for this lecture and in the next
lecture we will start talking about some actual
task related to the preprocessing of the corpus
thank you