hello everyone welcome back to the final lecture
of the first week so in the last lecture we
were discussing about various empirical laws
so in particular zipfs law and heaps law that
how the whats the vocabulary are distributed
in a corpus ok and we say that the distribution
is not very uniform there was certain words
that are very very common so we saw that roughly
hundred hundred words in the vocabulary made
for fifty percent of the corpus that by the
time mean that number of tokens and on the
other hand there are fifty percent who have
words in the in the vocabulary that occur
only once ok and we discussed whatever various
relationships from among the numb the my vocabulary
size and the number of tokens that i observe
in a corpus and also how they grow with respect
to each other and zipfs law gives gave me
a relation between the frequency and the rank
of a word
so today in this lecture we will start with
the basic key processing in in language so
we will cover the the basic concepts and what
are the challenges that one might face while
doing the processing ok so we are going to
the basics of text processing ok so we will
start with the problem of tokenization as
the name would suggest ok remember the name
token token is an individual word in my corpus
so now what happens when i am preprocessing
the text in given in any language what i will
face is a string of characters the sequence
of characters now i need to indentify what
are all the different words that are there
in this in this sequence
so now tokenization is a process by which
i convert the string of characters into sequence
of various words so i am trying to segment
it by the various words that i am observing
ok so now before going into what is tokenization
i will just talk about a slightly related
problem sentence segmentation ok so this you
may or may not have to do always and it depends
on what is your application so for example
suppose you are doing classification for the
whole document in to certain classes you might
not have to go to the individual sentence
and you can just talk about what are the various
words that are present in in this document
on the other hand suppose you are trying to
find out what are the important sentences
in this document in that application you will
have to go to the individual sentence so now
if you have to go to the individual sen sentence
the first task that you will face is how do
i segment these whole document into a sequence
of sentences ok so this is sentence one one
sentence two and so on and this task is called
sentence segmentation
so now you might feel that this is very trivial
task but let us see is it trivial ok so what
is sentence segmentation it's a problem of
deciding where my sentence begins and ends
so that i have a complete unit of words that
that i call as a sentence now do you think
there might be certain challenges involved
suppose i am talking about the language english
can i always say that wherever i have a dot
it is the end of the sentence let us see
so there are many ways in which i can end
my sentence so i can have exclamation or question
mark that ends the sentence and they are mostly
unambiguous so whenever i have a exclamation
or question mark i can say probably this is
the end of the sentence but is the case the
same with a dot so i can think of a scenario
where i have a dot in english and but its
not the end of the sentence so we can find
all sorts of abbreviations right they end
with a period like doctor mister mph ok so
you have three dots here so you cannot each
of there this as the end of your sentence
so again you have numbers two point four four
point three and so on so that means the problem
of deciding whether a particular dot is the
end of the sentence or not is not entirely
trivial so i need to build certain algorithm
for finding out is it my end of the sentence
ok so in in text processing we we face this
kind of problem in nearly every every simple
every simple task that we are doing ok so
even if it looks a trivial task we face with
this problem that ok can i always call dot
as a end of the sentence
so how do we go about solving this now if
you think about it whenever i see a dot or
question mark or exclamation i always have
to decide one of the two things is it the
end of the sentence or is not the end of the
sentence ok so any data point that i am seeing
i have to divide into one of these two classes
ok so if you call think of these as two classes
end of the sentence or not end of the sentence
so each point you have to divide into one
of the two classes and this in general this
problem in general is called classification
problem ok you are classifying into one of
the two classes
now so the idea is very very sim simple so
you have two classes and each data point you
have to divide into one of the two classes
so that means you have to build some sort
of plural algorithm for doing that so in this
case i have to build the binary classifier
what they mean by a binary classifier there
are two classes end of the sentence or not
end of the sentence in general there can be
multiple classes
so now for each dot or in general for every
word i need to decide whether this is the
end of the sentence or not the end of the
sentence so in general my classifica[tion]-
classifiers that i will build can be some
rules that i write by hand ok some simple
if the nice rules or it can be some expressions
i say my particular example matches with this
set of expressions it is one plus if i doesn't
match it is a class or i can build a machine
learning classifier so in this particular
scenario what can be the simplest thing to
do let us see can we build a simple rule based
classifier
so so we we will start with a example of a
simple decision tree so by decision tree i
mean a set of if and i say statements ok so
i am at a particular word i want to decide
whether this is the end of the sentence or
not ok
ok so i can have the simple if then else kind
of decision tree here so met a word and i
the first thing i check is are there lots
of blank lines after that so this would happen
in a text whenever this is the end of the
a paragraph and there are some blank lines
so if you i feel that there are a lot of blank
lines after after me that means after this
word i may say ok this might be the end of
the sentence with a good confidence so that's
why the branch here says yes this is the end
of the sentence but suppose there are not
lot of blank blank lines then i will check
if the final punctuation is a question mark
exclamation or a colon in that case ok so
there are quite unambiguous and i may say
this is the end of the sentence
now suppose it is not then i will check if
the final punctuation is a period so if it
is a period if it is not a period this is
easy easy to say that this is not the end
of the sentence but suppose this is a end
of this is a period so again i cannot say
for certain if it is the end of the sentence
so i give a again check for simplicity i might
have a list of abbreviations and i can check
if the word that i am correcting facing is
one of the abbreviations in my list if it
is there i say ok this is not end of the sentence
if it is so here i am etcetera or any other
abbreviation if the answer is yes i am not
end of the sentence if the answer is no that
means this word is not an abbreviation and
this will be the end of the sentence this
is very very simple
if then else rule rules ok this may not be
correct but this is one particular ah way
in which this problem can be solved in general
you might want to use some other sort of indications
we call them as various features these are
various observations that you make from your
corpus ok so what are some examples ok so
suppose i see the word that is ending with
dot can i use this as a feature whether my
word starts with an upper case lower case
cap all caps or is it number ok
how will that help so let us see i have here
i am here and my word is four point three
so i am at dot i want to find out if it is
the end of the sentence if i can say that
the previous the current word is a number
it's an high probability that this will be
in number and it will not be the end of the
sentence so this can be used as an another
feature ok
so again by feature you can think of a simple
rule whether the word i am currently at is
a number ok or i can use the fact where as
the case of the word with dot its upper case
or lower case so you so what happens generally
in abbreviations we are mostly in upper case
so suppose i have doctor and it starts with
an upper case ok i can say that this might
be an application ok
saying with the lower case lower case will
give me more probability that this is not
an abbreviation similarly i can also use in
the case of the word after dot ok so is it
upper case lower case capital or number so
how will that help so again whenever i have
the end of the sentence the next word in general
starts with a capital so again this can be
used what can be some other features so i
can have some numerical features so that is
i will have certain thresholds what is the
length of the word ending with dot is it if
the length is small it might be an abbreviation
if the length is larger it might not be an
abbreviation ok and i can also use probably
the what is the probability that the word
that is ending with dot occurs at the end
of the sentence ok so if it is really the
end of the sentence it might happen then that
in a large corpus this end sentence quite
often same thing i I can do with the next
word after dot is it the start of the sentence
what is the probability that it occurs in
the start of the sentence in a large corpus
ok so you might be able to use any of these
features to decide given a particular word
is it the end of the sentence or not ok so
now suppose i ask you this question do you
have the same problem in other languages like
hindi so in hindi you will see that in general
there is only agenda that you use to indicate
the end of the sentence and this is not used
for any other purpose so this problem you
will see is again language depen dependent
this problem is there for english but not
so for hindi but you will see there are other
problems that do no exist for english language
but are there for other indian languages ok
we will see some of the those examples in
the same branch ok
now so how do we implement a decision tree
so as you have seen this is simple if then
else statement ok so now what is important
is that you choose the correct set of features
so how do you go about choosing the set of
features we see in your from your data what
are some observations that can separate my
two classes here so my two classes here are
end of the sentence and non the end of the
sentence and what are the observations we
were having ok in general it might be an abbreviation
in the case of the word and that is before
the dot maybe upper case or lower case and
one of these might indicate one plus the other
might indicate other plus so all these are
my observations that i use as my features
now whenever i am using a numerical features
like the length of the word before dot i need
to pick some sort of threshold ok that is
whether the length of the word is between
two to three or say more than three between
five to seven like that so my tree can be
if the length of the word is between five
to seven i could one plus otherwise i could
another another plus
ok so now here is one problem suppose i keep
on increasing my features it can be both ah
numerical or non numerical features it might
be difficult to set up my if then else rules
by hand so in that scenario i can try to use
some sort of machine learning technique to
learn this decision tree ok in in the literature
there are lot of such ah algorithms available
that given a data and a set of features we
will construct a decision tree for you ok
so i will just give you so the names of some
of the algorithms and the basic idea on this
they work is that so at every point we have
to choose a particular subject ok so you have
to choose a feature value that it splits my
data into certain parts and i have certain
criteria to find out what is the best way
to split so one particular criteria is what
is the information given by this ok so these
algorithm that we have mentioned here like
i d three c four point five point cart they
all use one of these criterions ok
in general once you have identified what are
your interesting features for these task you
are not limited to only one classifier a decision
tree you can also try out some other classifiers
like support vector machines logistic regression
and neural networks these all these are quite
popular classifiers for various mbb applications
so we will talk about some of these as we
will go to some some advanced topics in this
course
ok now coming back to our problem tokenization
ok we said that tokenization is a process
of segmenting a string of charac characters
into words finding out what are the different
words in this question now remember we talked
about token and type distinction suppose i
give you a simple sentence here i have a can
opener but i cant open these cans how many
tokens are there if you count there are eleven
different words eleven different occurrences
of words so you have eleven word tokens but
how many unique words are there so you will
find there are only ten unique words ok which
word repeats is the word i repeats twice so
there are ten types and eleven tokens so my
tokenization is to find out each of the eleven
word tokens from the sentence
in practice at least for english you can use
certain toolkits that are available like nltk
in python corenlp in java and you can you
can also use the unix commands so in this
course you will mainly be using nltk toolkit
for doing all the pre processing task and
in some other ah tasks as well ok but in general
you can use any of these three ah possibilities
so for english most of the the the problems
that we will see are taken care of the tokenizers
tokenizers that we have discussed previously
ok but still it is good to know what are the
challenges that are involved when i have i
tried to design a tokenization algorithm ok
see for example here you will see that it
have if i encounter a word like finlands in
my data so one question that i have is whether
i treat it as simple finland as it is finlands
or i I convert it to finlands by removing
the apostrophe ok so this question you might
also try to defer to the next processing step
that you will see but sometimes you might
want to tackle this in the same stuff ok
similarly if you see what are do i treat it
as a single token or two tokens what are this
trouble you might have to solve in the same
step whether i treat it as a single token
or multiple tokens same with i am shouldn't
and so on similarly whenever your name end
at each like san francisco should i treat
it as a single token or two separate tokens
now remember when we were talking about some
of the cases why and page hard so you might
have to find out that this particular sequence
of tokens is a single entity and treat it
as a single entity not as multiple different
tokens ok so this problem is related similarly
if you find m dot p dot h whether you call
it a single token or multiple tokens
so now there are no fixed answers to to these
and some of these might depend on what is
the application for which you are doing this
pre processing ok but one thing you can always
keep in mind suppose you are doing if for
the application of information trivial if
the same sort of steps that you apply for
your documents should be applied to your query
as well otherwise you will not be able to
match them perfectly ok so suppose if i am
using it for information trivial so i should
use the same convention for both both my documents
as well as the queries
ok so then another problem can be how do i
handle hyphens in my day ok this looks again
a simple problem but we we will see its not
that simple so let us see some kind of examples
what are the various sorts of hypens that
can be there in my corpus
so here i have a sentence from a research
paper abstract and the sentence says this
paper describes mimic an adaptive mixed initiative
spoken dialogue system that provides movie
show time information ok so in this sentence
itself you see two different hyphens one is
with initiative initiative another is show
hyphen time ok
so now can you see that these two are different
hyphens the first hyphen is not in general
that i will i will use in in my text ok second
hyphen i can used in my text i can write show
time with an hyphen but how did this hyphen
initiative came into the corpus ok so re so
we have given this a title end of line hyphen
so what happens in research papers for example
whenever you write a sentence you might have
to do some sort of justification and that's
where you end the line even if is not the
end of this of of the word so you will you
will end up with an hyphen ok so now when
you are trying to pre process and when you
are retrieving such kind of hyphens you might
have to join these together and we should
we have to say that this is a single word
initiative and not initial hyphen tive ok
but again this is this is not trivial because
for show time you will not do the same show
time you might want to keep it as it is
then there are some other kind of hyphens
like lexical hyphens so you might have these
hyphens with ah various prefixes like co pre
meta multi etcetera sometimes they are sententially
determined hyphen hyphens also that is they
put so that it becomes easier to interpret
these angles like here case based hand delivered
etcetera are optional similarly if you see
in the next sentence three to five year direct
mark marketing plan ok three to five year
can be written perfectly without keeping the
hyphens but here you are putting it so that
it becomes easier to interpret that particular
occurrence
so again when you are doing tokenization your
problem that how do i handle all these hyphens
further there are various issues that might
that you might face for certain languages
but not others so for an example like in french
if you have a token like lensemble so you
might want to match it with ensemble ok so
that might be a similar problem that we are
facing in english but let us take something
in german ok so i have this i have this big
sentence here
ok but the problem is that this is not a single
word this is a compound composed of four different
words and the corresponding english meaning
is this one so your four words in in english
so when you are putting in in french they
make a compound
so now what is the problem that you will face
when you are processing the a german text
and you are trying to tokenize it so you might
want to find out what are the individual ah
words in this particular compound so you need
some sort of compound split up for example
ok so this problem is there for german not
so much for english
ok so now what happens if i am making a language
like chinese or japanese ok so here is a sentence
in chinese so what do you see in chinese words
are written without any spaces in between
ok so now when you are doing the pre processing
your task is to find out what are the individual
word tokens in these chinese sentence so this
problem is also difficult because in general
for a given utterance of a sequence of characters
there might be more than one possible ways
of breaking into sequence of words and both
might be perfectly valid possibilities ok
so in chinese we will not have not have any
space between words and i have to find out
what are the places where i have to break
each ah words and this problem is called tokenization
word tokenization same problem happens with
japenese and h[ere]- for the complications
because they are are using four different
steps like katakana hiragana kanji and romaji
so these problems becomes a bit more serious
now the same problem is there even for sanskrit
ok so if some of you have taken a sanskrit
course in in your class eighth or tenth so
you might be familiar with the the rules of
sandhians in sanskrit language ok
so that is it this is a simple single sentence
in sanskrit but this is a huge this looks
like a sing single word it is not a single
word it is composed of multiple words in sanskrit
and they are combined with a sandi relation
ok in this is stands for pro proverb in nice
proverb in sanskrit that translates in english
as one should tell the truth one should say
kind words one should neither tell harsh truths
not flat flattering lies this is a rule for
all times this is a this is a proverb
and this is a single sentence that talks about
this proverb but there all the words are combined
with sandhi relation so if we try to undo
the sandhi this is what you will find at the
segmented text ok so there are multiple words
in this in this sentence they are combined
to make a si make a single it looks like a
single word
now so this problem we saw in chinese japenese
and sanskrit but in sanskrit the problem is
slightly more complicated and why is that
so in in japense and and in chinese when you
try to combine various words together you
simply concatenate them you put them one after
another without without making any changes
at the boundary it doesnt happen in sanskrit
when you combine two words you also make certain
changes at the boundary and this is called
the sandhi operation ok
so in this particular case since see here
i have the word bruyat and the word na but
when i am combining i am i am writing it bruyanna
so you see here the the the letter t gets
changed to n ok so that means when i am trying
to analyze the sentence so this particular
sentence in sanskrit i need to find out not
only what are the breaks but what is the corresponding
word from which this sentence you derived
so from here to find out the the actual sen
words are bruyat lesna that gives give me
this bruyat and this is very very common in
sanskrit that you are always combining words
by doing a sandhi operation so this further
complicates my problem of word segments word
tokenization or segmentation
ok so this is just a list from wikipedia what
are the longest words in various languages
then note this sentence is about the words
you see in sanskrit the longest word is composed
of four thirty one characters is a compound
and then you have greek and afrikaans and
and other languages in english you will see
that the longest word is of forty five characters
is non scientific
so what is the the particular word in in sanskrit
that is composed of four thirty one letters
so this was from the varadambika parinaya
campu by tirumalamba ok this is a single compound
from his from his book
ok so now when i talk about this problem of
tokenization in sanskrit or in english this
problem is also called word segmentation have
a sequence of characters and you segment it
to find out individual words now what is the
simplest algorithm that you can think of let
lets take as in the case of chinese ok so
the simplest algorithm that works is a greedy
algorithm that is called maximum matching
algorithm so whenever you are given a string
you start you point to it at the beginning
of the string now suppose that you have the
dictionary and the words that you are that
you are currently seeing all should be in
the in the dictionary
so you will find out what is the maximum match
as per my dictionary in the string you break
there and put the pointer from at the next
character and again do the same thing so so
this greedily chooses what are actual words
by taking the maximum matches and this works
nicely for most of the cases ok
now so so this related question now can you
think of some cases where the segmentation
will also be required for the english text
in english in general we do not combine words
to make a single single word ok we do not
do that but what is the scenario where we
we are doing that right now ok so does do
hash tags come into mind so for example suppose
i have hash tags like thank sachin and music
monday so here different words are combined
together without putting a boundary in between
so if you are given a hash tag and you have
to analyze that you have to actually segmented
in into various words ok now so when i talk
about sanskrit so so so this we have a segment
to available at the site sanksrit dot inria
dot fr so we will just briefly see what is
the design principle of building a segmentor
in sanskrit so first we have a geometry model
that says how do i generate a sentence in
sanskrit i have a finite alphabet sigma ok
that means a set a set of various characters
in sanskrit now from this finite alphabet
i can generate a lot words ok that are composed
of various number of ah phonemes or all letters
from this alphabet
now when i have a set of words i can now combine
them together with an operation of sandhi
thats what i mean by sigma star here here
ok so w star here so i have a set of words
w and i will do a kleene closure that means
i can combine any number of words together
but whenever i am combining words i am doing
them by a sandhi operation this is the relation
between the words
so so i have my set of inflected words also
called padas in sanskrit and i have the relation
of sandhi between them and thats how i generate
sentences but the problem is how do i analyze
them so that is the inverse problem that is
whenever i am given a sentence w i have to
analyze it by inverting the relations of sandhi
so that i can produce a finite set of word
forms w one to w n ok and i am saying together
with the proofs so that is a formal way of
saying that but what i mean is that w one
to w n whenever they combine by sandhi operation
they give me the actual sandhis the initial
sandhis ok
so thats how the segment is segment is built
now this is a snapshot from from the segmentor
so i gave the same sentence there and and
it gave me all the possible ways of analyzing
the sandhis and it it says that there are
one twenty different solutions ok
so here whenever i have bruyana so you see
there are two possibilities bruyat and bruyam
thats ok like that it gives me all the possible
ways in which this sentence can be broken
into individual word tokens now this is another
problem that i will have to find out what
is the most likely word sequence among all
these one twenty possibilities but we can
use many many different models that we will
not talk talk about in this lecture probably
in some some other lectures
ok so coming back to normalization so so we
talked about this problem that the same word
might be doing multiple different ways like
u dot s dot a versus usa now i should be able
to match them together ok especially if you
are doing information retrieval we are giving
a query and you are retrieving from some document
suppose your query contains u dot s dot a
if the document contains usa if you are only
doing the surface able match you will not
be able to map on to each other so that so
so you will have to consider this problem
in advance and do the pre processing accordingly
of either your documents or the query but
using the same sort same sentence
so what i what we are doing by this we are
defining some sort of equivalence classes
we are saying usa and u dot s dot a should
go to one class and the other same type we
also do some sort of case folding that is
we can reduce all the letters to lower case
so whenever i have the word like ah w o r
d i will always write small w o r d so that
whenever even if it is starting the sentence
and it occurs in capitals because of that
in general i know that this is a word word
w o r d but this is not a generic rule sometimes
depending on application you might have certain
exceptions for example you might put treat
the name and it is separately so if you have
a entity general motors you might want to
keep it as it is without case folding
similarly you might want to keep us fortunate
districts in upper case and not do the case
folding and this is important for the application
of machine transition also because if you
do a case folding here you will know u s in
lower case that means something else versus
u s that is in united states excuse me
we also have the problem of lemmatization
that is you have individual individual words
like am are is and you want to convert them
to their lemma that means what is the base
form from which they are derived similarly
car cars cars cars so all these are derived
from car so again this is some sort of normalization
we are saying all these are some sort of equivalence
class because they come from the same word
from
so in the the problem of lemmatization is
that you have to find out the actual dictionary
head word from which they have derived ok
and for that we use morphology ok so what
is morphology i am trying to find out the
structure of word by seeing what is the particular
stem the headword and what is the affix that
is applied to it ok so these individual units
are called various morphemes ok
so so you have a stems that are the hybrids
and the affixes that are what are the different
units like s for plural etcetera you are applying
to them to make the individual word ok so
my examples are like for prefix you have un
anti etcetera for english and a ati pra etcetera
for hindi or sanskrit suffix like ity ation
etcetera and taa ka ke etcetera for hindi
and in general you can also have some infix
like you have the word like vid and you can
infix n in between this is in sanskrit so
we will discuss in detail about it in morphology
later
so so there is another concept you have lemmatization
where you are finding the actual dictionary
headword so there is also a concept called
stemming where you do not try to find the
actual dictionary headword but you just try
to remove certain ah suffixes ok and you opt
whatever you obtain is called a stem so this
a crude chopping of various affixes in that
in that word ok so this is again language
dependent so what we are doing here words
like automate automatic automation all will
be reduced to a single ah lemma automatically
so this is stemming so you know the actual
lemma is automate with an e but here so i
am just chopping off the affixes at the end
so i am removing here this ic ion all and
putting it to automate ok so this is one example
so if you try to do a stemming here see you
will find from example e is removed from compressed
it is removed and so on so what is the algorithm
that is used for for this stemming so we have
the porters algorithm that is very very famous
and this is again some since set of if then
else rules ok so what are some examples here
so what is the first step i take a word if
it ends with sses i remove es from there and
i end with ss so example is caresses goes
to caress if not then i see whether the words
end with ies i put it to i like ponies goes
to poni ok if not i see if the word ends with
ss i keep it as ss if not i see if the word
ends with s i remove that s ok cats goes goes
to cat but k caress does not go to caress
with with only one s because this is step
comes before if there is a double s and in
the word i re written it otherwise if there
is a single s i remove it that
like that there are some other steps so if
there is a vowel in the sen in the in my word
and the word ends with ing i remove ing so
walking goes to walk but what about king you
see in k there is no vowel so king will be
writtened as it is same is a vowel and there
is an ed i remove this ed and i have this
word played to play
so you can see that vo what is the use of
this heuristic of having this vowel if you
didn't have this vowel you would have converted
king to k ok and like that there are some
other ways like if the word ends with ational
then i will put it put ate so rational so
relational to relate and if the words end
with word ends with izer i convert i remove
that r digitizer to digitize ator to ate and
if the word ends with al i remove that al
if the word ends with able i remove that able
if the word ends with ate i remove that ate
ok so like that these are some steps that
i take from my corpus from each word i I converted
to its step ok it does not give me the correct
dictionary headword but still this this is
a good practice in principle for information
retrieval ok if you want to match the query
with the documents
so this is for this week so next week we will
start with another pre processing task that
is a spelling correction ok
thank you