ok so welcome back to the second week of this
course so last week we handed with the with
some the concept in pre processing of the
text ok so so what are the concept that we
covered we covered given is is sentence or
document in general a text document how do
i cyber into into a sentences how do a segment
into words we saw what are the spec specific
issues that might arise because of various
languages and we talked about normalization
case folding and other aspects like lamentation
stability ok so these are some very very standard
pre processing tasks that you might have to
do on on a given text in in a given language
ok but there is another task that you might
have to do certain in in certain cases if
the the data that you are obtaining is a bit
noisy what i mean noisy there are certain
spelling errors and you want to correct them
for doing your ana analysis so this task is
called spelling correction so what are the
various ah problems that i involve in spelling
correction and what are the different algorism
that we will be using so we will be start
with the very very simple algorithm of how
do use at the distance for spelling correction
in this particular lecture ok
so what is the problem of start a spelling
correction suppose you are you are reading
or you are seeing the text in your data and
the sentence is i am writing on behalf of
but in behalf you see only b e h a f and the
l is l is missing so now you want to correct
this particular word to the actual word behalf
now what is the auto what is the algorithm
approach of of solving this problem ok so
in general if you see this word like behalf
so ideally we want want to find out what are
the closest words in english that might come
in place of this ok so what are the words
you can think of i can think of probably behalf
and i can think of probably behave yes and
they might be some other words
now so when i will talk we talking about spelling
correction i will talk about two different
scenarios one is isolated word error correction
that is i am trying to correct a word that
is incorrect but i am not trying to use the
context around it so given the word b e h
a f i want to correct it without choosing
what is there before and after this word and
this is call isolated word error detection
so now so in this approach i will try to fin
find the word that are closest to behalf ok
you see maybe behalf and behave to will be
two words now so immediately i have a i have
a problem so how do i define what what is
what do i mean by closest ok so ideally we
say ok where you haven some sort of match
between this word and that word but how do
i further define it so i need some sort of
distance metric how do i major distance between
one word to another word and as per this metric
whichever two words are coming out to be closer
will be called as closest if there are coming
to far i will not even consider that as a
cand candidate for the correction so i really
want a distance matter that that can give
me the b e h a f and b e h a l l f are very
very closed together so so we will start and
we will actually use this the the metric called
edit distance and this one of the simplest
metric that we can think of in this case now
what is edit distance ok so what is my problem
i am given two strings ok in general i am
given two strings one that is incorrect another
might be correct and i have to find out what
is the minimum distance between these two
strings ok so ah
so thats what i want to define by my concept
of edit distance now how is defined so minimum
edit distance is defined as the minimum number
of edit operations that i have to do for going
from one strings to another ok as a name say
edit distance how many edits your making to
go from one string to another string thats
how it is defined now immediately i i will
have the next question what are all the various
edit operations i can make for going from
one strings to another strings so we will
start with three basic operations that are
insertion that means i i insert a character
in the first string deletion that means i
i delete a character in the first string or
substitution i delete or i substitute one
charter in the first string by another one
by another character so these are three different
operations that we will considering so now
my question would be how many of these operations
are needed to go from one string to another
string that is my edit distance between two
strings ok
so lets take a simple example so i have the
initial word is intention and the final word
is execution and i want to find out how many
of these operations are required to go from
intention to execution ok so now if i try
try to see that so what is what am i doing
to go from intention to execution i am first
doing a deletion i deleted i ok now i substituted
n with e again i substituted t with x i kept
e as it is then i inserted c ok so here star
means i went to null that is the deletion
here null went to c that is insertion ok then
again i did a substitution and with u and
t i o n re remain as it is so how many operations
i need i needed i needed five different operations
one was deletion one insertion and three substitutions
ok
so here the various operations that i did
now i need to define for these operations
what will be the edit distance ok so there
are two different variations that i can i
can use in one variation i might say that
each operation has cost of one so whether
i am doing deletion insertion or substitution
each has a cost of one so in this case what
will be the edit distance between the two
strings because i have done five operations
each has a cost of one so distance will be
five ok so this is called levenshtein distance
now i may also use another variant where the
substitution has a cost of two because this
is one insertion and one deletion so if i
takes substitution cost as two what will be
the edit distance between the two strings
so when i have one plus one for one insertion
one deletion plus three times two four three
substitutions that will be eight ok
so now my question is that how go we find
the minimum edit distance between two strings
so what will be an approach for doing that
so let us define it formally what are we trying
to achieve so i am trying to search for a
path by a path i mean what are the sequence
of edit operations that i have to make for
going from the start string to my final string
ok so now i can define what is my initial
state that is what is the word that i am trying
to transform so in the previous example intention
ok so this is my initial state then what are
the various operators that i am allowed what
various operators that i am allowed to use
over my over any of the strings i am allowed
to use insertion deletion or substitution
these are my three opre operators and there
is a one goal state that is the final string
that i am trying to get so it will be execution
the previous case and i want to minimize the
path cost number of edits i want to find out
what is the minimum number of operations or
minimum path cost by which i can go from initial
strings to final string ok so now if you think
of it in a very naive manner what what will
be an approach that you might try so i am
starting with intention and i have to reach
execution so one very naive method might be
in intention and try out all possible edit
operations until unless you reach execution
ok
so that is i shall int intention i see ok
if i delete one character i can go go i can
delete i i go to n intention similarly you
might delete other characters ok you might
insert one character in the beginning say
e or you can insert in any of the places or
you might try to substitute one character
like e can be substitute by i can be substitute
with e and that gives you another word and
you might keep on trying all this operations
until there is a point when you when you are
at the goal state so this might be one a possible
approach now what is even problem that you
see where is approach ok so do not dont you
think you might have to to travel a lot of
paths that are not at all relevant for my
problem ok why should i keep keep deleting
i n t e n t i o n all together in one path
when this will never give me execution ok
so so so here i am trying to navigate all
the possible edit operations to achieve the
goal state ok but this is discuss me huge
space ok we will try to work out one simple
example that how many even if i if i try to
find words with the addition one or two it
might be the number of operation the the number
of possibility might be huge so how can i
make in optimal how can i optimise this ok
so in this case what would also happen lot
of paths might end up with the same state
ok so i might end up with doing some insertion
and another deletion that might end up in
the same instead i was starting with or it
might have a with one insertion deletion an
another substitution so again this is unavoidable
in that kind of approach but we will like
to avoid it further do i really need to keep
track of all of them i need only those paths
that will come between intention to execution
ok so so the idea would be i define some sort
of a states and keep track what are the shortest
paths to each state because ideally i want
to find it what is the shortest distance between
two strings so there is no reason that i should
store all possible strings that all possible
ah wage of arriving from one string to another
that are having a higher distance ok because
i want to keep the minimum distance path so
so what is an approach that i will use so
for that let us try to define it more formally
so i have two strings x and y x is of length
n and y is of length m and i am trying to
find out the edit distance from x to n x to
y so in general i can define some edit distance
matrix
so how will i define it so let us see my definition
d i j where an element d i j denotes the edit
distance between the first i characters of
x and first j characters of y ok so how many
operations i need to to make to go from i
i characters of x to j characters of y ok
so now as for this definition what will be
the edit distance between x and y this will
be simply d and m ok that means the n characters
of x and m characters of y yes so now question
is what kind of algorithm i should use for
obtaining this particular the element of this
matrix ok so there we will try to see this
problem as a dynamic programming approach
ok so so we will compute d n m in a tabular
manner in general what do we do in dynamic
programming so whenever we have to solve a
problem we try to divided in such a manner
that i first solve the smaller problems and
try to use their solutions to solve the bigger
problem so that i will i can avoid certain
habitations in my computations ok so i will
first start by solving d i j for small values
of i n j and i will implemently use that to
find out finally my d n m by using the the
smaller values that i have already compute
it ok so so this is the bottom of approach
i first solve the very smalls of problems
and then i use it to solve the bigger problems
so i compute d i j for small i j and based
on the smaller values that i have computed
i will compute larger values of d i j ok and
i keep on doing that until i get d n m so
this will be our basic idea
so now what we will need to see that how should
i will be using the the smaller computations
to get the value for the large amounts ok
so i can define so here i am i can define
my dynamic programming algorithm for finding
out the edit distance between two strings
ok so now so first we are doing the initialization
so there we are saying d i zero is i and d
zero j is j now does that make sense what
is d i zero that is the distance between the
i characters of x and zero characters of y
now what will be the distance how many operations
i have to make for going from i characters
of x to zero characters of y and how can i
do that the only possible way of doing it
efficiently is i keep on deleting each of
the characters so there will be i operations
of deletions so the cost will be i similarly
how we go from zero characters of x to j characters
of y i can do j different insertion so thats
why i can in initialized as d i zero is i
and d zero j is j ok that is fine
now in general how do i define d i j in terms
of the previous the other sho short elements
that i have already filled up ok so here are
three by in which d i j might be filled so
so suppose i am trying to find out the edit
distance between x that is having right now
i characters of x and y that is having j characters
now the idea is that how go i compute d i
j using the smaller values of i n j so that
is how go use d i minus one j d i j minus
one and d i minus one and j one so let us
seen this example so i want to use d i minus
one j so what is d i minus one j so this is
suppose one character so this is my i minus
one distance between x i minus one to y j
and suppose we have already compute it that
what is the minimum cost between x i minus
one characters and y j characters now how
do i use to find out what might be the minimum
possible way of minimum possible edit distance
between x and y j so for the i characters
in x i can do a deletion i go to x i minus
one and then i use the distance between x
i minus one y j ok so how can i write the
distance i can say that same distance that
much would be d i minus one j ok plus one
because i deleted one character from x is
that clear in x i i delete one character i
i went to x i minus one and i have already
completed distance between x i minus one and
y j ok so that is one for deletion and and
this cost we already have similarly how do
you use the use d i j minus one same idea
so here i have x and y x is i y as j and suppose
i have already computed i j minus one so how
will i compute the distance between i and
j i is the same distance that i computed between
i and j minus one plus i inserted the jth
character ok so this you can think of it a
has insertion so distance will be i j minus
one and one ok and what might be the the third
possibility third possibility would be that
i know what is the distance between i minus
one j minus one and i am seeing whether i
am substituting i with j ok so so there might
be two ways if these characters are the same
that means i am not having any cost but if
there are different characters i will have
a cost corresponding to the substitution so
d i minus one j minus one plus two if the
characters are not same and zero if they are
same ok so there are three ways in which i
can i can write d i j it can by the d i minus
one j j plus one d i j minus one plus one
or d i minus one j minus one plus two if the
characters are different or zero if the characters
are the same so there are three different
ways i can define these cost now the cost
we are only store in the minimum cost i will
see what is the minimum of all three cost
and thats what i will storage d i j and that
i keep on doing this until i arrive it d n
m so that is the simple dynamic programming
approach for solving this ok
so let us see once one example now so same
example intention and execution ok so now
so we have already filled up some entries
here now can you relate to this what are what
is this entry this is my d one zero so initialization
we saw that d one zero will be simply one
because that mean i can simply delete i can
delete this character and i a achieve arrive
at the final sub history it starting from
i how do i go to null i delete i so this is
one similarly this will be two i can delete
i and n one at a time this will be three i
n t and all so on similarly why this is one
from null to e that means i am inserting one
character ok null two e x i am inserting two
characters so this will one two and so on
so that explains all these initial levenshtein
distance in this step now my my problem is
how do i fill up the other this stable so
for example how i fill this this particular
ok so now how did we define my dynamic programming
approach i said i will filled d i j based
on d i minus one j d i j minus one and d i
minus one j and j minus one now in this case
what is d i minus one j suppose i want to
fill this element this my d i j what is d
i minus one j this is my my i minus one j
what is my d i j minus one this is my i j
minus one and what is my i minus one j minus
one this is my i minus one j minus one now
what will be the cost here it will be minimum
of all this three operations so let us find
out for individual d i minus one j is one
plus one so this gives me two d i j minus
one cost between null and i am sorry i think
i i i wrote it incorrectly it should be d
i j minus one and there should be the d i
minus one j ok fine
so what is d i minus one j that is from null
to e ok what is the cost one plus one that
will be two d i j minus one is i to null that
is one plus one this will again give me two
and d i minus one j minus one is j zero yes
plus two if the if the two characters are
not the same so here the two characters i
and e there are not the same so this will
be two so that is i can go from any of these
paths and i have a cost of two so minimum
will again we two so i enter here ok so now
suppose you want to use that to find out the
value here so now one think we can see i need
three different entries this this and this
ok so what will be the cost minimum of three
three three again this will be three so like
that i will keep on filling up all the table
until i arrive at this element that is my
d n m ok so in general there might be more
than one ways of arriving at the minimum cost
so we will see how do we store that but right
now we can just put that cost as it is
so where fill up this complete matrix this
is what i will get ok and you see the distance
between intention execution in this case is
eight ok so but but you also see in this slide
that for certain strings the edit distance
might go up to twelve ok that is possible
but finally the edit distance between intention
execution comes up to be eight ok so this
up this approach gives me very very efficiently
what is the edit distance between one string
and another string and we know how to use
this now so there is one further thing that
we can do with this algorithm so that is again
depending on my algorithm my particular task
that is about computing alignments ok so for
some applications we just want to know what
is the edit distance between two strings but
for other applications you might also want
to find out what are all the places where
the edit took place so what is the alignment
remember the way we did the case of intention
versus execution we found out what are the
actual places where where insertion deletion
substitution are taking place so this is what
i mean by alignment which parts are line to
the other part in the string so now the question
is can i modify the same algorithm to also
find out what will be the various alignments
in the string ok an you will see it is very
very easy by using the previous algorithm
that we have seen ok for some application
we might need to align characters of the two
strings to each other now we do this by keeping
a sort of backtrace so what do you mean by
backtrace so whenever i am filling out the
value of d i j i can come of from either d
i minus one j d i j minus one or d i minus
one j minus one so whichever gives me the
minimum cost i will put a pointer that i came
from either form left from bottom or diagonal
diagonal element ok so whenever i i i am at
d n m i will again start doing a backtrace
from there which element i came here from
and i keep on doing it from started from there
until i arrive at the null characters ok so
every time we enter a cell we remember where
we came from and when we reach the end we
trace back the path from the upper right corner
to read read all the alignment ok
so let us see how we will do that in this
case so suppose i was filling up this element
and i know i can come from either here or
here or here all three are equally likely
so i will put all i might put all three points
but suppose when i was here the the best possible
we was this one so i should have come from
the diagonal to this element so this is what
i will store similarly here i will store another
back point and so on so now once my edit operation
is over i all all you have these back point
is each and every cell i start from d n m
and keep on following by back point so suppose
i follow this one i reach this cell again
i follow point i reach this cell this one
and so on until i reach the null characters
and that will give me the alignment of two
strings ok so here so you will have alignment
starting from d n m so we will see from here
i can go to the this element this element
this element now when i am here it quick have
come from either of the three elements so
you might have some sort of preference you
might say ok i whenever there equal to equal
possibility among all three i will always
diagonal ok this you might say so you come
to this element then you go to left then again
you go down based on preference down based
on preference down based on preference and
then thats where you get your alignment so
this is the this is some way you you can compute
which characters in intention are align to
which character in executions ok
so simple idea whenever so you can say these
are deletion insertion and substitution so
whichever gives you the minimum cost you will
add that pointer if all three are giving you
the same cost you might have all the three
point ok ok so in general suppose i start
with a with a word x zero to x n so zero means
null x n is the complete word x and i have
the output string y zero to y m so if i see
this matrix of size n cross m so every possible
ah path from zero to zero zero to m n is a
possible alignment ok so what i am trying
to find out which path gives me the minimum
possible edit distance ok and this in in as
per dynamic programming approach and optimal
alignment should be composed optimal sub alignments
so that means whenever i am going from i to
j i can use always the optimal sub align alignment
would be i minus one j and so on ok so thats
how this problem algorithm is designed ok
so if you do the victories you can find out
from the intention you go to executions and
what are all the places where you did insertion
deletion and substitutions ok and which words
you did not have to change at all ok now what
is the complexity of this algorithm
so lets talk about the time complexity how
much time we took so you see you have to fill
all the n cross m entries of the matrix so
there are n cross m different ah think you
have to do and for each entry you need a question
number of operation you will find out minimum
of three different distances so there are
n cross m times some constant so the time
complexity can be simply order of n m ok yes
what would the space complicity again the
space complexity also the same you are using
only n cross m different element that must
the space that you need you are not using
any other space remember for each element
you are using some other elements from the
same matrix so you not an any edit distance
space so again a space complexity is n cross
m now what about the backtrace so that is
i am i am at d n m and i want to find backtrace
the worst case can be i find i have to go
through all the n elements in my column n
elements sorry n elements in my top and m
elements in my ah first column ok so in the
worst case i might have to do n plus m different
operations so this complexity is again n plus
m ok so you will see this is very very efficient
in compare to the approach that fever the
naive approach that you have seen earlier
you start with the input strings try out all
possibility this will be become explanation
very very soon
so fine so this for this first lecture for
for this week and in the next lecture we will
start talking about certain variation of edit
distance ok why why do i actually why should
i even think of some variations and how do
we use that for finding edit distance ok