so hello everyone and welcome to the second
lecture of second week so ah in the last lecture
we talked about what is the basic edit distance
concept given two strings as input what is
a dynamic programming algorithm that you can
use find out what is the edit distance between
these two strings ok and remember we we we
define certain operations certain edit operations
and we gave weights or cost for each of these
operations but all these cost for equal ok
so the if you are substituting a a character
by another character irrespective what is
the what are two what are the two characters
the cost remains the same same goes for for
inserting a character it the cost remains
same and also for deletion of a character
it remains same so in this lecture we will
briefly discuss that is there any way in which
we can try to ah discriminate between various
sorts of ah edit operations
firstly is this should we discriminate between
various operation should there we assigned
the same cost or should be try to give different
cost and different operations then we will
also talk about the practical problem that
given a query so why query i mean a term that
might be incorrectly spelt how do i come up
with list of terms that are actual that for
actual terms that should have been used instead
of the the incorrect so what what should be
in what is a good or efficient algorithm to
find out all the set of terms that are variation
of edit distance of safe edit distance of
one or two of that query
so so starting with the concept of weighted
edit distance so can we weight the the edit
distance cost depending on what are the characters
that are involved in the in the operation
so firstly is it required so so do you think
substituting a by e should have the same cost
substituting a by m so what should depend
on ok what kind of so for example there are
certain errors that you make very very commonly
and certain errors that you make very very
rarely ok so now suppose you co error is very
very common should i assigned it a higher
cost or a lower cost so think about it what
is what is it mean to a assign it a higher
cost assigning it a higher cost means that
the edit distance between the two strings
will increase if that edit operation is present
ok so that means the probability of obtaining
the other string as a candidate we will go
down if the operation as a high cost but if
something is very very some some sort of edit
operations are very very common some spelling
mistakes are very very common we want we would
like to give them a lower cost so that i can
the actual candidate have a small edit distance
with the incorrect word ok
so it is important to understand what kind
of ah characters will have a lower edit distance
and what kind of character will have a higher
edit distance can be somehow give a weight
so so so this is the basic idea so why do
we need to add various weights to the computation
so the idea is that some letters in a language
are more likely to be mistyped than others
ok so let us take some statistics so this
is a confusion matrix for a spelling errors
that was found in a corpus so x is the incorrect
character and y is the correct character ok
so what is what is this stability is going
how often in that corpus they found an incorrect
x for a correct y
so for example if you try to read the table
the the entry for the first row the anti corresponding
to a e that means how many times instead of
the correct e and incorrect a bar substituted
and that number comes up to be three forty
two ok so that means in the corpus three forty
times at an instead of e a was written similarly
one hundred eighteen times instead of i a
was written similarly seventy six times instead
of o a was written ok
on the other hand if you see b it never happened
that a b was written as a so that means people
make the mistake of converting or instead
of writing e writing a this is a very very
common mistake on the other hand b two a is
not very common ok so so you can look at this
confusion matrix and you will find a lot of
nice patterns so one thing you will see is
that the errors among the vowels are very
very common so substituting i for e e for
i a for o they are very very common ok so
there may be because the person is may be
not knowing the spelling or so is even if
you knows the spelling by mistake is typing
the other verbal so this is ah this is also
possible
now there are some other kind of errors that
you can see here that come because of the
way keyboard also designed ok so the you will
see the the characters that that come very
very close in the keyboard so sometimes you
miss type them ok so this is again a common
source of a spelling error so for example
m and n are very very close together and they
also sound very similar so it is very likely
that you you mistake m for n or n for m so
that is this kind of errors are very very
common so so some errors come come because
some of the characters sound very similar
so like the all the vowels or certain characters
and also some characters are very very close
in keyboards so so that is again another source
of errors
so now once we know that some errors are more
likely than others can i use that this statistic
to design my weighting scheme so as i said
earlier if some error is more likely the addict
cost from one character to another character
should be low so that i can easily find what
should be the actual candidate given in the
erroneous word ok so the smaller edit distance
means that is more likely to be the correct
candidate that's why we will give a smaller
cost to those spelling mistakes that more
likely and in larger cost or a higher cost
those spelling mistakes that are not so let
that are very very rare see so keyboard design
is again again one thing that gives rise to
many of the errors that we have seen in the
previous slide ok so again try to correlate
among the characters that are coming very
close in the keyboard so we will see that
many a times people make mistakes in typing
one character for another
so now suppose you have some data and by analyzing
the data you can find out what kind of errors
are common what kind of errors are rear and
accordingly you can design your weights for
different ah different ah edit operations
so now once you have each weights that depend
on the actual characters you can modify your
initial algorithm ok so how can you modify
your algorithm so for example here so i will
so if you if you try to compare this with
a algorithm that we saw in the previous slide
small reference here is that we should have
giving a uniform cost for deletion insertion
substitution
what we are doing here so deletion is now
ah conditioned on the actual character that
is been deleted ok so you see d i g zero is
d i minus one zero plus a cost for deletion
of x i so what is the cost for deleting that
particular character same goes for insertion
what is the cost for inserting that particular
character even in substitution you might have
cost for so that separate cost for deletion
insertion and substitution of one character
by another ok and everything else remains
the same the only thing that changes is that
instead of using equivalent cost for each
operation you are now giving cost that are
dependent on the actual characters that are
inserted or substituted or ah deleted so that
is my weighted edit distance
so now so what to do you do with so how do
you modify your algorithm for taking care
of transpose for instance ok so that is the
algorithm were we had the we had three operations
we had insertion substitution and deletion
they were three operations that we why we
are using in that ah in that previous operation
so there is another very common edit distance
operation that is used and this is called
transpose so that is if i am ah so if i am
transposing toward two characters and you
will receive this is a common error that sometimes
you make ok
so for example so i am wanting two type a
l and instead i typed it as l a so this is
called transpose so in general if i write
x y as y x so this is called transpose another
name for this is metothesis so now how can
i modify my algo algorithm to take care of
this case so till now we have three operations
insertion deletion substitution in insertion
i see the the previous insertion deletion
i see only till the previous word ok but what
do i do in the case of transposition so in
the transposition i will have to so because
it is ah we have go to characters before so
i need to go to d in my cos matrix d i minus
two j minus two yes and suppose i give a cost
of one for transposition
ok
so i will write ah d i j as so there are other
cost that we had defined earlier but for transposition
i will say d i minus two d i minus j minus
two plus one and what will be the condition
only if so the previous word in x so ok so
i i had defined my strings as x and y here
ok so this is my string as x this is my string
as y so what will happen here this is up to
i so this x i minus one will be same as the
jth character in y so if x i minus one is
y j and x i is equal to y j minus one ok so
if i find that so x is still i is and y it's
will j so if i find that the i minus oneth
character of x is same as the jth character
of y and the ith character of the x is same
as the j mines oneth character of of y then
i will say that this cost is d i minus d j
minus two plus one
so again i will do a minimum of this this
if this happens this is my transpose and then
they i have other conditions for insertion
deletion and substitution and that's how i
can modify my algorithm by initial algorithm
to also include transposition ok so with all
these operation this is the only other operation
that is also commonly used in computing edit
distance so now so so we talk about edit distance
and also about ah doing including another
edit operation like transpose
so as i said earlier so we will also discuss
briefly so so what is the practical scenario
so the practical scenario here is your given
an input word ok so remember in the introduction
slide we two are talking about this error
ok say wold cup and by mistake i i have written
w o l d instead of writing w o r l d so now
the practical problem here is once i know
that this is not the correct word in my vocabulary
how do i find out what are the possible candidates
that might come in place of w o l d so that
is what are the suitable candidates now as
per our definition so the suitable candidates
are those that are having a small edit distance
from the actual error word ok so intern my
problem is how go i find out words that are
within some a small error some small edit
distance of word
so now how do i solve this problem given a
word like w o l d find out all the words that
are within the additions of say one or two
now one simple thing you might says that i
will list down all the words by vocabulary
somewhere ok so i have all the words in my
vocabulary starting from w one to wn ok and
i will find out what is edit edit distance
of w one with world w two with world and up
to wn ok i will find out all the edit distances
and then i will among those i will choose
all those that are coming up to the very very
small edit distance some some top entries
that are coming out to be within a small edit
distance so i will find out this type of entries
ok this is my candidate so but you but you
you can immediately see that this may not
be a very very efficient solution ok because
my vocabulary size can be quite huge and i
have to find out edit distance from this to
each of the words in my vocabulary so that
will be really really time consuming ok so
instead can i so can i do something more efficient
so one simple thing is i should try to search
in an efficient data structure for searching
all the words in my in my dictionary ok
so so in case you do not know so so one of
the very efficient edit structures that is
used for searching the strings is called the
trie structure ok so using the trie structure
you can do search efficiently in the linear
time so linear in the length of the input
string so i am giving you one example here
so so i can use the trie structure so so idea
is that so you you take any word you can start
from the initial root node of this trie structure
and keep on following the arcs and in the
time linear to the length of your word you
will reach to a node and find out if the word
is available in the vocabulary or not so by
that you will able to search all the words
in the vocabulary and this trie structure
can be used efficiently for computing the
distance of any any new word with a word in
this in this trie
so this is one possibility but this again
it requires you to do a lot of computations
with respect to all the words in your vocabulary
what can be other possibility so other possibility
if your thing would be so instead of trying
out to find out the ah edit distance of this
error word to all the words in the dictionary
can i start from my error word and try to
enumerate all possible words within some edit
distance ok
say one or two ok i am trying to enumerate
all the possible words edit distance one or
two so i will find out the word like world
and everything else and then i can have a
further check to see if these words there
in my dictionary and all and there i can use
maybe a trie structure that whether these
words are available in my dictionary or not
so this can of the possibility now what is
do you see do think this will be efficient
this approach so let us see some some numbers
ok so yes so i can possible generate all possible
terms is starting from the error word that
are within edit distance of less than equal
to two and there i can take care of all the
deletion substitution addition and transposition
i can try to take care of all the possible
ah edit operations so starting where wold
i generate all the possibilities with the
edit distance of two
now so if you just try to do it's a simple
math try to compute how many different possibilities
you will have to explore so let us see so
suppose if you take a word of length nine
that is nine characters and suppose in you
are taking a language like english and alphabet
is thirty six so and so that twenty six plus
other ah other characters and if you just
do that so this will give you roughly one
hundred fourteen thousand three forty four
three twenty four different possibility to
explore staring from the word of length nine
in which of the four you think will give you
a lot of possibilities ok deletion will probably
not give you many possibilities but substitution
will give you lot of possibilities and insertion
should also give you lot of possibilities
substitution you can substitute each character
by and you have a thirty six characters so
that gives you a huge number of possibilities
so this is again huge number so it's starting
from a word of length nine you you are going
to explore hundred fourteen thousand three
hundred different possibilities ok but yeah
english is still ok so you have thirty six
characters so think about a language like
chinese where the alphabets size is seventy
thousand so you cant even think of applying
an approach like that ok
so this is an approach is slightly better
than then before but it is may not be very
very efficient again depending on the alphabet
size so what can be the other possibilities
ok so other possible algorithm is that ah
the idea that all this all ah all this edit
opp edit distances can be attained if you
try to do a symmetric delete from the the
current word and the possible candidate words
ok so all the edit distance of operation two
can be found out just by doing deletes in
both the words ok
so what is the idea so this is called the
symmetric delete a spelling correction so
idea is that from your query word and so from
your query word you will try to find out all
the words that come up within delete of two
from the query word and from your dictionary
for each of the word you will try to find
out all possibility that come within and edit
distance two as per only the deletes and that
this will cover all the possible variations
of edit distance of two ok
so you can we can take a simple example so
suppose i so let's take the same example of
w o l d or so even or we can try to take a
a different example say w o t l d instead
of w o r l d that is the correct word and
this is the error word ok so what we will
do is symmetric delete operation so this is
this i will do offline it's an offline a starting
from word i will store all the possibilities
within edit distance of one and two so i will
store with world that there is word w o l
d that comes up w o r d and so on and from
these again you will have this is delete one
and you will also have again candidate for
delete two at run time when you get this query
like w o t l d that is incorrect you will
do the same thing so this is at run time and
you will again generate all the possibilities
with delete of one and two
so we are doing here one only to show the
possible possible so you will find w o l d
w o t d and so on and now you will try to
match if one of this is available in this
dictionary that is that is built by this symmetric
delete operation and you will find w o l d
and w o l d is a match and once this is a
match you will go back to the original word
and then confirm that this word and this word
have a edit distance of less than or equal
to two ok and and that's how you can find
out all the possible words within edit distance
of two without i am doing a lot at run time
now can you tell why because you only doing
deletes at run time and deletes a not mind
ok
so if you do one delete if you heard of nine
characters you have only nine possible deletes
so this is not very ah inefficient at at at
run time and this all is done at offline and
later you will have a further check to see
that these two words have additions of two
if your two or three sort so yeah if you take
ah number of deletes of two for a word of
length nine it will be at most forty five
so this is not a very big number so this is
one approach that that you can that that you
can use for finding out all the possible dictionary
terms within some edit distance efficiently
at run time ok yeah
so now so when we talk about edit distance
and some variations so we will not focus on
the task of spelling correction with which
we had a started this module on edit distance
and all so so when we talk about spelling
errors there are two kind of errors that you
might have to deal with so one that are easy
to to handle errors so i will say slightly
easier they are called non word errors because
they are at so the erroneous word is not in
my vocabulary so in this case so erroneous
word is b e h a f that is not in my vocabulary
i can deduct decision erroneous word and my
task is to correct it to the actual word b
e h a l f behalf and this is also called non
word error ok what is slightly more difficult
is something called a real word error when
the the word that is in error is also in my
dictionary but somehow the user has missed
spelt to a word that is in my in my dictionary
so here some examples so like typographical
error so instead of writing there somebody
has write a three now three in my vocabulary
so it is not easy to that the this is in error
now correcting this is called a real word
error correction
similarly they can be something for because
of the homophones ok because of say piece
and peace the two different variations of
pieces you might misses spell very very easy
and t o o and t w o is very very common error
so they are also called real word errors now
to handle both both of the ah non word error
and real word error you need to use various
probabilistic models ok and this is what we
will be focusing so ah in non word spelling
errors so the non word means the word that
is not in my ed edit dictionary so any word
that is not in the dictionary is called an
error ok and so for handling this problem
it is better that you have a good very good
lexicon tells you all the possible word in
you lexicon and this lexicon may also be dependent
on the particular corpus that you are processing
ok
so for you if your processing scientific coppers
you might have different corpus then if you
are processing use corpus so you should know
what your words in the in the dictionary and
when you encounter word that is not in your
dictionary you will tre treated as a errors
and try to correct it so what in general what
you will do in non word spelling correction
so starting from the error word you will try
to find out candidates that are similar to
the error word and how will you define the
similarity with respect to the error word
so you will say the words that are within
form a small at a distance ok that can be
that can be one possible criteria and if you
are using noisy channel model that will be
the topic for the next module so you will
see the one that is coming out to be as per
the highest noise and probability so this
will be your candidate words so you will choose
some of the candidate words like that
on the other hand if you are dealing with
the real word spelling error you will try
to find out so now you have the you did not
know in the sentence which of the word is
actually erroneous so what you will do for
each word you will find out other words that
are similar in edit distance or some other
criteria but in the candidate you will also
include your actual word so so t w o is there
so we include t double o also with two and
you say that the actual sentence might contain
any of these two words ok and then finally
you will try to maximize the probability of
the sentence using some noisy channel model
so this is what we will be discussing in the
next next lecture so where we will talk about
noisy channel model in detail and how it can
use for doing the task of spelling correction
so
thank you