ok so welcome back for the third lecture of
this week so in the last lecture we talked
about what are the various variations of a
edit distance that you might be using in general
ok so today we will now talk about very extended
algorithm for doing a spelling correction
so in general when i talk about spelling correction
i might be talking about isolated word reduction
or correction that is a word without the context
even there it might be a word that is in my
vocabulary or not in my vocabulary ok so we
will see examples for that or i might talk
about doing correction in the context there
again a word might be in the vocabulary or
out of the vocabulary and and we will see
how this this simple approach of noisy channel
model can be applied for doing a spelling
correction ok
now what is my noisy channel model so if you
if you think of the the model name what is
happening we having a observation x that is
a word that is misspelled and you want to
correct it that is your observation but what
what is the idea of this model so whenever
have a miss spelling you wanted to write a
correct word ok and you went through a channel
that can be your keyboard or something else
and that's how you mod your word got miss
spelled so that is what you are assuming you
have a correct word w ok this is your correct
word and you have a incorrect word x that
is your observation yes now you wanted to
type this correct word w but you went through
a channel and this we are saying is a noisy
channel and you are making some mistake while
going through this channel and the word that
you are observing is x but not w now your
observation in x now given this observation
x how do i find out what is my mostly slightly
candidate for w what is my w ok
so in general how can i try to up to this
problem i am seeing a word x that i know it
is miss spelt now how do i know it is miss
spelt one two way of doing that is i maintained
a dictionary that that is my set of all the
words my vocabulary and if the word x does
not match with any of this word i say this
might be in misspelled ok now once i know
x is a misspelled word that means i have to
correct it now what are i have to first started
with ah what are all the possible candidates
for correction so suppose possible there could
be i find out all the words within the added
distance of something ok now among those which
one is the most slightly candidate ok so so
in terms of noisy channel model what is the
w from which x has been written written so
miss spelt and and we wrote x so in terms
of noisy channel model i want to find out
w hat that gives me the maximum probability
p w given x among all the possible words in
my vocabulary or it can be in my set of candidates
what is the what that gives me the maximum
value for p w given x
now how do i compute this probability p w
given x you see as for the noisy channel model
i first started with the word w and then i
went through the channel and i ended up with
the word x so i can only find out using my
channel what is the probability of x given
w ok i will have to somehow used to find out
probability of w given x yes so what is a
particular theorem in probability that you
can use for is so remember bayes theorem so
i i want to find out probably w given x but
i already can find out from my channel probability
of x given w so how do i write p w x in this
term so i say this will be p x given w p w
divide by p x yes so i will i can replace
i by argmax of this
now what is your variable here the variable
is w you can have multiple different words
but your x remains the same for each individual
word so what in fact you are trying to do
for each word your completing this value and
then you are seeing that is the maximum value
which word gives you the maximum value now
among the three different probabilities that
you are using for this formula which one you
might remove for this computation is it the
probability p x remains the consent across
all the words so it will not matter to my
decision of which one is having the highest
probability because this was the simply depend
on this particular multiplication so i can
as well remove p x and keep my argument ok
and that's how we actually use
ok so i write it like that and i remove the
probability p x and that's how that's so how
i will find out which one is the correct word
w for x which give me the maximum probability
for probability x given w times probability
w so now i will we will see how do we compute
these probabilities individually what are
the various which we can compute this probabilities
ok so so we are taking about non word spelling
errors
so again what do i mean by non word spelling
errors a word that is not in the dictionary
or my vocabulary and i know ok this might
by misspelled word suppose i have taken the
word here actress ok so actress is not in
the dictionary it can be actress across or
whatever but we do not know so this is the
observation that we made now using noisy channel
model i want to find out what should have
been the correct word ok so now the first
thing i will needed to do i will need to find
out what are the candidate words that might
be correct ok
so how do i find the candidate words i will
try to find out words that are having similar
spellings that are having small edit distances
ok or i might try to use the words that are
having similar pronunciation so both of these
are possible so then i make some sort of candidate
set so suppose i have ten different words
that might have given to actress so these
are my [var/various] various candidates for
w and i need to use the noisy channel model
to find out which one is the most slightly
candidate
so and suppose i am using might d l at a distance
ok this is small variation of my levenshtein
distance remember levenshtein distance what
were the operations we at insertion deletion
and substitution in this particular ah edit
distance we also have the transposition ok
so insertion deletion substitution and transposition
of two adjacent correct words so we discussed
about how to how to modify our dynamic problem
algorithm to take into count of this transposition
in the in the last lecture so now so given
to two strings i i can always find out what
is the ah word so given a string i can find
out what are the other words that come within
additions of one or two ok so suppose i start
with actress that is my observation in correct
word i try to find out that are the algo candidates
are come with a additions of one ok
so here is i have here is the word acress
now i find the words like actress cress caress
access across acres and acres occurs twice
in this list why and we will see that let
us try to understand first candidate word
actress so that does we written here so we
have written so this is my correct word this
is my incorrect word so what change did i
make for going from correct word to incorrect
word so i went i had a letter t in my correct
word but it repla i replace it with null so
this is an deletion i delete it t from my
correct word so that's why this is deletion
ok
similarly how would i go from cress to actress
i have to have insert a so this is the again
insertion yes similarly how i go from caress
to acress i am doing a transposition so c
a change to a c transposition acress access
to acress c got change into r across to acress
o got change to e now so why there were two
acres you see acres to [acr/acress] acress
i can go by doing one insertion but insertion
can happen at two points it can happen either
here or it can happen here and these two will
have different probabilities ok remember with
the probabilities of substitution will depend
on what is the pervious word that what is
the pervious character in this word ok so
they will different probabilities that's why
they are two different insertions ok
now so that means whenever i have a misspelled
word i have to first generate all the possible
candidates ok so so there we try to use some
sort of a statistics how many different candidates
should i be using so so the general statistics
is that eighty percent of the errors are within
distance of one and nearly all the errors
are within the additions of two so that means
i can mostly try to use the candidates within
a additions of one or two ok may be one will
do for most of the cases so that's what we
did in the pervious example starting from
acress we found out all the candidates with
in a additions of one and while generating
the candidates i might also allow for deletion
of space or hyphen so if i a word like this
idea without a space i might allow this idea
with this space and similarly for hyphens
and not with a hyphen so now now when we are
trying to compute the probabilities we had
two different terms probability of x given
w and probability of w so you will first see
how do we compute probability of x given w
now suppose we are taking the simple case
where there are ah only one this only one
edit operation from the input string or the
correct word to the incorrect word
so what do i mean by probability of x given
w i would mean what is the probability of
that edit operation being done so remember
we had four operations insertion deletion
substitution and transposition so we need
to define probabilities for each of these
so here that's what we are defining we are
defining deletion over x y what do i mean
by that whenever in the input string a input
word i had the sequence x y this is my correct
and it got typed as x this is my incorrect
so x y got typed as x so this is i have deleted
y so this will depend on the pervious character
x in the correction
similarly what about insertion i had x in
the correct and i inserted y in the incorrect
so this is the case of insertion substitution
x got typed as y so i had x in my correction
i got typed as y in my in correct decision
what is transposition again x y here incorrect
got typed as y x in my incorrect so these
are the four different possibilities if i
am having only one edit operation between
the two strings so now the question is how
do i find out probability of a particular
ah deletion or insertion operation so let
us take one of these and see how do how we
will actually find out find out these probabilities
so let us take the simple case of deletion
so how do i found probability that in a in
a string a charact a set of characters x y
a character bigram i can also say it is a
hecta bigram got converted to only x
so how i will feel find out this probability
so we will have to see in general in corpus
how likely is this error so now what kind
of data do i need to count to find this probability
so i need some sort of data were you just
have written some texts and they made some
mistakes not knowingly ok so they made some
mistakes that if general people do and somebody
has then seen this corpus and tried to correct
it ok so suppose i have a corpus that is ah
corpus is a real corpus and that contains
various errors and then i also have a corrected
corpus
now how will i use these two different corpora
to find out the probability of deletion x
y i will say how many times do i seen my corrected
corpus a word containing the bigram x y for
which the corresponding word in my actual
real corpus had only x that means actually
the word should have been have having x y
but it was remains x so how will compute the
probability i will see in my real corpus how
many times i have this corrected bigram x
y and out of those how many times y was deleted
in my real corpus and that will give me the
probability that how after x what is the probability
that y is deleted so whenever how many times
x y occurred together out those how many cases
y was deleted as similarly i will find out
find it out for all cases of insertion substitution
and transposition
so let us see the actual matrices ok so you
are seeing again insertion deletion are conditioned
on the pervious character ok so that's how
i find out the probability of x given w x
is my incorrect word and w is my possible
candidate for correction so so remember how
we found out deletion we said how many times
this correct a bigram w i minus one and w
i occur in my corrected corpus and among those
how many times w i was deleted after w i minus
one ok similarly here insertion how many times
the word w i minus one occurs in my corpus
and among those how many times i inserted
x i in my real corpus were people made mistake
how many times they actually inserted x i
after w i ok w i minus one
similar substitution how many times w i occurs
in my corpus among those how many times it
was substituted with x i same thing you will
do for transposition how many times these
two characters occurred together among those
what fraction of times they were transposed
so that means we need two corpus one we we
have made mistakes another the same corpus
that has been corrected ok and then you can
compute all these probabilities now if we
go back to the pervious example of finding
various candidates for actress so we had seven
different candidates here
now we already saw what is the corrected error
word and and we are using the the model we
saw saw in the previous slide to find out
probability of x given word ok this one so
now first we are writing what is my x given
w so whenever this first my deletion from
actress t got delete and we got actress so
how did you find the probability of deletion
we said what is the probability that c t among
all the times that c t occurs what is the
probability that t gets deleted so out of
ct i see only c in my corpus and this probability
i find my corpus to be point zero zero zero
one one seven ok similarly insertion that
means a got inserted in the beginning of the
string transposition a c in place of c a and
so on in so here we have you see there are
two different ways you can do insertion after
e or after s that's why you have two different
probability that is also ok
so so again from the corpus you will find
all these probabilities values probability
of x given my word for different words what
is probability x given now what is the other
probability of the compute probability of
w itself so what is the intuition as such
you will try to give try to favor a word that
is more likely to occur in the corpus then
a word that is not so likely in the corpus
ok so suppose i use a corpus and i also find
out the probability of the word ok so now
i have found out probability of x given word
and the probability of the word both of this
so remember my noisy channel model i have
to multiply these probabilities and find out
which of the candidates gives me the highest
probability value
so suppose i do the same so in this slide
you will see so i am multiplying these two
probabilities and we are putting ten to the
power nine just so that we are able to see
these numbers ok they were be a point zero
zero zero to the point that we will not able
to compare so the first probability is two
point seven times ten to the over nine minus
nine sorry so what are the two candidates
that that have the highest probability you
see here i have actress and i have across
so these are two words that i having the highest
probability and in general you might write
across has the correct candidate ok
so now remember we were saying we can do it
without with the context or with the context
so without using the context this is the best
we can do and suppose they come up to be really
close two point seven two point seven one
without using the context you cannot find
out which is the which is a better candidate
than the other but supposed you are allowed
to use the contexts so can you do better ok
so let us see for the same spelling correction
if i have the context what will i do so suppose
my sentence says versatile acress whose ok
and i have to correct it and remember what
were two candidates the two candidates are
actress and across so the two sentences are
versatile across actress whose versatile across
whose now which one is more likely ok
now how do i find out how do i use the fact
that probably versatile actress or actress
whose is more common than versatile across
and across whose so on so for that what we
can do we take some corpus so this is some
corpus of contemporary american english and
we use some smoothing so do not worry about
what i mean by smoothing we will cover that
in detail in language modeling so suppose
i do some smoothing so idea is that if were
we try to find out the probabilities of a
word coming after another word that's what
we are doing and from there i find out these
probabilities that the that the word actress
occurs after versatile is point zero zero
zero zero two one and the probability that
the word across occurs after versatile is
the same and that makes sense also versatile
across many different fields and versatile
actress they might have the same sort of probability
of occurrence in the corpus
now what about the other bigram what about
the other two word combination that is actress
whose and across whose so we see in the corpus
we find actress whose has a much higher probability
than across whose ok and if you have this
information we can use that to refine the
probabilities for that if suppose i simply
multiply the probabilities with my earlier
corpus so what will i get so i will say probability
of versatile actress whose is the initial
the two probabilities two hundred ten times
ten to the minus ten and probability of versatile
across whose will be one times ten to the
minus ten so this gives me that versatile
[ac/actress] actress whose is much more lightly
than versatile actress whose as per my corpus
if i am using the context and this can further
help me to find out what is the correct ah
correct word that should have been there in
place of actress ok
so now the next concept is the real word spelling
errors so so what they mean by that there
are there might be errors where the [mis/misspelled]
misspelled word is actually in my dictionary
ok so like you see the sentence here the study
was conducted mainly be john black and we
know the correct word should have been by
but the user ended up typing be [no/now] now
just think for a moment can i solve this problem
without using the context so without using
the context how can i even say that it should
be by and not be ok i might use the individual
probability of a word occurrence but that
is not a good method to say that so in that
case i might find errors everywhere in my
corpus
so i should be try try to using my context
in somewhere ok same in the next sentence
the design in construction of of the system
and i know this should be and but the user
ended up typing an now these are real words
in the vocabulary and now i want to correct
the spellings one thing is sure i should be
using the context now how do i actually use
the context for trying to correct these errors
ok and this is again some statistics that
twenty five to forty percent of the spelling
errors that this here are real words ok
so now suppose i i have a sentence x that
contains words w one to w one now we do not
know which of the which of these words is
in error ok because all of these are real
words in my dictionary so how do i [e/ actually]
actually start doing the spell correction
so what i will do for each of the individual
word i will try to find out what are the [bes/best]
best possible candidates that might be the
correct words ok and there i should not forget
to include this world itself because this
might be a correct word also so here what
we are doing for the word w one we are saying
ok candidates are w one or some word w one
prime w one double prime w one triple prime
and so one they are possible candidates for
correction w two again that's what w two and
other candidates same way w three now what
is my problem now i can have any sequence
from the candidates of w one i can choose
any one w two i can choose any one and so
on and among all these possible sequences
i have to find out which one is giving me
the highest probability in somethings ok
so i want to find the sequence w that maximizes
the probability of w given x ok that is whether
this would be a good sequence or this would
be a [goo/good] good sequence or this would
be a good sequence as for all which of this
sequence will be the best in this case so
again you have to find out w that maximizes
probability of w given x so again can we try
to use the noisy channel model so we will
see ok so now we are taking a real example
here two of w thew and probably it should
have been two of the and we are not seeing
the other words right so as my the model what
will i do i will take the word two i will
put this word along with all the other possible
candidates
so i have put in put t w o t a o t u all are
having a smaller distance similarly with off
i am putting o n o double f with the thew
i put thew threw thaw the and so on and we
know the correct sequences two off the fine
but in general suppose i had to find out the
probability for each sequence this might become
exponential so you can do the simple math
suppose each word on an average has four possible
candidates including itself and there are
five different words in my sentence so how
many different sequences i will have four
to the power five ok and if the number of
words increase in my sentence this will keep
on increasing
so now to avoid this problem we will try to
use some sort of we make some assumptions
that it is also simplification to the model
what is that we say ok [ll/let] let us assume
there will be a at most one [err/error] error
in the sentence ok so how does it help it
helps in that whenever i am choosing the the
candidates i will only choose a a different
word for one of the one of the words so so
what do i mean by that suppose i had my sentence
w one w two w three and this has some other
possible things like w two prime w two double
prime this has w one double prime w one double
prime and this has w three prime w three double
prime so in the previous model we would have
taken all the three cube that is twenty seven
different candidates in the previous one so
with this assumption what we will do for w
one if i am choosing a candidate of w one
prime i will assume w two two and w three
were correct ok so this is the assumption
there might be at most one error per sentence
so how many candidates will be there i will
have two possibilities here two possibilities
here and two possibilities here ok so there
would be at most six plus one if you are taking
the one there the sentence might have been
correct say w one w two w three as it is ok
so so the candidates are w one prime w two
w three only one error per sentence w one
double prime w two w three and so on so this
hugely reduces the number of candidates for
which i have to check and this is quite true
also and that is why you do not make more
than one error per sentence in general in
general ok
so now once we have this assumption we want
to find this [sec/sequence] sequence w that
maximizes the probability of w given x so
i can again try to use my noisy channel model
how find out the sequence w hat that maximizes
the probability of p w given x x is my observed
sequence and w is one of my candidate sequences
and we know how to find out the candidate
sequences so that is for each of these sequence
is w i have to find out the probability w
given x now as for the noisy channel model
how will i write it down so i will again use
the bayes theorem here because i am starting
from w and going to x so i can only find out
the probability of x given w so this is what
i will do ok now how do i write probability
x given w x is a sequence w is a sequence
so suppose they have the same number of words
i can make a simplifying assumption that p
x given w is simply multiplication of probability
of individual word given that in the sequence
ok
so suppose my word is this is my w and this
is my x so probability x given w i will write
x probability of w one prime given w one probability
w two given w two probability w three given
w three ok so now there are two kind of probabilities
here one is when the two words are not the
same probability of doing an error yes one
they at the same now how do i find out the
individual probabilities this one we have
already see in the previous case i will find
out what are the [audit/edit] edit operation
and what is the corresponding probability
if it is deletion insertion and so on so this
is same as the previous case same as in previous
but how do i find out the probability of w
two given w two should it be one now it will
depend on what is the kind of errors that
you are seeing in your corpus if you are seeing
that they are on an average one error per
ten words you will say this probability is
point nine thus the this is what is correct
these are probability of that the same the
word is correct
if there are one error in hundred words you
will say that this probability is point nine
nine and that's how you will fix this probability
ok so p x given w same as non word spelling
correction but we also need this probability
w given w and that is the probability that
you have correctly typed a word and that you
can find by the kind of the the amount of
errors you are seeing in your source if there
is one error per ten words you will say this
probability is point nine if there is one
error per hundred words you will say this
probability is point nine nine that's how
you will set all these probabilities and you
will choose the candidate x that gives you
the maximum probability ok candidate w sorry
now the other part is finding out probability
w ok by w i mean the the sequence w one prime
w two w three how do i define the probability
of the sequence w ok for that we will use
a technique called language modeling so that
will give me the probability of n is the sequence
of words and we will use any of this unigram
model bigram model or any other model for
for finding out this probability of
so so this here will be the topic for the
next lecture so this in this lecture we discussed
what are non word errors re word errors how
do we use noisy channel model to correct those
but there we also need something like probability
of the sentence as such probability of the
sequence of words w how do we obtain that
and that's why we will go to the idea of language
modeling in the next lecture ok