ok so so welcome ro the forth lecture of second
week so in the last lecture so we dis we were
discussing about a spelling correction and
also seeing how do we do that it using the
contexts and remember the last ah problem
that we are facing is how do you find the
probability of sequence of words ok so I have
sequence of words in in my sentence that might
be candidate what the probability of that
sequence and thats why we will we said we
will be using language models for it so today
the talk that the topic of this lecture is
to see what are my n gram language models
and we will start with some motivation of
what are the different applications were we
might need them so n gram language modeling
is a very very ah nice technique in n n l
p and its applied in many different applications
it is very very one of the very basic concepts
in n l p ok let us see what are my n gram
language models ok
so i will start with the motivation of context
sensitive spelling correction that was a topic
of just the previous lecture suppose i am
having the sentence the office is about fifteen
minutes from my house ok so here you can clearly
see that this is just a spelling error minutes
has been typed as minuets but suppose the
word in minutes is also in my vocabulary ok
suppose i see my vocabulary and i find that
minuet is a some sort of slow graceful dance
ok that was popular in seventeenth and eighteenth
cen centuries so this word in my vocabulary
so now that means i cannot easily detect that
this is the incorrect word by using some isolated
word as correction so i should be using the
context for that so what is the probability
that so i will try to use some sort of language
model to say with a probability of this a
trends about fifteen minutes from its higher
than the probability of a trends about fifteen
minutes from ok
if you observe these two a trends you can
you can yourself see that for it will should
be more probable but how do you formally defined
these probabilities and what is the model
that we use for it and thats what we will
be seeing in this language model ok now so
what are some of the other applications for
this is helpful remember one of the earlier
slides in a ourlast week you were saying in
this case of speech recognition you face this
problem that when you are uttering something
you have to trans you have to transcribe that
ok so whenever I am saying i saw a van it
might also sound like eyes awe of an ok so
among the two a trends is which one is more
likely so again can i give some sort of probability
value to each of these sequence in the say
that probabilities i saw a van is more probable
than the other
similarly in machine translation there is
a problem of collocations that certain words
even if they are correct translations do not
occur much in the language with a in the context
of others like if i say if i have the word
winds and before that as an adjective i can
put either high or large because so for example
i have an hindi actress tej and i want to
translate that into english how i we will
winds now for tej it might happened that both
translations high and larger possible in in
english now among those which one should i
choose and suppose from my corpus again find
this language knowledge that high winds occur
with more probability then large winds then
i would say that high is a more probability
translation than large
and there are other applications is spelling
correction we have seen and you might have
to use that for generation whenever you have
to generate sentences again which particular
generation has the higher probability ok another
possible application that you might be using
it in say google search or ah other places
whenever you are trying to type something
that they will be predict what will be the
next word so whenever i am saying please turn
off your cell what will be the next one you
can bit probably phone please turn off your
cell phone and your program does not probably
compared or something ok so given is a in
a sequence of words how they predict what
is the next for that is that is going to come
in this sentence so that is my auto completion
task that is huge a lot in a coyote completion
or even when you are typing something in your
s m s or you might have certain softwares
that that do that so so they also use the
concept of language modeling ok
so these are also called the predictive text
input systems so given whatever you are typing
they will give you choices in how do you complete
it what does the various possibilities were
which will complete ok so now so given these
applications in background let us see what
is my language model what is the goal what
do we gone to achieve so we talked about this
in the previous lecture we said we i want
to complete probability of w that is what
is the probability of the sequence w one to
w one this is the sequence of words what is
the probability of the sequence so this is
one of the gold compute the probability of
a sentence or a sequence of words ok pro p
w what is the other related task that we saw
in prediction system that given three words
w one w two w three what you might w four
so probability of w four given the three previous
words probability of an upcoming words
now in general any model that computes either
of these probability of the sequence or probability
of the word given the previous a trend is
is called a language model ok we were see
language model using these definitions ok
so now how do i actually compute probability
of the sequence w means sequence of words
here so suppose from the examples that we
were taking initially i have the sequence
about fifteen minutes from i want to compute
the probability of the sequence now suppose
i do not tell you anything else what is the
simplest model that you will applied to compute
this probability so you will probably apply
the chain rule of probability yes ok so remember
chain rule of probability so it derives from
conditional probabilities ok so you conditional
probabilities you might remember so that is
what is the probability of b given a that
is probability of the joint the joint probability
p a b divided by probability a now you can
also use that to writing in some other way
so you can say probability a b which probability
b given a times probability a ok and if you
you can do that for any number of words in
my sentence or in general any number of evens
in probability so you can say probability
a b c which probability a probability b given
a probability c given a b and you can keep
on doing that finite numbers and that is my
chain rule of probability ok i can write p
a b a p a times p b given a in general even
if i am more variables i can do the same same
chain rule of probabilities idea and this
is the general formulation probability x one
given x one is probability x one probability
x two given x one and so on and probability
x one given x one to x n minus one
so now given this chain rule now go back to
a initial ah problem probability of about
fifteen minutes from so how do i write it
using the chain rule of probabilities so how
will you you right this probability you will
say this is same as probability of about times
probability of fifteen given about times probability
minutes given about fifteen probability from
given about fifteen minutes so you can right
it like that yes ok now suppose i even increase
this to about fifteen minutes from office
what will you do ok and you will write it
in terms of this probability also probability
of this given about fifteen minutes from
so now how the question that comes is find
i can write it in terms of chain probability
chain rules chain rules how do i actually
compute this probabilities now what is probability
of office given about fifteen fifteen minutes
from that would be in my corpus how many times
do i observe about fifteen minutes from among
those how many times i observe office after
that now what is one particular proper you
will face in doing it in this work you might
not have seen sufficient number of about fifteen
minutes from in the corpus suppose it occurred
only once it occur with the office this probability
will be one but does not mean that only office
can occur this about this occurrence and this
problem becomes savior as you keep on going
to the higher and higher number of words in
the conditional ok
so so we will never see enough data for estimating
these so i cannot estimate easily what is
the probability of office given about fifteen
minutes from so that means this will not work
as as it is so we we will need to do certain
simplifications ok now so what is the simplifying
assumptions that we make we say ok we can
probably use only the previous word and forget
about everything else so I have to compute
the probability of office given about fifteen
minutes from and its a that is approximated
by probability of office given from i forget
the other terms ok so or i can use the previous
two words so this can be written as the probability
of office given minutes in from ok so this
is simplification that we are making why we
are doing that because now it is easy to find
complete the probabilities what are the words
that come of that from and how what session
of times office comes after from but this
was not possible when i was taking condition
on four previous words because information
was probably not seeing them enough in my
data so this helps us giving a better estimate
of these probabilities ok more formally we
can use kth order markov model ok
so i have this information have to compute
the probability of the sequence of w one to
w n by using chain rule i write it as as this
w i given the previous i minus one words multiply
for all the words now in kth order markov
model assumption what i will do i conditioned
it only on the previous k words so i will
write probability w i given w one w i minus
one as w i given only the previous k words
ok so here you are using only one up to k
three previous words not all the i minus one
words so this is kth order morkov model assumption
ok
so we can do that for all the come all the
components in this product ok now and that
thats how we will define ever n gram models
ok so if i take this particular probability
probability office given about fifteen minutes
from if i am using only the previous word
ok that will be using it two gram language
model so in general if i am using only n minus
one words of prior context i am defining in
n gram language model ok so here if i am using
if i am not using any word from the context
zero words from the context this is a unigram
language model n is equal to one here if i
am using one word from the context then its
a bigram language model n is equal to two
if i am taking two two words from the context
it is a trigram language model n is equal
to three ok now can you try to relate in n
gram language model with some kth order markovs
assumption
in kth order markov assumptions you were using
kth previous word so if i am using k previous
words i have a k plus one gram language model
so i can say an n gram language model is an
n minus oneth order markov model ok in n gram
language model i use n minus one words from
the context so this is the relation between
an n gram language model and an n minus one
order markov model now internal we can extended
to trigrams we assume two words from the context
four grams three words from the context of
five grams four words from the context ok
but in general we cannot see that any n gram
will be sufficient model for the language
why because language we also see some long
term dependencies so consider this sentence
the computer which i had just put into the
machine room on the fifth floor crashed
now what is the word on these the word crashed
depends ok if you were see here the word crashed
depends on the about computer but this cannot
be captured by using two gram three gram four
gram five gram six gram so on to see so you
might have to go to eleven twelve grams and
that is probably not very advisable so you
use must always knew that an any n gram model
is not a sufficient model of a language but
it captures many word ordering relative regularities
ok so in most of the applications we can use
simple n gram model with an it will two three
and we will get up with it ok
so now the question is how do we estimate
these n gram probabilities from a corpus so
for that the simple method of estimating these
probabilities is by using some maximum likelihood
estimate ok so what is that suppose i have
to compute the probability of w i given w
i minus one so i will find out in my corpus
how many times the word w w i minus one occurred
among those what fraction of times w i occurs
after that ok remember we were doing it from
the one of the earlier slides in versatile
actress whose so how many times the word actress
comes after versatile what fraction of times
same here what is the fraction of times that
the word w i occurs after the w i minus one
so which defines a probability distribution
after w i minus one each word my vocabulary
can come and this will be a probability distribution
ok
so in general it i can give a notations of
c instead of count c w i mi minus one means
number of times w i minus one occurred in
my corpus and so on now lets take an examples
and see how do i estimate these probabilities
so i have three sentences in this corpus i
am here who am i and i would like to know
and you also have some tokens on a start of
the sentence and the end of the sentence and
you want to compute the bi bigram probability
w i given w i minus one so how will you do
that so suppose i want compute all these probabilities
probability of i coming at the start of the
sentence probability of here coming with this
probability end of the sentence coming after
here probability of would coming after again
so on so how do i compute this probabilities
so i just take the first one probability of
i coming at the start of the sentence so i
will find out how many of start of the sentences
i have seen among those perfection of the
times i occurred so i have seen three start
of the sentence out of those two is highly
occurred so this probability would be two
by three here how many times i have seen here
one ok and among those how many times the
end of the sentence occurred also one this
will be one by one and so on ok
so so this is what i find two by three one
one by three one by two and zero so this is
easy given a corpus you can find out the bi
bigram probabilities by its just giving the
counts now this is some example from some
restaurant corpus so that had nine thousand
plus sentences and these some bigrams that
were the numbers are given here so can you
see some regularities here so i and i do not
occur together much ok but i and want occurred
eight hundred twenty seven times so you are
in a restaurant after i mostly say want i
want some sort of food ok so i want is a bigram
that occurs a lot in this data what are the
others bigrams that occurs a lot want to i
want to do something eat chinese ok chinese
food eat lunch to spend so all these bigrams
that occurs a lot so this tells in lot about
that corpus so i am talking about the restaurant
corpus where its more about ordering some
food and eating some so so a kind of foods
ok
now suppose i i have to compute the probability
bigram probability what is do i need i need
the count number of times this were occurs
without the word and you know divided by the
unigram probability of the previous word so
suppose i give you the unigram counts also
of all these words can you come with the bigram
probabilities yes it is becomes quite easy
so now i just divided by the number of times
i occurs so here so number of times i amount
of the together divided that number of times
i occurs so this gives you probability goes
to point three three so probability of want
occurring after i is point three three from
this corpus and so on i can compute all the
words in this corpus ok
so now given a corpus you should be confident
now that how do i compute the bigram probabilities
now suppose you have computed bigrams probabilities
from the corpus now can use that to solve
over initial problem that is how do i find
the probability of this sentence this sequence
of words so i have the sentence here a start
of the sentence i want english food and in
end of the sentence i i want to find the probability
of the sentence so how do use bigram model
do that i will say ok this is probability
of i given as the start of the sentence times
probability want given i times probability
english even want and so on because i am actually
using the chin rule of the probabilities but
i am using in first short of a markov assumption
ok so that gives me all this probabilities
and i multiply that and then it gives me the
probability of this sentences each ok
so if i use the previous probability that
will be flip point zero zero zero zero three
one and now you can give me any sentence and
i can use my bigram probabilities to find
out the probability of the sentence and i
can solve all my problems of spelling corrections
and other scenarios so now so from this corpus
what does the knowledge n gram represent ok
so these are some values so what do you ah
try to infer from there so probability english
given want is point zero zero one one and
probability chinese given want is point zero
zero six five what does it that tell so if
you see that will tell that the ah any chinese
food its six time more popular than the english
food in whatever from whatever detail it was
taken from ok to given want is point six six
so that is two occurs a lot with a corpus
after i want i want to do something eat after
to is again point two eight someone want to
eating to do something into eat occurs a point
two eight probability food given to a zero
that means the word food never occurs after
to and that is something that talks about
the language in language generally use a verb
after two i want to do something and here
the food is a noun so this will not this will
not occur in my data similarly want given
a spend as a zero again some fact about language
that two words generally do not occur occurred
simultaneously ok and i given the start of
the sentence point two five again gives gives
some in instigation that most of the sentences
start with i in that in that corpus so mo
mostly about i want to do something so you
started with i so these n grams might represent
some knowledge about the language and grammar
as such or about the particular data or domain
that you are trying to build it these form
and this is some idea that we can use for
even modeling different domains in in my data
separately i can build different language
models for each domain ok so will talk about
this further ok
so now so there are certain practical issues
that you might have to aware of like when
i am doing this probability computation for
a sentence i am actually doing multiplication
of many probability values and all of these
might be very very small so if i simply do
multiplication of probabilities it might lead
to some underflow and this might just end
up in getting a zero values for all the probabilities
so its better that you do everything in log
a space in that way you are simply adding
them and in any case adding each individual
operation or more efficient operation then
multiplication so you are just storing the
log of probabilities and you are adding these
problem these logs ok so you can if you aware
to find out probabilities p one times p two
times p three times p four if you convert
in log space that is nothing but log p one
plus log p two plus log p three plus and so
on
so you can restore a log values and you can
just add this there is another problem of
handling zeros ok suppose in your a trends
there is a particular bigram that you see
that never occurred you a trend data so what
would happen you will give it a value zero
but that will convert the whole the ah everything
zero ok so you need to do something for that
and we will see that in the in the in in the
concept of a smoothing ok so there are some
popular toolkits are available so s r i s
r i s r i l m is one popular toolkit but there
are many other toolkits that you can use for
language modeling ok you can also if you want
to use some large corpus data you can try
to use these google n grams so there again
available on this link and there you will
find out for each different n gram what is
the number of times they occurred in the corpus
ok
so if you go to this link you will find out
there are huge number of tokens sentences
and all ok they they gave you you unigrams
bigrams trigrams fourgrams and fivegrams so
what are some of the examples so suppose i
am sing it after a starting from serve as
the so the that data will tell you serve as
the inspector occurred sixty six times the
in the in the corpus serve as the inspiration
occurs thirteen ninety times serve as the
installation occurred one thirty six times
and so on so this is a fourgram that you find
from the data but you see these are only the
counts now how will you use that the compute
the probability that probability will inspector
given serve as the so for that you will also
need to use the trigram count of serve as
the so again this five is available you can
you can get this fourgram of the data and
trigram data and try to compute the all the
probability values ok
now so they also give a nice a p i by which
you can visualize many interesting patterns
in the usage of words ok so because heritage
divide across many different centuries you
can also plot it temporally so what we are
seeing here suppose i give three different
queries albert einstein sherlock holmes and
frankenstein on google n gram viewer it tells
me over the years what is the probability
of these bigrams so can you see something
interesting here so sherlock holmes became
popular around eighteen eighty five and so
on before that is when nearly zero frankenstein
probably there in the novels even before that
so even from the six eighteen hundred he find
the occurrence of frankenstein that keeps
on increasing even two thousand its more its
much more than albert einstein and sherlock
holmes albert ein einstein started getting
popular in in the data around nineteen seventies
thats why the most of the dict discoveries
happen happened and and it came into the books
and at some at some point of time it became
more popular than even sherlock holmes ok
so you can do nice sort of analysis of what
kind of words came into ah the language all
my data in what times and how the popularity
changed over the years by using these kind
of data ok
so so today we will we gave only some in intuition
and what is language model how do we compute
that and what we can use it from for there
were some problems that we saw that how do
we handle the zeros ok so with zero is the
whole probability of the a trends will go
to zero even if one of the component has a
probability of zero so how do we avoid that
problem how do we solve that problem thats
were the concept of the smoothing will come
in picture and thats what we will covering
the next lecture ok