okay so welcome that for the final lecture
for second week so in the last lecture we
were discussing about the basic of language
modeling and there we we just hinted about
the one problem about the zeros in language
models so today in this lecture we will discuss
how not only how to handle this zeros in language
modeling's but also how do you go about evaluating
your language model that you have learned
from some data [vocalized noise] ok so these
are the two main topics for this lecture ok
so so we start with the evaluation of language
models so so what is the basic criteria for
evaluating a language model so one symbol
indication could be a language model is better
if it is assigning a high probability to the
actual sentences the real sentences and a
low probability sentences that are not so
grammatical that can be one criteria for evaluating
language models but can but this has to be
done manually so you will have to check what
is a probability that your model is assigning
to various sentences that are real most of
the sentences that are not real that are not
grammatical but can we do that in an automatic
manner so for that we might we may also use
some sort of training and test data so so
what is the idea behind using this training
and test data so i have some corpus and i
learn my language model on some part of that
okay
so this is my training set now once i have
learned that language model from my training
set i will test whether it is providing a
good high probability for my test data and
i will have some evaluation evaluation metric
for finding out how good this model is doing
on my test data and by this method i can i
can even compare across different language
models so if i have learned three different
language models for example i can find out
which one does better on my test data and
that will be the best model ok so in general
what are the different ways in which language
models can be evaluated so as such there are
two different criteria for evaluation one
is called extrinsic another one is called
intrinsic ok we will discuss what are these
individually [vocalized noise]
so what do i mean by extrinsic evaluation
of my language models [vocalized noise] so
suppose i have learned two different language
models a and b from some training data now
what do we do in extrinsic evaluation we try
to use them on certain task so remember some
of the applications that we have discussed
offline language models so they can used in
the spelling correction or in speech recog
recognition and all that so now what i will
do in this extrin extrinsic evaluation is
that once i have learnt two different models
i will try apply them to these tasks individually
and then see what is the performance that
i am obtaining for each of this task by different
models now i will say whichever model is giving
a better performance on these task is my preferable
model so this is called extrinsic evaluation
or task based evaluation ok so here we have
discussed if we have mentioned three different
tasks a spelling correction a speech recognition
and machine translation i will have two models
a and b i will get accuracy values for these
three tasks and i will compare the accuracy
and tell which language model is preferable
than other so this is my extrinsic evaluation
but if there is some intrinsic way of evaluation
without actually applying it on some task
ok
so for that so we have the motion of perplexity
so this is how we evaluate language model
for for for intrinsic evaluation so intuition
comes from the shannon game if you heard about
this name so so what is that what is that
game how well can you predict the next word
given sudden context ok so let us see some
examples so i have the first sentences here
i always order pizza with cheese and and there
is a word that you have to predict may be
you can say pepper or whatever and similarly
the second sentence the president of india
is and you can predict the next word similarly
in the third sentence i wrote a and you can
predict letter or program or whatever ok
so now in my data i know what are the words
that will fill up these blanks now suppose
i have two different language models i will
find out which of these fills up these blanks
better than the other one ok so whichever
one is good at predicting the next word is
my preferable language models so one thing
you can easily say from here the unigram models
are probably not built for this task ok so
suppose you want to predict the next word
you just you need a model what would happen
so if you remember unigram models do not use
the context at all so you will just end up
providing every at every place the word that
is having the highest probability ok
so probably unigram models are not good for
this task but you can apply a bigram models
the the model which uses the previous word
trigram models that uses the previous two
words and so on [vocalized noise] ok so so
finally among different language models a
better model is one that you will assign a
higher probability to the actual word ok now
what is the formal definition of perplexity
so in general what we are trying to find out
the best language model that predicts an unseen
test data ok so how do i define perplexity
ok so so this is a simple definition of perplexity
i have some test data i am finding out the
inverse probability of test data normalized
by the number of words that i am seeing in
my test data ok so thats means finding the
probability of test data and then normalize
it with respect to the number of words and
its inverse probability ok that means if i
have a low perplexity i have a better model
ok so formally i can define my per perplexity
like that suppose in my test data i have words
w one to w n i am finding the probability
of this whole sequence and normalizing it
by minus one by n here
ok so now now this is is a general definition
now the next question that you might have
is that where does the language model come
into picture in this definition is simple
definition of finding probability of this
whole address w one w n and sub with some
normalization now where does the language
model come into picture now remember the chain
rule that we discussed of probabilities if
i have this sequence w one to w n how can
write the probability of the sequence in terms
using the chain rule of probability so that
is what you see here so i can write the same
expression like that one divided by probability
of w i given the previous i minus one words
ok this is in general this definition of probability
w one to w n now now can you see how do we
apply language models in this definition so
in language model we take one particular assumption
about using this chain rule that is how many
previous context will i will be be using ok
so you can in place of this you can replace
any of the model that you have learnt so suppose
you want to replace with your bi bigram model
that means you want to find out what is the
probability that the bigram model will give
for this utterance so what you will do so
we simply replace here the bigram model probability
so that will give you the perplexity for the
bigram model that you have learnt or trained
using some training data ok so you will feed
in all this probability w i given w i minus
one in that model and that will give you the
perplexity of the bigram model [vocalized
noise]
ok so now just to give you an intuition what
do i mean what the number of number that i
will get indicates perplexity value what does
that indicate let us take a simple example
[vocalized noise] so suppose i have a sentence
that contains n random digits ok and i have
a model that assigns a prob a probability
of one by ten to each digit ok now i want
to find a perplexity of the sentence using
that model that will give me a probability
of one by ten to each digit so what will be
the perplexity let us try to use the definition
ok so what how the did we define perplexity
that is probability of this whole sequence
yes w one w n to the power minus one by n
yes so can you try to fill in the values suppose
my model gives a probability of one by ten
to each word so this would be one by ten to
each word to the power n for n different words
n to the power minus one by n so that is nothing
but one by ten to the power minus one and
that will give me ten so this tells me [vocalized
noise] that the perplexity of this model is
ten the model that assigns a probability of
one by ten to each digit ok now this might
give you a hint of what this number indicates
ok so let us take another example from some
test data oath so what kind of perplexity
values we get and what can how we can interpret
this values [vocalized noise]
so an experiment was experiment was conducted
over wall street journal corpus so in training
they had thirty eight millionwords on which
the language model was trained and for testing
they had one point five million words on which
perplexity was computed and they trained three
different models unigram model bigram model
and trigram model now and they found out what
is the perplexity of the model in using the
test set so these are the numbers that were
found for unigram model perplexity was nine
sixty two bigram one seventy and trigram one
zero nine so now let us try to answer this
question what is this value of nine sixty
two perplexity in unigram indicate ok so what
it means is that whenever my model is trying
to assign a word it is it is as if it is has
to choose among nine sixty two different possib
possibilities at each individual choice point
independently and randomly ok
so this is this means the model is very very
perplexed so if the perplexity is high my
model is very very confused if it is low my
model is not so much confused so in this case
what you are seeing if i use a unigram model
perplexity is nine sixty two the model is
very very perplexed but if i go for a bigram
model it is one seventy the model is not so
much perplexed now trigram model it becomes
even better its only one hundred nine ok so
thats what you are seeing unigram per perplexity
of nine sixty two means the model is as confused
on the test data as if it had it had to choose
uniformly and independently among nine six
sixty two different possibilities for each
word ok and that you can also relate with
your previous example because every time it
had it had to choose among ten different possibilities
for each digit ok because it is about giving
a probability of one by ten to each digit
[vocalized noise] ok so now you understood
what the perplexity means
now so once we have built a language model
we can also use it for other tasks so one
very interesting task is called shannon visualization
method that is can i use this language model
to visualize or generate sentences ok so if
you have read the original paper of shannon
on the mathematical information theory so
there he uses this method to generate various
sequences of words ok so what is the idea
suppose i have learnt a language model can
i use that to generate various sequences of
words or sentences so how do we actually apply
this shannon visualization method [vocalized
noise] so suppose i have to generate a sentence
so what i will do i will have to generate
a sentence so i will first choose a random
bigram that is starting the sentence as be
the probability so what do i mean by that
[vocalized noise]
ok so i am learning my bigrams so i have in
with the start of the sentence whether the
word w one occurs with what probability with
the start of this sentence what w two occurs
with some probability so this is a complete
probability distribution that will add up
to one now if i have to generate a sentence
i have to choose one among this possibilities
and this will depend on the probability of
that bigram ok so this you can think of as
multinomial distribution and you are sampling
one word from this multinomial distribution
so suppose you pick picked up a particular
word here ok so you start generating a sentence
you start n w two ok now i have to choose
the next word so that is the next step choose
a random bigram wx as per its probability
so what i will do now i will go to the distribution
w to n different words w one w two w two and
so on and from this distribution again from
this multinomial distribution i will sample
one sample one word suppose i find sum w fifty
ok again i will try to a sample word with
its distribution w fifty and the next word
now the question is when do i stop when do
i say that my sentence is complete i will
say my sentence is complete once i sample
a word with the end of the sentence ok at
some point i sample wi and the next word is
end of the sentence i say my sentence is closed
ok so this is the whole idea of shannon visualization
method
so i do that until i choose end of the sentence
and we will see one example from one corpus
so from restaurant corpus that we discussed
in the last lecture suppose i have learned
my bigram model and i want to generate a sentence
so how will i do that i choose start of a
sentence find out the first word i find i
then i take the first word as i choose the
next word how do i choose choose the words
by sampling from the multinomial distributions
ok so in this case if we sample we might end
up with getting the sentence i i want want
to to eat eat chinese food and after food
we get the end of the sentence so i want to
eat chinese food would be a sentence that
is generated by this method
now suppose we try to use this method over
the shakespeares corpus so there so we have
some number of tokens and the vocabulary size
is twenty nine thousand sixty six ok just
to give you an indication that bigrams are
actually very very sparse so if you take the
voc vocabulary size of twenty nine thousand
something how many bigrams are possible so
what do you mean by a bigram two words together
so i can take say v square are the possible
bigrams because every possible combination
can occur but so this gives me a number of
eight forty four million possible bigrams
but in the corpus how many bigrams were actually
observed so we find there were only three
hundred thousand bigrams that we have observed
in the corpus so this is very very sparse
ok so now suppose i build various language
models from this corpus and try to generate
various paragraphs and sentences so what do
we actually observe ok you will see what happens
if i take unigram model bigram model trigram
model and and high order models
so so here you are seeing if you take unigram
model you are getting some words that are
probably very popular in shakespeares but
the sentence themselves do ah are not making
sense ok so you see the word like which here
it occurs independent of any other words and
this becomes a complete sentence that will
not probably something that you will see in
the shakespeares corpus so now suppose you
go to the bigram model ok now so you start
making some sense so you have words sequences
like what means ok i confess and all sorts
ok they have good bigrams but if you's try
to observe the sentence probably they are
not making much sense now if you go to trigram
model then again you have getting some more
sense five first if shelled i and the shell
forward it should be should be bent they have
some nice sequences again and this is starts
making a much more sense in terms of sentences
and if you go to quad terms then you are getting
something that is resembling ok king henry
henry watt i shall go see the traitor gloucester
ok so this look like a valid sentences from
the shakespeares corpus so that is the idea
as you go to higher and highder higher order
model the kind of sentences you generate will
be something that actually resemble the corpus
from which we are hm training this language
model
okay so this is my visualization method so
now we will try to go to the problem of a
smoothing that we discussed in the last lecture
so remember what the problem was in my language
model suppose i am training for bigrams so
so yes so just take the statistic that we
saw from shakespeares corpus there were eight
hundred forty four million possible bigrams
out of which only three hundred thousand bigram
actually occur so now if you assign the probability
to each bigram very few will will get a probability
greater than zero others will get a probability
of zero now suppose you are taking a test
data and finding out how much it resembles
shakespeares corpus and whenever you see a
bigram you are taking probability from the
trained language model now suppose a bigram
occur that is not there in the shakespeares
corpus imagine the probability is zero now
what happens to perplexity value remember
this is simply the multiplication of all the
different probabilities so this one becomes
zero ok so that will not to very very helpful
so you actually would like to give it some
probability so that this does not become zero
ok thats why we will study topic of smoothing
how we can assign different probability values
ok to get get around this problem of zeros
ok so let us take a simple example suppose
i am learning my trigrams and my training
data i have seen the following sentences ok
i have seen these many occurrences denied
the allegations denied the reports denied
the claims denied the request ok and i am
learning a model of finding out the word after
denied the ok
now suppose in my test data i see these two
occurrences denied the offer and denied the
loan so what would happen to the perplexity
of my model ok so in the test data i have
seen these two occurrences that were not there
in the training data so so probability of
offer given denied the will be zero same with
probability of loan given denied the so the
test set will be assigned a probability of
zero and the perplexity cannot be defined
ok and that was thats what we were saying
initially so how can i go around this problem
so that i can compute my perplexity even if
there are certain bigrams or trigrams they
did not occur in my training data so what
is the idea of smoothing so idea is suppose
so this is what we were seeing i am computing
the trigram model for the word w after the
occurrence denied the and suppose in my data
i see four different words right i see allegations
reports claims and request in total seven
words and i can assign the probability to
each of these as three by seven two by seven
one by seven and one by seven ok and that
is what you are seeing in this plot three
by seven two by seven one by seven one by
by seven so these adds up to one now what
about the probabilities for the other other
trigrams like denied the attack denied the
man denied the outcome these are also very
very feasible trigrams so here what will happen
we will assign a probability of zero to all
of these yes so all these have a probability
of zero now what is the idea of smoothing
the idea of a smoothing is can i take some
probability mass from each of these four words
and assign that to the three words or any
other words that i have not seen in my training
data ok so that is
can i steal some probability mass from these
four words to assign some probability mass
to the other words in my co in my data so
that is suppose here i have taken a probability
mass of point five each from the four words
ok so that means i get a probability mass
of two by seven and that mass i distribute
among all the other words in my corpus and
this can be distributed in multiple different
ways ok we will see some solve some possible
ways in which we can distribute this poss
this stolen mass to some oth to the other
words that we were dint see in my training
data ok and how much mass has to be distributed
that also we will see so there are different
methods that that do that ok so the basic
idea is clear so i exactly we do that ok so
a simple method is called laplace smoothing
or add one estimation so what is the idea
so pretend as if you have seen every n gram
one more time that we actually did in my training
data so that is suppose i saw it only once
so i will pretend as if i have seen it twice
so what will happen to the n grams that i
have not seen at all in my training data so
i will pretend as if i have seen them once
ok so this is simple idea so so we will just
add ones to their their actually counts that
we found from the training data we will just
add one to that so remember this maximum likelihood
estimate for this bigram probability of w
i given w i minus one we find it using number
of times if we observe w i minus one followed
by w i divide by the number of times i observe
wi minus one in my training data so this is
my definition of mle so how do i estimate
language model or a bigram model using mle
now how do i use the laplaces smoothing there
so what did we say we will pretend as if we
have seen each n gram one more time than we
actually did so what we will do here so we
will add one to the actual count ok so will
do that for each possible bigram but to ensure
that the probability adds up to one i have
to normalize i have to make some modifications
to my denominator so that so that they are
normalized so what will i add to my denominator
ok so to get this answer you can see how many
different bigrams will be there for which
i will be adding one so how many different
wis will be there that will be number of words
in my vocabulary ok that means i will add
one capital v times so to normalize i will
also have to add a v here in the denominator
ok and that is essentially the idea of my
add one smoothing that i add a one to my actual
n gram count and add a v in my denominator
two to to normalize it ok so this is my add
one estimate number of counts plus one divide
by the count of the unigram wi minus one plus
the vocabulary size so that is the very very
simple smoothing technique that you can use
in general ok so that does not require a lot
of ah fancy estimates you can just get your
language model and easily apply this smoothing
method ok
now we can all when we apply this add one
smoothing method we can also talk about what
is the effective bigram count so let me understand
what do i mean by this effective bigram count
so what i mean is so you see here you have
modified your actual counts or the probability
so what is the idea so now what is in effective
what would have been the count in your act
actual training data such that you have got
the same would have got the same probability
ok so what i am saying so this is your new
probability probability wn given wn minus
one as per the add one smoothing yes so question
here is what would have been my effective
bigram count c star w n minus one w n such
that if i do the mle estimate pmle w n given
w n minus one i will get the same value as
this ok so how do i get the effective bigram
counts so this effective bigram count if i
would divide by counter w n minus one i should
have got this probability so thats means i
can compare c this probability with this probability
and that will give me what is my effective
bigram count ok so thats how i define my effective
bigram count so we will see some example so
if i apply this for my restaurant corpus so
what kind of ef effective bigrams do we observe
ok so we remember this is what this is the
counts that we see in my bigram this my restaurant
corpus ok so we saw that in the last lecture
i wont occurs very high number of time sense
so on so this is the actual bigram that we
see now suppose i apply add one smoothing
so so you cannot apply to this data right
exactly because is not the complete data this
is just a small screenshot ok so now suppose
you use add one smoothing and then if you
find that what is my effective bigram counts
so what kind of effective bigram count do
you see you see in this table certain counts
are zero so one thing you would ah assume
that after applying this smoothing technique
these will not be zero this will be greater
than zero and whatever for having a high value
should have a smaller value because some mass
would be sh esti would be stolen from there
to give it to the words they did not occur
and thats what exactly you will see when we
apply this add one smoothing and then do the
effective bigram counts so here so these are
my effective bigram counts so you see here
whenever the word i want the bigram i want
occur eight hundred twenty seven times initially
the effective bigram count now is only five
twenty seven on the other hand i too did not
occur at all in my training data but now it
has a effective bigram count of point six
four
another observation you can make from here
given the previous word for the next word
if that occur zero times the effective bigram
count remains the same so its point six four
whenever the previous word is i for the words
like to chinese food and lunch but this varies
across different previous words so if you
take the word like want for wants this value
becomes point three time for to it becomes
point six three ok so this depends on the
previous word and that you can also see why
ok because i am i am doing this plus v to
the count of the unigram yes and that will
be different for different words thats why
this value will be also different for different
words [vocalized noise] ok so in general so
so here we talked about the add one estimation
but in general there are some simple variants
of this also ok so one simple variant is called
add k var add k estimation so we are adding
one to each bigram so why why want why cant
we do some general thing like k k can be point
five or more than one depending on how big
your data is ok so this is called add k estimation
so here what is the idea we add k to each
count and accordingly we will ah add kv to
my denominator yes so this is actually the
same as add one ah estimation if i take k
is equal to one
now i can also make some variant here so suppose
i say kv is equal to m ok so now i can write
it as this plus m and this plus m by v yes
this is effective the same now m is k times
v so this is another variant and this also
gives me an idea on how i can improve this
basic smoothing method so here what i am doing
i am adding m by v to each word effectively
i am doing m times one by v to all the v words
in my vocabulary ok and if we add up for all
the words in a vocabulary m by v you get an
m so now can we do something better there
the idea is instead of adding mtimes a uniform
one by v to each word can you add m times
the unigram probability for the word and you
say this will add up to one for all the words
you will effectively end end up guiding the
same values in numerator and denomi denominator
when you normalize the probability but this
might be a better estimate ok why is that
so let us first see all these valuations ok
so this is when i replace kv by m thats what
i get and in place of one so here in place
of one by v i can also replace the probability
of the word ok that will be a different smoothing
but what we are saying this might be a better
way of doing a smoothing this called unigram
prior smoothing so so let us just discuss
this point why this might be a better way
of doing a smoothing ok so remember what we
are trying to do here we are trying to find
a probability or different words that do not
occur in my training data wi given w i minus
one ok take a word w i that is very very common
ok so like i have a word government that is
very very common ok and i might have some
other word like may be something like smoothing
ok that may be other word w one w two ok what
are you doing in your add one smoothing or
add k smoothing you are just studying k or
k or one and dividing by the count of the
previous word plus kv and this will be same
for both the words yes so now so what is the
idea of unigram prior smoothing idea is that
if i know that this word is more common in
my corpus then this word probably i can say
that the probability of this word occurring
of a w i minus one will also be higher than
the probability of this word occurring after
wi minus one and that i am trying to exploit
this data i have from my corpus and i am trying
to exploit that for doing my smoothing ok
so this is called unigram prior smoothing
ok so in general so there are many other ways
of doing smoothing also so we discussed add
one smoothing and the institution behind unigram
prior smoothing but there are other advance
models of smoothing also that we will see
in the next lecture so in week three ok