hello everyone welcome to the first tutorial
session for the natural language processing
course so in this tutorial sessions we will
be seeing how to set up the programming environment
for the course and how to use it to solve
your assignment problems so we will be using
python as our default programming language
and we will using jupyter as our default programming
environment so if you are already comfortable
with a particular programming language or
an environment it is perfectly fine that you
use one of those but if you feel that you
will be requiring our assistance it is recommended
that you use python and jupyter
so let us see how to install a programming
environment so what i will suggest is that
you can go to google and type anaconda python
so anaconda is a package that gives you the
programming language programming environment
and all other necessary packages required
to run your course so you can see that the
first link here which is the anaconda package
leads you to the download page so the we get
here we can go to the menu and see the download
link is up here for installation we can look
into the packages here as we can see the package
is available for different operating systems
and we recommend that you go with the python
two point seven version
so depending on your you can install the sixty
bit installer or the thirty two bit installer
so if you are working on osx or linux where
installers are available here we recommend
that you install that version and go to the
particular director where the package is downloaded
and run your dash command to execute this
particular package command line installer
will take you through and it show you how
to install the package for the windows the
graphical installer is available and you can
download it by clicking on this particular
link as i have already have the install version
available with me i will be showing you a
step by step process of how to install this
set up
so if you have space constraint you can cry
the minimal package called as miniconda otherwise
it is advisable that you go with the current
installation which is anaconda so here is
the installation package and ah you can go
to a step by step process and yes it ask for
two separate ways of installation if you dont
have admin privileges in the particular system
you are installing you should be selecting
this one just for your particular use and
you can define why you are package should
be install and make sure you have at least
two gb of free space available in your system
since just that i have already a package install
so i will be just showing you how to install
it to on a separate folder and i just you
have to just make sure this are ticked and
click on the install button
so the install will take somewhere around
fifteen to twenty minutes to complete and
once its complete you will be able to see
the anaconda package in your programs and
once you click here we can see different packages
installed where you should be selecting jupyter
notebook so jupyter notebook is a programming
environment that runs from your browser so
it has a server running at the back and i
have an instance of jupyter already running
in my browser so in it go with by default
goes to your document folder and within the
document folder it will show you where exactly
your files are residing
so as part of the assignment we will be providing
you some help of files of which this is the
particular programming file that you should
be looking for so this is your programming
environment so notebook is not just a programming
environment it helps you keeps lot of things
that you learn it helps you document the stuff
that you basically go through so that you
can refer it back so i will be using python
as my language inside jupyter and python also
tends to be my favorite calculator for example
if you want to calculate just some values
i can just see how multiplication of two values
this may an answer so nine eight seven into
five forty three will give me this particular
answer now if i want to stop using my variables
i can gives the values to the variables there
is not type declaration as required we can
just give a variables name so maybe i can
give variable one and this will be variable
two and c equal to variables one plus variable
two and then i print the value for c
now assuming i want since we will be we are
studying about natural language processing
we will be taking a lot of things and lot
of textual data to handle we will how to stop
text strings so if you have a variables you
can just assume text strings enclosed with
in quotes so here i have typed hello and world
and i do the plus operation to both the variables
let see what happens so the particular variables
strings hello world together which means it
concatenation in a both the variable so this
automatic identification whether the sum needs
to be done or concatenation needs to be done
this handled by the python interpreter
suppose if i change and i say hello mook lets
say how with becomes yes so the output given
here basically shows hello mook similarly
a variable initialized at a particular cell
can be reused at an another cell as it resides
in your memory for example i reused the hello
which is already there in which was already
defined in the particular cell here and i
use hello in nptel let see how it comes it
works and important thing that you have to
care of is indentation so when using conditional
statements like the if or the loops like the
for loop you have to make sure that the block
indentation is maintained so what i want to
check is that if a is equal to hello so i
check for whether the variable a contains
the variable hello then the variables are
given the values one nine two otherwise the
variables b and c are given the values ten
and eleven let see which value gets print
since the value a since the variable a has
the value hello it prints one and two suppose
i change it to nptel and execute it and now
i run here so here i get the values ten and
eleven so if you are still confused how to
run the code after typing the code in the
particular cell we can either use the short
cut controlled and enter or you may go to
this button and this will execute the code
so let us change the variables values here
and see if what happens if they enter code
now be gets the values sixty and that gets
printed here
now suppose i am using a loop to print all
the values between one and five that is one
to four how do i do so i defined keyword four
i define a variable and i define that the
variable will be within a range from one to
five if we can make it we can make it seven
or any value of your choice and lets see so
it prints all the values from one to six if
i dont want to print it line by line i can
just use a comma here and it gives me the
values written in the same line so this is
some basic syntax that that will let you coding
python and we recommend that you go through
some of the basic tutorials regarding python
and some of the basic data structures that
python has so that it will help in making
ah coding experience mutch better
so in order to provide that we will be providing
you some links and some resources that you
can go through and get with the particular
code so as part of your assignment you are
supposed to solve questions that involved
edit distance that involves ah calculating
the likelihood using bigrams and unigrams
and i will be showing you how to handle this
so as from the week two lecture one you might
be aware of the concept called as edit distance
so edit distance is a particular function
that helps you compare two strings and find
the similarity between them
so the edit distance gives you the minimum
distance between two strings and the minimum
distance can be calculated in terms of the
number of operations that required to change
one string from to another and this is defined
in terms of three operations insertion deletion
and substitution so we have provided a function
called ah levenshtein that helps you execute
or calculate the edit distance so this is
how functions are methods are used in python
we use the keyword def followed by the name
of the function and since i have two strings
to come i give the strings as my function
arguments that so that when you call the function
you have to give which are the two strings
to be given
now these are the three operations the insertion
deletion substitution that you will be using
to compare both the strings so we need not
worry about what exactly is happening inside
you can think of It as a black box and you
can just execute it but if you are curious
you can obviously work around with it hack
around with it and see how the output changes
so assuming i already have the code setup
and i already executed this particular cell
so that the function goes to gets invoke now
i call this function levenshtein and i give
two strings which is hellp and hello and i
want to see what will be the difference between
the strings or what will be the edit operation
edit distance it turns out that the edit distance
is one which is being written by this particular
variable here
suppose i want to give yes it also gives the
same values so if i have a new string the
value changes as part of your assignment you
have one question where you are supposed to
solve the problems using jaro winkler distance
jaro winkler distance is a variant of edit
distance that is used to combine strings and
we have provided the explanation of how to
calculate the jaro winkler distance between
two strings and you can read about more in
the wikipedia link provided that for your
convenience i have we have already implemented
the jaro winkler as a function and we have
stored it in the packages edit distance so
we can call the jaro winkler function and
you can again assume it to be black box just
to solve your assignment
so in jaro winkler as you can see the value
ranges between zero to one and the so if two
strings are exactly the same they will provide
you the value of one and if they are complete
different they will provide a value of zero
so if i give the same string i get a value
of one as my jaro winkler distance so this
is very useful when it comes to ah combine
strings such as person names because there
are each variations in the person name that
we use for example it is very common that
the word vimal might be spelled as bimal depending
on your demography
so suppose we apply this function and let
see how the string gets the value so the similarity
between bimal and vimal turns out to be point
eight six seven now let us see given a data
set or a corpus of words and you want to find
the most similar words of a given string from
that how do we do that so you will be provided
with a file called unigram dot csv you need
to load that file and you have to ah so you
have to so ah every line contains s single
word or every unique word and the frequency
with which it appears in a particular purpose
so i read the file to the variable unigrams
and unigrams will be store as a list there
is a default data structure used in python
you can ignore about list from the python
manuals so for convenience you can think of
it as an array where i if i want to access
the first element i just give the index of
the first entry which is zero and i print
that well so the entry gives me foul for which
has a frequency of one suppose i want to say
the first ten entries in the file i will use
the colon followed by number ten so it will
give me all the numbers from zero to nine
and that gives me the first ten entries which
is foul which appears one time foul which
appears three times and immature appears one
times bringing appears one time
now i will be using a different data structure
called as dictionary that helps me separate
the count and the word from one another so
dictionary is as the name suggest we have
a key where the key is your word and when
i provide the key to the dictionary it will
provide me the count with which it is appearing
so here is the function that helps me and
it stores the value inside the dictionary
called as wordfreq
so once i execute it so a dictionary has two
entities one it is called as the keys and
it has it made as a list of the keys so if
you type wordfreq dot keys it will provide
you all the keys that it has now if i want
to know how many times thunder is appearing
what i would do Is i would see the count of
thunder by just giving the key as thunder
to the variable wordfreq now it appears the
it appears only once let us see how many times
hanging is appearing and thats validate with
the its coming out to be correct the its coming
out to be correct as its four here and we
already have checked it was four
now since you know how to open a file how
to store it in a dictionary and you already
also know how to compare two strings let us
see we can whether we can find similarity
the most similar word to a given string or
a given word so what i do is that i it trade
through all the possible words in the dictionary
and then i find the levenshtein distance between
the string that i want to come here which
happens to be tord it is a spelling mistakes
so i have to which word be replaced with t
o r d and if you see here i take each word
from the keys of the dictionary and assign
it to the variable item one at a time and
i compare tord with item and i am going to
print all the words that has a levenshtein
distance which is less than or equal to one
so if you fine tord well and good otherwise
let us see what are the other words once it
turns out there are five words which are similar
to tord which is lord tore torn told or word
let us see all the words which have a levenshtein
distance of less than or equal to two when
it turns out there are much more entries which
have a leveneshtein distance of two with words
now what will be doing either you are given
with another file called the bigrams dot csf
and it contains all the bigrams with the frequency
with which the bigrams are appearing
so this is very straight forward just like
what we have done previously for unigram dot
csv we are going to use the same set o f code
if you see here i but here i have just written
it in one lag so i have the bigrams file which
i have read and i have spitted into a list
then i define the dictionary called wordbigram
and i store every bigram as my key and the
count as the value so bigrams and unigrams
as tord as now two different dictionary one
is in wordfreq and other is in wordbigram
now suppose i want to calculate the bigram
likelihood as we know the formula is the count
with which the bigram occurs by the count
with which the first word in the bigram occurs
so if i want to calculate the bigram likelihood
of comeback i want in other frequency with
which the comeback is occurring in a particular
corpus and the frequency with which come is
occurring and it turns out that the value
is occurring ten times and come is occur one
forty six times so if i want to calculate
the probability of come back and come i would
do wordbirgam come back divided by word frequency
of come which will give me ten by one forty
six it turns out that the value gives coming
out to be zero so there is certainly a some
problem the problems is that since both come
the frequencies are individual values the
system assumes the answer also should coming
an integer but it turns out that the value
is coming out to be a floating point number
so to handle up there are different ways of
explicit type casting what i am doing here
is just multiply the value with a one point
zero so that before the division occurs one
of the value turns out to be a float so after
the operation is done the value turns out
to be point zero six eight now suppose we
want to calculate the likelihood of the same
bigram but using add one smoothing as we know
add one smoothing basically adds a one to
the numerator for the bigram likelihood and
it also adds to the vocabulary size or the
number of unique words in a corpus to get
the number of unique words in a corpus we
can just take all the keys in the dictionary
and we can find the count of that and the
number of keys and it turns out that the function
length performs the same so i have used the
length function to find all the length of
the keys and with that i print the add one
likelihood after add one smoothing and we
can also see how many unique words are there
in the corpus
so this is pretty much ah for what you can
do with your assignment two and there will
be one question where you are suppose to modify
the course in word for the particular operation
so in that particular question you are suppose
to change the value for substitution as insertion
and deletion involve at cost of one but substitution
involves a cost of two so in order to do that
i am going to modify the value so what this
particular function does is that it compares
whether two characters at a position are same
so if they were not same it returns a one
because this is a logical operation otherwise
it returns a zero so previously the cost was
one so it was left as is now since the cost
is two and just modifying it to be two here
and let us see how much does it cost and how
bimal and vimal compare with this operation
and it turns out that the value becomes two
this is generally done when to want to substitutions
and you want to check more into the insertions
and deletions operations
and for some aspects you might require some
external packages to be installed and i will
be showing you how to install an external
packages suppose i know their exist a package
gensim and i assume that it is installed in
this system i will invoke that external package
using import gensim but it turns out that
the package is not installed so anaconda comes
with a default package manager which you can
select using here anaconda navigator
so anaconda navigator provides you all the
different packages and it provides a reposit
way of different packages that you can install
alternatively you can create a new cell and
you can install a package within the ah notebook
itself what you have to do is that you have
to mind this exclamation mark so you have
type pip install gensim and this will also
help you install the particular package but
you can have in trouble with that you can
by default go to the anaconda navigator and
it will help you install the so i will just
show you how to install this same and that
will be the end of the tutorial session
so here you can click on to the environment
tab and you can see for all packages are reliable
in the repository of anaconda and you can
just type gensim and you can click here you
can say electric and you can apply it to install
as i was suggested you may alternatively use
this command to install if you want to create
a new notebook you should click on the new
and you should go to we should select one
of this so this will give me a new notebook
where you can have a fresh notebook where
you can try out code by yourself so this is
pretty much
thank you yeah