ok so welcome back for the third week of this
course so in the last week where we ended
you are discussing about language modeling
we talked about the basis of language modeling
then we talked about what ah how to be evaluate
a language model and then we came to the topic
of smoothing ok so what was the simple idea
we discussed what is my advanced smoothing
where i add one to each individual count and
accordingly i do some normalization my denominate
and we added by saying there are certain simple
variance possible like at k i can also do
the unigram prior smoothing by instead of
adding uniform weight to each word i at a
weight that is depending on the probability
of that word unigram probability for that
word and that we were arguing that might work
better than simply adding uniform count to
each of the bigrams
there are we had certain parameters like what
what will be a best way of choosing k a and
m in different models ok so simple answer
would be so you ah there is no unique value
that you can choose suppose you have some
held out data so we can try to find out for
which value of k and m you are getting the
best publicity for that held out data and
that can be one possible way of choosing the
values of k and m ok
so now today we will talk we will go beyond
the advanced smoothing and talk about some
other advanced a smoothing methods ok so we
will start with two different a smoothing
methods called good turing smoothing and kneser
ney smoothing so so what is the intuition
behind using a good turing smoothing so intuition
is essentially i want to find out what should
be the probability for the words that i have
not seen in my training data so what give
turing is smoothing says ok so why don't you
use the estimate of the things you have seen
once in your training data you estimate about
the things we have not seen similarly whatever
you have seen twice use that estimate that
things you have you will seen once and like
that ok so this this this just tries to adjust
the probability mass so that the things that
was seen twice are used to find the probability
for the things that was seen once things that
was seen once are used to estimate the probability
for the things that will not seen at all ok
so so the idea is that you we have to use
the count of things we have seen once to find
the count of things we have never seen ok
so for that let us give ah let us first define
what is the frequency of frequency ok we used
this one of the earlier lectures also so we
take this three sentences ok i am here who
am i i would like from this sentences i am
trying to construct the frequency of frequency
so that is how many words occurs once how
many word occurs twice and so on
so so if you see here the word i occurs tries
m occurs twice and the other four words occurs
once so what will my frequency of frequency
i will find out how many of words occurs once
with frequency one so that is my n one so
there are four words here that occur only
once so n is four now you will see how many
words occur twice so how many words have a
frequency of two so that will i will have
one here n three is one so this is my frequency
of frequency ok so four words occur once one
word occurs twice one word occurs tries
now how by use that in good turing estimate
so what is the idea so this we discussed earlier
so i want to reallocate the probability mass
of n grams that occur r plus one times in
the training data to the n grams that occur
r times ok especially you want to see the
n grams that occur one once to find the probability
mass for the n grams that occur zero times
but you that you do that in general ok so
the n grams that occur r plus one times used
that for r times ok
so now in particular reallocate the probability
mass for n grams that were seen once for those
that were never seen so now we should see
formally what will be the effective probability
mass n count that we will get by this good
turing estimate ok so let us see suppose i
have a i want to find out four words that
occurred c times words that occurs c times
what will be the effective adjusted count
after applying good turing estimation ok
so now how we defined that so what would happened
by training data i will have words that occur
zero times words that occur one time let it
be n zero n one words that occur twice n two
and so on so n two numbers that occur twice
similarly now there are n c number of words
that occurs c times n c plus one words that
occurs c plus one times ok
now i want to find i want to use good turing
to estimate the the count for these words
that occur c times so what it be say we said
we will use this probability mass and give
it to these words now how to we distribute
so what is the probability mass associated
with the words that occurs c plus one times
ok
so now suppose there are n words or nth bigrams
in total ok so now what is the probability
mass for the bigrams that occurred or n gram
we can say in general that occurred c plus
one times you see how many n grams are there
there are n c plus one different n grams so
what will be the probability mass for them
it will be
n c plus one times c plus one divided by the
total number of n grams that are n that is
a probability mass yes and this i am distributing
to the words that occur c times now how many
words are there there are n c words so what
is the probability that each of them will
get divided by n c yes so now so this is the
probability mass for that each of them will
get now what will be the effective count remember
how we define the effective count c star such
that if i if i divided by n merely this will
give me the same probability so that will
tell me c star is n c plus one times c plus
one divided by n c and that's what we have
written here ok so n c in general is the n
grams that ah seen exactly c terms in the
corpus so by using this definition i can find
out what is effective count for any word that
is occur n c number of times in the corpus
ok
so that's what we have seen so this this is
the probability for the words things let us
in c times c star n yes c star is my nothing
but my effective n gram count ok now what
about the words that will not seen at all
that are the words that that or whenever i
am saying words here it means the n terms
in general so what about the n grams that
did not occur at all matter in data
so frommy definition i will use the probability
mass of the words that was seen once ok so
what will be the probability mass so there
are by definition there are n one words that
was seen once so each one of them occurs once
so what is the probability mass it is n one
by n yes and this probability mass i will
give to the words that was seen zero times
yes
now you might have a question how much of
this each of them individual we will get so
this is the probability mass that are the
word the n grams are did not occurs in the
corpus to get that we will get but how much
of this individually each of them will get
so if you can just divided by the number of
n grams that did not occur in the corpus so
we will see some by some example how we can
be estimate this value ok
so here if my count is zero so good turing
estimate for the things that for the frequency
c when c zero is n one by n that we just saw
ok so that is a effective probability mass
that i will give to the all the words or n
grams they did not occur in the training data
ok so this gives me nice methods of estimating
the probability for the words are did not
occur in my training data
now there are certain complications that you
might have when you applying this good turing
estimate so for a small c generally you will
see that n c greater than n c plus one that
is a number of words having a frequency c
is greater than number of words having a frequency
c plus one so remember what is what would
be empiric empirical law that shares that
so that is a japes law that's that is shared
that there is a universal relationship so
this is generally good it but it might happen
when we go to very very high frequencies certain
ah certain certain frequency are not observing
that so this is possible ok
so what do we do in general so when we go
to higher and higher frequencies for larger
ks or larger cs here we can replace it with
some sort of best fit power law and we will
do some normalizations ok so instead of doing
it for each individual k i might actually
just fit so the so the i have n one n two
and so on and when i go to the higher values
i simply sit fit some sort of power law and
that is so that it is normalized and i will
obtain the same probability mass that is one
ok
so this is power law can can be fit it in
general so in in various toolkits that you
might very you might use this methods they
they do it for only few values of k summation
few values of k it maybe k is equal to five
or k is equal to ten ok in then the the formula
that we were using might have to be real adjusted
ok but the basic idea was is same what we
have seen here ok
so now suppose you apply this good turing
smoothing methods for a corpus like a p neswire
academic academic press news there are twenty
two million words and so that's why you are
seeing for different counts what is the good
turing estimate that was seen this is for
bigrams ok so what yours observing in the
table so for the bigrams that occurred zero
number of times the good turing estimate was
point zero zero zero zero two seven zero ok
for once point four four six for twice point
one two six now so how do i actually get this
number point zero zero zero zero two seven
zero so we can just do that quickly
so remember for the words that occur zero
times what is the total probability that we
are giving them getting the probability of
n one divided by n ok now what is the probability
given to the individual word so you multiplied
by n zero and n zero is the number of bigrams
that occurring zero times ok what would be
the effective count effective count we will
remove this n yes so it will be n one divided
by n zero now what is n one so you need to
find out how many bigrams occurred once yes
that you can find from training data how do
you find n zero that is how many bigrams did
not occurred in my data now if you remember
from shakespeare corpus so we ah how do we
find out how many bigrams did not occur at
all so we need to see what is my vocabulary
size what are different sym ah different unigrams
ok
suppose in my vocabulary size of v that is
my number of unigrams so how many bigrams
are possible v square bigrams are possible
so how many actually occurred suppose i know
that out of this some n b bigrams occurred
in my corpus so v square minus nb gives me
the bigrams that did not occur at all in my
corpus so this will become my n zero number
of bigrams that did not occurred in my corpus
so this value i obtain by finding out n one
number of bigrams that occur once divided
by v square minus n v and these are number
of bigrams in total so that is the unique
bigrams that occur in my corpus ok
now what is the other objection that you might
have from this table while looking at this
table so for zero and one this is different
but once you start seeing from two on words
what is the pattern that you seen you see
that most of the effective counts are the
original count minus some value like point
seven five ok so you see all of these a roughly
original value minus point two seven to seven
five so now one might are give why don't i
just you see minus point zero five seven point
zero seven five ok in maybe give a different
value to the initial two components that is
also done in practice ok so this is called
the absolute discounting that should you will
see next
so the idea is that why don't i substract
something like point seven five or some d
from each bigram that occur more than say
more than once or or whatever ok and i can
have one or two different values of d for
some initial bigrams and this is called the
absolute discounting methods and you you can
probably interpolated with my unigram probability
that we saw in the last lecture to give it
give a weight estimate yes this is called
linear inter ah interpolation with the unigram
probability of the absolute discounting method
and that is the formula that we have written
here so this is i am doing some sort of discounting
from each bigram count yes
plus i am interpolating it with my unigram
probability with weight some lambda w i minus
one you do we need a weight here so that when
i saw this probability probability absolute
discounting [noises] w i given w i minus one
for each individual w i this will add up to
one that's why i need some sort of normalization
constant that will make sure that this will
add up to one
ok
so we can keep probably some values of d d
for count one and two and otherwise i can
use this particular interpolation methods
now that's why the idea of our other advanced
smoothing model comes that was our kneser
ney smoothing man methods so what is that
ok so that is can we do better than using
the regular unigram correct ok so so see so
when before we first started with a simple
ah advanced smoothing we were giving uniform
weight to each ah each particular n gram uniform
addition then from they moved on to unigram
prior we said ok why do we give uniformly
we we give a higher weight to the words that
occur more often in my corpus
now we have seen can be do better than even
this and that's why we will see the kneser
ney smoothing idea so what is the idea so
know again let us go to the shannon game ok
suppose at this sentence i can't see without
my reading and have to filling this blank
and suppose possibilities are glasses and
francisco and all of us will say ok i should
fill in glasses now take a scenario where
reading glasses doesn't occur in my training
data and reading francisco also doesn't occur
in my training data
now if i use the previous model what will
i do the probability of filling in glasses
versus francisco depend on their unigram probabilities
and suppose this is my data from some yours
corpus so i will find probability of francisco
is higher than probability of glasses ok that
can very well happened and that will that
that means i will add up filling it francisco
here there is not the correct word correct
choice here ok so can we do something better
than simply using their unigram probabilities
that is the idea of kneser ney smoothing so
francisco is more common than glasses in my
data but can i use this idea that in my data
whenever see francisco it occurs only after
san in in this occurrence san francisco
on the other hand whenever i see glasses it
occurs some ah after mul multiple different
words ok so this is the intuition that is
i will see given a word what are the other
words it comes with ok so here if i take word
is francisco it occurs maybe with only one
word yes only one word san but glasses occurs
with many other words right it can occur with
different different words and this so so both
glasses are occurs occurs with ten different
words and francisco occurs with only one different
word so what is the intuition if a word occurs
with many other words that means it is more
likely to complete this particular bigram
that we are seeing right now
so reading after reading a word is more likely
to occur if it has already completed many
other bigram so if it is more commonly used
bigrams with many many other words this will
not happen with francisco because francisco
is used only after san so given a new context
probably san francis francisco is not good
choice but glasses are occur many many other
different words so after read ah completely
new context glasses is a better choice than
francisco so formally how this method used
this intuition
so in instead of using simple probability
of this word unigram probability each probability
continuation word so that is how likely is
this word to appear as a novel continuation
what do you mean by novel continuation how
likely it is to complete a bigram or in n
gram so how do i find out the probability
so for each word to find this probability
as we said we have to count the number of
bigram types it completes so how many bigrams
where it occurs as the last one the final
word ok
now for each bigram whenever it occur the
first time it was like a novel continuation
so that's what we mean by novel continuation
probability here that how many bigrams it
is complete so this will be simply it will
be proportional to the number of bigrams it
is completing so here how many w i minus one
are there such that w occurs after that in
my corpus so that is the property of continuation
ok it's a same thing how what is the probability
of continuation that should depend on the
number of bigrams types it completes now how
should i normalized it i want to find this
probability for each word in the corpus yes
so this is proportion to the number of bigrams
types it completes so i should find out in
total how many bigram types are there that
each word is completing so that is effective
their number of bigram types in total not
totals the number of bigram types how many
different bigram types are there ok so here
also we are only taking the types how many
different bigram types we are completing
so i will normalized it by using all possible
bigrams so here there says all possible bigrams
because i am saying the count is greater than
zero in my training data how many bigram types
i have seen so this will give me the probability
continuation the word the w ok so once i have
found this probability i can even go back
to my unigram prior based absolute discounting
method and replace p w i by p continuation
w i ok and that is my kneser ney smoothing
model so instead of using the unigram priors
for smoothing i used this kneser ney smoothing
by using the continuation probability ok
so if i do that a frequent word like francisco
occurring only in one context of san will
have a low continuation probability so this
will give an model with kneser nay smoothing
you see so all these are there is all same
this is same now instead of p w i we are put
p continuation w i that we get from the previous
ah slide whatever map whatever ah formula
we wrote in the previous slide that will give
me this continuation p w i ok
so now this one question here that we discus
even the in the earlier example how do we
find lambda w i minus one so what was the
intuition i gave the hint was that lambda
w i minus one should be such that summation
over k n smoothing of w i given w i minus
one for all w i in my vocabulary should be
one so now again take it as a simple exercise
that suppose i want to find out what will
be the value of lambda w i minus one for this
particular formula ok and you can assume that
d less between zero to one ok for this particular
case what is the value of lambda lambda w
i minus one that i will get ok so answer is
also on this slide so you will get lambda
w i minus one of this so try to find out if
i have to cons satisfy the constant of the
summation of the probabilities for all the
words should add up to one what is the value
of lambda that i add up with ok in that will
give you this value particular value ok
now so other than these two models of good
turing and kneser ney smoothing there are
other other smoothing models at you might
be able to use ok so one simple idea instead
of using a new smoothing model why don't we
combine various models so remember we always
doing that somewhere so you computing bigram
i was trying to use the probability of the
unigram for unigram priors smoothing now can
i generalized this idea suppose i am finding
out the trigram probability trigram language
model now from my data i can compute the trigram
language model probabilities bigram and uni
unigram using the m l e can i try to effectively
combined these different probability models
to find my trigrams language model ok
so there are actually two very very popular
ways in which this can be done one is called
interpretation based methods another is called
back of language models so you will just see
ah some simple intuition how this can be combined
together so so what we have seen as i increased
my n power of my n gram model increases we
also see saw that in my when i saw the perplexity
values when i take a larger n gram i get lower
perplexity i get better perplexity that means
so that means the the the model becomes much
better when i take a larger n but what is
the problem that happens if i take a larger
n remember why we did all this is smoothing
because when i am taking larger n data becomes
more and more is fast so many of the actual
n grams become zero the probability become
zero
so at one side higher n gram is better a trigram
model is better other side is very very fast
so why cant i take advantage of the both both
things that is i take a higher order n gram
model whenever i have the data but whenever
i do not have the data i try to use the low
n gram model so i do that togetherness single
model so that is the basic idea of these model
that we will see
so now general approach is can be combined
multiple n gram models to get a single model
that can had that can also take the advantage
of larger n gram model but avoid this fastness
problem ok so that is some cases might have
to use less context whenever you do not have
information about larger data larger context
so in back off what you will do suppose i
am computing a a trigram language model so
w i given w i minus one w i minus two whenever
this trigram occurs in my training data i
will use the probability as for my m l e but
if i does not if it does not occur in my training
data i will back off to my bigram language
model so that means whenever the count of
w i minus one w i is greater than zero i will
go to bi bigram suppose that is also zero
when i go to unigram this is idea of back
off language model so if you have good evidence
you go to trigram otherwise you go to bigram
otherwise you go to unigram ok
on the other hand interpolation you compute
all three and just interpolate than together
you try to mix these together ok so so let
us see what do will do in back off language
models so idea is that i am computing a trigram
model w i given w i minus two ah i minus one
and so here this is the previous word and
this is previous to previous word ok so if
i do not have counts for w i minus two w i
minus one w i suppose this is zero then i
use probability w i given w i minus one
now suppose count of w i minus one w i is
also zero then you go to probability w i ok
now seen but you might add up having some
problems with how do i normalized the final
probability distribution that i will get ok
so so this is the particular formula formula
of back off that you can use so back off for
this trigram model w i given w i minus two
w i minus one is p hat w i given w i minus
two w i minus one if the count is greater
than zero
now what is p hat this is actually similar
to my maximum likelihood estimate that you
will get but it has been something has been
subtracted from there so some probability
mass has been shown from there so there it
when it can be given to the other counts why
we ne need that suppose you are computing
bigram this ah trigram back off probability
model
so in general you are doing it after w i minus
two w i minus one you are finding for various
words w one w two w three ok suppose this
occurs three times this occurs two times this
occurs zero times so now once use the m l
e method ah estimate immediately this will
have a probability of three by five this i
have two probability two of two by five suppose
there is no other bigram and this will have
a probability of zero and now you want to
use back off to go to two five use probability
w three given w i minus one but here itself
probability mass adding up to one so how can
you use the bigram probability so far that
you might have to reduce some mass from these
two values so that's why we are writing p
hat and there are different ways you can reduce
so we will take someone simple example we
are a doing it by some ah simple constant
you are re ah reducing some simple constants
but this this can be proportional also you
can multiply some ok
so will you will take that is my p hat it's
a reduced probability value from my m l e
constant ok so now if the count is greater
than zero i take p hat if the count is equal
to zero then i have to use the previous i
have to back off to the bigram model so i
have to use probability w i given w i minus
one and that's where i back off to this model
but what is interest thing that you have seeing
here so this is a recursive definition i am
using the back off probability of w i given
w i minus one and i multiplying with some
constant again to ensure that the probability
mass adds up to one ok
so now so the recursive definition so how
do we define probability w w i given w i minus
one again it's p hat w i given w i minus one
if the count is greater than zero and p hat
w n if the count is equal to zero ok so i
think it will help a if you take a simple
example and try to see how do we actually
use this definition to compute the back off
probabilities ok
so let's take an example ok so here we are
taking an corpus where we are having only
four words a b c and d and this is one data
that is provided so what is this is data so
this is it is telling how many times a occurs
after a b it occurs four times on the other
hand b occurs after a b zero times c occurs
after a b zero times ok similarly a occurs
after b five times b b occur after b three
times c occur after b zero times and also
the individual word words a occurs eight times
b occurs nine times c occurs eight times d
occurs seven times now given this data you
ask to compute the prob back off probability
model of w n given w n minus one where the
previous word is b and previous to previous
word is a ok
and you have also told that you can use this
simple definition for p hat that is p x minus
one by eight suppose i want to use that to
find out the back off probability distribution
ok now so that is nothing but probability
back off of word given a and b a is pervious
to previous word and b is the previous word
ok so let us take to do that so i want to
find out the back off probability w given
a b so this would be w can take a b c and
d so right now from my table what are the
counts i am seeing e occurs so this occurs
four times this occurs zero times this occurs
zero times this occurs zero times ok so assumed
by definition of back off probability i can
say that this probability will be p hat a
given a b because the count is greater than
the zero but this will be lambda times previous
two words a b so this lambda a b a constant
times back off probability of so i will go
to the previous word back off probability
of b given b this will be lambda a b times
back off back off probability of c given the
previous word b and this will be lambda a
b back off probability of d given b
so what it say is that now we have to compute
the back off probability of b given b c given
b and d given b ok so again we use the definition
so now i am computing back off probability
of w given b and w is equal to a b c and d
now i see a occurs five times b occurs three
times c occurs zero times d occurs zero times
so i show my definition this will be p hat
a given b what will be that that will be five
by eight yes minus one by eight that is four
by eight what will be this p hat b given b
three by eight minus one by eight that is
two by eight now what will be this this is
this occurs zero number of times so this will
be lambda of b times unigram probability of
c maybe p hat c ok
now what is this we can see from my data what
is p hat c so c occurs a times yes and total
number of so what is the total of my ah unigram
count if you will add up to thirty two ok
so this so p c the mle varies so it's lambda
b times p c minus one by eight p c is eight
by thirty two yes so this will become eight
by thirty two one by four minus one by eight
that will be lambda b times one by eight ok
similarly for d is equal to zero i can write
lambda b times p hat d that is that is lambda
b times p d minus one by eight ok that is
lambda b times p d here was seven by thirty
two seven by thirty two minus one by eight
ok so that would be lambda b times this will
be seven minus four three by thirty two ok
so suppose you get this values
now how will you compute the the how will
you go to the probability b a w given a b
you have to first find what is the back off
probabilities of for these two two cases c
and d so far that you define the what is the
value of lambda b now how do you find lambda
b if you normalized this right so you will
say lambda b times one by eight plus three
by thirty two plus four by eight plus two
by eight should give me one right this should
be one for if you sum over all the words so
so what this is this say lambda b times seven
by thirty two is equal to one minus six five
eight that is two by eight so what is lambda
b so we will get ok
so you will get this eight by seven so once
a we substitute add up this eight by seven
here that will give you this probability eight
so you will find this probability and this
probability also so you have the back off
probability for this now put this back off
probability here and we have a constant how
do you find this constant again you will have
two normalized it lambda a b times summation
of this plus this probability should add up
to one that will give you my lambda a b and
also give you this probability distribution
so that's why you find the back off probability
distribution using this recursive definition
ok and what do you linear interpolation we
have different unigram bigram trigram orders
i try to interpret them in different proportions
ok so what we are doing here we have computed
a trigram model bigram model unigram model
and different proportions lambda one lambda
two lambda three are given to this ok
so such that they will add up to one in general
you can also conditional lambdas on the context
ok what is your previous an and previous to
previous word the lambda might depend on that
so this is the same same equation except that
now lambda is a depending on the context ok
and now the question might be how do i choose
a held out corpus how do i choose my lambdas
so that you will do as we say earlier you
will have an held out corpus will find out
which values are lambda gives you the highest
probability and that that lambdas you can
has for your smoothing ok
so that's we will finish our topic of language
model so all so we covered lot of sim simple
ah smoothing methods and some advanced smoothing
methods and then we will now go to the next
topic of ah so we will start with the topic
of morphology ok so that will be the topic
of the next lecture ok