so hello everyone so welcome back for the
second module of third week so in the last
week we had so in the last week in the last
module we were discussing about language modeling
that is how we can effectively use the word
ordering information for where is applications
we will go to the next topic we will talk
about the morphology information that what
are the different modules that help us captures
information [an/and] what are different linguistic
terms that are involved so today we will start
with the linguistic terms and then we will
and with what the are possible modules that
can help us capture this in a in an automatic
panel so what is so we are talking about computation
morphology today so what is morphology in
morphology we study what is internal structure
of words so that is given a particular word
in a language what are the [dif/different]
meaningful units it is made up off and each
small unit is called a morphemes so let us
take some examples so if i take the word dogs
so it is made up of two different units one
is dog the actual root word and another is
affix that is applied to the word to make
it a plural that is ok so there are two morphemes
in this single word dogs similarly if i take
a word like un lady like so we are having
three different units here so these are three
different morphemes so un that corresponds
to not irrigation or opposition then lady
well behave women like that is having the
characteristic of so there are three different
morphemes that together constitute this single
word (Refer Time:02:00)
so now we will also see what are the various
linguistic notions that that you might be
my want to be aware of and we are talking
about morphology so for example what are allomorphs
so is given a word like happy if you are converting
to it is opposites we are making ah a word
like unhappy but if i take ah another word
like rational i will i will use i r so i will
make irrational so if they are different morphemes
that can be use for the same purpose they
are called allomorphs ok so here is an example
so so allomorphs we are saying variants of
the same morphemes but in general we cannot
replace by one another so so let us see here
so if i have the word happy i can use u n
to make it unhappy comprehensible i can use
i n incomprehensible if a possible i can use
i m impossible and rational i will say irrational
ok but you can see that we cannot replace
i r by u n here so i cannot say unrational
that is not a valid english word so there
are various ah reasoning for why a particular
morpheme is used one of these is could be
because of the phonemes that are they are
in the in the particular word so irrational
we have the irrational with happy we have
unhappy so that is the for different words
we have different sort of morphemes that you
apply to make opposites so that is for one
particular function but for different functions
like and and ah person and all that you again
have various person and all that you again
have various ah category morphemes that are
applied
so again when we talk about morphemes there
is a distinction called bound morphemes verses
free morphemes so what are those so bound
morphemes are those morphemes that cannot
appear as a word by itself ok so for example
take the previous example unhappy so i cannot
take the morpheme un here use it as a as a
unique single word itself so this is bound
by another word that is applied with this
say unhappy so it is it is bound with happy
or some other words with this you can be use
it on the other hand if i take the word happy
it is [free/free morphemes] it can used on
it is soon ok that is how we divide the morphemes
into these two categories bound verses free
so here are some examples so bound morphemes
are like s so it can be used for making plural
so with dog we have dogs l y so quick to quickly
and e d walk to walked so these are all bound
morphemes and then there are free morphemes
when they can appear as a word by themselves
ok and they can also combine with other morphemes
if needed so for example if i take the morphemes
like house it can appeared as a word by itself
but can also be combine with other morphemes
like s to make plural houses similarly walk
it can combine with e d to make a plu[ral]-
make a past tens of walked and so on some
words like of ah in etcetera they are also
free morphemes they can appear on their own
so then there is another distinction and this
is very very important when we talk about
morphology so in general when i talk about
a word it can have two main parts one is the
stem the main the root word and another is
the affix and it can have more than one of
affixes as well so what are stem and affixes
ok so when we talk about a word so ah a stem
is the core meaning bearing part ok so i take
i take a word like boys so the the the stem
here will be boy so that is the meaning can
bearing part and then there are various ah
bits and pieces that can be apply to it that
that can ultra certain grammatical functions
so i can have i can apply and as at the end
of to make a plural of this so these are called
affixes so in general you can make a correspondence
between ah stems and affixes and bound and
free morphemes so you can say that the stems
are kind of free morphemes and the affixes
are kind of bound morphemes so this kind of
correspondence you can you can make
so now what are the different types of affixes
that you can apply with the given stem so
this we just discuss about one simple example
of applying s so this s apply after the word
boy are make a plural with boys so this is
called suffix that is applied at the end of
the word but in general what are the different
types of affixes that can be applied so so
we start with prefixes so prefixes are applied
before the word so some example in english
are un so we make unhappy anti antinational
pre preexisting and so on we have these prefixes
in other languages also for example in hindi
and sanskrit we have (Refer Time: 07: 00)
the prefixes like ah [FL] that we can apply
with various words or verbs so these are of
prefixes
then we have suffixes that are applied after
the word so like with the word talk i can
make a new word talking by applying the suffix
by i n g similarly the word quick i can make
a new word quickly by applying the suffix
l l y at the end ok and in in the case of
hindi for example you can have this exercise
like tha and k a ka etcetera that can apply
after the words
then so the prefix and suffix are the major
major su[sufix]- major suffixes affixes that
we have in language but certain language have
some other kind of exercise also so one is
called infix that is it is applied in between
that stem not before or after that so ah so
example is like in sanskrith we have the word
with to know and we make the present tense
by putting vindati so the word the the character
n the phonin n is applied in between between
v and the so you becom becomes vindati so
there are examples in other languages also
like in the case of philippines here basa
b a s a is read and to make it the to converted
to the past tense read the infix u m is applied
in between so we have b u m a s a so u m is
applied in between is called infix now so
can we think of an infix in the case of english
english it is not common in in common language
it is not infix is not used but in general
can we make a word in english that that uses
infix so so here an example is if i take the
word absolutely and put a word bloody inside
so you can have a word like [ab/absolute]
bloodilutely so this is to put some emphasis
that is not used in common english (Refer
Time:09:00) but in ah certain movie dialogues
and all you can find such kind of words
finally so what can what you think can be
the fourth category we have prefix suffix
infix what is the meaning is that a suffix
an affix comes before as well as after so
this is called circumfix ok so this proceeds
as well as follows the same word so an example
in dutch so you have a word for mountain b
e r g and to to converted to plural we have
an affix that is applied before g e as well
as after so the the whole affix is g e t e
half of that is applied before and half of
that is applied after so this is called circumfix
so among this four kind of affixes the first
two are very very common prefix and suffix
and the last two are expressive to certain
languages only
now morphemes can also be divided into some
other categories like content verses (Refer
Time:10:00) functional morphemes so what are
content morphemes that are those that will
that will be a semantic meaning ok so for
example if even if i take any free morphemes
like car a word it is always a content morphemes
it contents some semantic meaning similarly
i can take a morpheme bound morpheme like
able also that is a semantic meaning that
given a word it it it keeps a sense of being
able to do something so on the other hand
there are certain morphemes that are functional
that do not take the semantic content they
are only used for certain grammatical functions
like as for plural as for third singular they
are both functional morphemes you apply it
after a word and it has a particular grammatical
meaning but it may not be a syman[tic]- it
may not contain a semantic meaning as such
now so based on whatever kind of affixes that
you that you apply to a word (Refer Time:11:00)
you will generate a new word ok so for example
if i if i have a word walk and i apply a suffix
i n g i get a new word like walking ok so
there is a process that converts a word walk
to walking ok so by putting certain morphology
here now take another example i take a verb
like drive and i i add some affix and make
a new word like driver so now what is the
differences that you see in the two processes
ok so we can call it may be e r drive plus
e r that gives you driver so from drive we
can creating driver verses from walk you are
creating walking so what is the difference
that you see in the two processes (Refer Time:12:0)
so if you think about it in the first case
we not changing the grammatical category of
the word as such ok so this is a verb walk
it remains the verb here also walking but
we add some grammatical information as a continuous
text on the continuance other hand here you
start with the verb drive and we end up making
a noun you covert the category of of the verb
itself by this process of morphology so there
are two different kind of morphological processes
so this is called inflectional morphology
and this is called derivational morphology
ok so so in this slide we are seeing the difference
between between these so so they they they
give you the relation between two words that
you have you have created first case you have
created from walk to walking so what is the
relation between these two words second case
you created drive to driver what is the relation
between these two words (Refer Time:13:00)
so in flectional morphology if makes changes
in the terms of numbers tens case and gender
ok so for example if you start with the word
verb bring you can alter the case you can
have brought you can have third person singular
brings and so on so they do not ah change
the ah category of this word so but you add
some more grammatical information that is
all so this is called inflectional morphology
you are adding certain inflectional information
only in the grammatical sense that is not
change in the category of the word on the
other hand you have derivational morphology
where you create some new words and you also
change the change the category of the word
so this is called part of speech that we will
take up in the same week in in the in the
fourth module so it changes the category of
the word so for example from logic you can
make logical and illogical logicality logician
and all that and there you can you can see
(Refer Time:14:00) the do not have the same
category all these words they have they are
different categories one is noun adverb and
and so on adjective
in general derivational morphology is also
fairly systematic like inflectional morphology
but sometimes certain derivations will be
missing ok so for example here is here is
some nice examples so if i take the word sincere
i can make sincerity scarce scarcity curious
curiosity but from fierce you should not use
like fiercity ok although it is very very
if it looks very very regular if you starts
seen from the previous words so they are pretty
regular but some words do not have the corresponding
derivational words
now so we are talked about whatever the various
kind of morphemes ok and what are the process
what are the different types of affixes that
you can apply but in general what are the
various morphological process that are involved
(Refer Time:15:00) to convert one word into
another word ok so so we will talk about this
so for so one simple process is called concatenation
so we will take various morphemes and concatenate
together to make a new new morpheme ok so
for example happy un you make unhappy simple
concatenation similarly here hope and less
together make hopeless and un happy make unhappy
and anti capital i s t and s these four morphemes
if you concatenate together and then make
a single word or singular morpheme
so now then we are combining the different
morphemes together at the boundary or when
they are combined there may be certain changes
ok the changes can be in in the way the final
word is pronounced or in the way the final
word is writen so there is two are called
fundamic changes and graphemic changes graphemic
in the terms how the word is written (Refer
Time:16:00) and phenomic in the way word is
pronounced so here some examples so if i take
a word book and if morpheme book and a morpheme
s if i combined together i get books so s
see the pronunciation if i take shoe and s
i get shoes so here it is not s it is za it
is a different phonyms that terms so there
are certain changes that happen at the boundary
in terms of how the word is pronounced similarly
if i take word like happy and e r these change
at the graphic graphemiclable so where in
the grapheme y changes to i so this is also
called simply spelling change at the at the
morpheme boundary so this can happen there
are some morphological processes also like
reduplication so then we adding in a suffix
you might do reduplication somewhere in the
stem
so example is (Refer Time:17:00) like in number
language if i take a word go or look if i
want to say examine with attention i will
say i will just repeat the go go similarly
in tagalog you have basa for read and if i
want to say will read i will i will read duplicate
ba ba ba sa so you reduplicating one part
ok in sanskrit again this is very common phenomena
or reduplication i take the word like much
that is to cook and if i if i want to converted
it to the perfect form cooked i will reduplicate
the pa and i say papaca so you see the word
pa is reduplicated they can be reduplication
also ah in in certain languages also ok example
in telugu so certain phrase is repeated again
so for example i want to say the child fell
down while walking so here i say [FL] so here
[FL] is being repeated twice for saying while
walking ok there are other morphological like
suppletion where a word is completely ah replaced
by something that has no connection at the
ah surface lavel so i have a word like go
and i am converting into the past tense and
it becomes went so you cannot find any connection
go and went and this are surface label this
is simple supplition similarly with good i
can make better ok and there are many examples
in english for this sometimes there some internal
changes in the morpheme so from from sing
you want convert the plural you will so from
sing you can get sang and sung for different
ten tenses and from men to converted to plural
and you get m e n ok and from goose you get
geese for converting to plural so you see
there are there are changes there are in internally
in in the word you not adding any new suffix
then while we are talking about word formation
they another process called compounding so
that is i can take two different words and
make a compound out of that ok and this compounding
can be from various part of speech for example
in english i can two take two adjectives so
bitter and sweet i can make adject single
compound bitter sweet i can take two nouns
rain and bow i can make a noun rainbow i can
take a noun and verb pick and pocket and this
becomes a verb pickpocket ok similarly over
do what is interesting is that these compounds
are very very particular to languages ok
so let us take an example like room temperature
that is a that is a compound in english but
is there a corresponding compound in hindi
so you you never say [FL] as a single compound
you will say [FL] so that means so finding
this compound is in interesting problem for
going to application like machine translation
so where you you cannot just directly convert
the words into the equivalent ah ah target
languages so you cannot say room with combined
temperature with [FL] you need to find out
with there is a compound there is relation
between the two words and according to the
translation
then there is another process that is called
acronyms ok for example the word laser is
an acronyms then there is blending ok
so your take so this is again a very common
process linguistic so were you take two words
and then you combine together blend them together
to make a new word but the you are taking
from both the words but you not taking the
full words so example is breakfast and lunch
you can take together and make a new word
like brunch ok similarly smoke and fog you
make a new word a smog motor motor and hotel
make a word like a motel ok and there is a
process of clipping ok so that used a lot
for example i have doctor doctor becomes doc
laboratory becomes lab and advertising because
becomes add dormitory becomes dom and examination
becomes exam bicycle becomes bike and refrigerator
becomes fridge so this is clipping so long
words are shortened
so now so this is all the different processes
that happens in happen in morphology now so
from the n l p prospective so we will talk
about how do we process of morphology so what
do a what does it and until what processing
of morphology so what are different things
that that are done so one simple thing is
lemmatization that is given a word can identify
what is the root word what is the lemma ok
an example is is if a give me a word like
saw can i tell what is the root word is it
a if it is a verb the root word what will
be see ah but if it is a noun the root word
will be saw itself so you can find a what
is the root word silly it is lemma there is
there is a morphological analysis also so
that is even a word can i find out what is
the corresponding lemma along with morphological
category of that word ok so it is particular
tag so example is i take a verb word like
saw can i tell the the lemma is see and this
a past tense of that verb or saw is the lemma
and it is a noun singular noun so this is
morphological analysis of the given word
then there is a process called tagging so
where i find out what is the actual ah so
what is the actual category of this word so
the difference here is from the morphology
analysis that i also have to disambiguate
so morphological analysis you saw i was giving
two different possibilities in tagging i have
to further find out what is the actual correct
grammatical category here so i have a sentence
is peter saw her i know the word saw can be
either a noun or verb and we also so their
lemmas but can i say can i tell in this particular
context the word saw will only be a verb and
not a noun so can i do the actual disambiguation
also this is that is how tagging is different
from the morphological analysis and then we
have a morphological segmentation where given
a word i can segment to with different morpheme
that involved so i have a word like denationalization
i said de nation a l i z ation they are different
morphemes that are in this word so in general
among all these processes so part of speech
tagging is very very popular so will words
sometime for that and before that we will
quickly see what is ah morphological analysis
lemmatization how it is done
ok and finally there is also these process
of generalization where i can take a word
a root word and a particular grammatical category
and i have to generate a a a new word from
this so see ah and i want to generate past
tense i want to find out saw ok in n l p it
is not very popular unless you are talking
about national language generation where you
might want to use this ok so ya before going
into the process what might be the application
for doing this why should we be interested
in doing morphological analysis for example
text to speech synthesis ok so what is text
to speech synthesis you have seen something
that is written and you have to find produce
the corresponding is speech speech for that
so now if you have a word like lead written
somewhere now depending on whether it is a
noun or a verb you will have a different pronunciation
for that ok lead verses led depending on noun
or a verb so it is important of find out from
the text whether it is a noun or verb ok same
thing goes with read ok read verses red in
general it is very important for other things
likes search and information retrieval ok
so might want to use the a morphological category
to reduce the certain space ok and also machine
translation we saw some example and especially
because if you know the morphological category
you can find out the for the target languages
what is corresponding affix is or different
words that is being used in that languages
and grammatical error correction and and all
that so if you if you know what is the morphological
category of this word in the whatever is written
if you can find out this is not the correct
morphology that is use you can try to correct
it
so now what is morphological analysis so this
is have seen earlier so as i input we have
words like cats cat citizen so on and as an
output i want to find out given a word like
cats what is the root verb here cat what is
category noun and it is a plural cat plus
n plus p l something like that so in this
table so if i am a given input in the left
as per the left column i want a output like
the right column ok so so the output that
i will generate will contain additional information
like this i0073 noun this is singular for
s g for singular p l for plural and v for
verb like that so this is all the information
that i want to get from the from the given
word now what might be the issues involved
while doing morphological analysis one particular
problem is that it is not very very regular
for example from the word boy i can get plural
boys but what happens if i taken input like
fly i get flies f l i e s ok so this you see
that they are following two different sort
of tools for doing changes at the bounding
similarly if i take the word like toiling
i can get toil but what happens if i give
an input like duckling should i used same
sort of full to get duckl that is not correct
of english word ok so how do i know the duckling
is not a correct english word when an input
like a duckling is provides to my system similarly
from getter i get g e t plus e r from doer
d o plus e r but what happens if given input
like beer do i output like b e plus e r so
these are some of the issues that involved
in processing morphology now if i have to
solve these issues what is what are the different
knowledge that i need to have
so so i need to have some knowledge on what
are the different words or fruits in english
ok so for example i need to know that duck
is a possible root but duckl is not a possible
root in english so we need some sort of dictionary
or lexicon of english what are different nouns
and verbs etcetera in english what else i
need to have some knowledge of morpho techniques
what is morpho techniques that is which kind
of morphemes follow other kind of morphemes
for example if i have to convert a noun to
plural i know plural morphems always follow
the noun so this is the morphotactics information
which morpheme follows are the morphemes then
i also need to have this information that
some endings go only on certain words not
on everything
so on d o i can apply e r to get doer but
on b e on the verb b e i cannot apply e r
to get a word like beer so this is again these
constraints also i need to have and then i
need to some worry about spell spelling change
rules so then whenever i have word like get
i apply e r it converts to getter so there
is just duplication on of duplication of the
ending t
so now so one question you might have is that
ok why cant i put everything together in a
big lexicon so that is all the root words
all their morphological variants why cannot
they already put in a big lexicon and there
i can search even new word i can search in
the lexicon find out what is the actual word
and its category if they are finite by country
do that so there are two different reasons
why this may not be very good solution so
one is if you take any language like english
it is very easy so where for a given but they
are not many variations in terms of morphology
so ah so this is some strategies from a data
set that in english there are roughly you
take ninety thousand lexical entries and you
will find out all the possible morphological
forms that you can generate then you find
a ratio of three point five two one that is
from word you can generate roughly three point
five more very to variants including that
word in english but this is not true for other
languages for example the same thing if you
do for sanskrit you have a lexicon of one
seventy thousand entries but if you try to
derive the forms so the ratio that you come
up with is something like sixty four point
seven is to one ok so the eleven million forms
that are generate so these are huge in number
ok so sixty four is a very big ratio in comparison
to three points five but again this may for
now it may not be a very big number again
ok you can still argue that this might this
will it be put in a big lexicon and and you
can search over that but there is another
problem ok that is you can keep on coining
new words and apply the same morphological
processes to generate its forms and you do
not know these words a prior so you cannot
store their morphological variants in the
lexicon so on the other hand if you can store
the what kind of rules in valued for mailing
from a word to its plural given a new plural
form you can try to find out its original
root word ok
so that is why we will be studying what kind
of methods are possibly used and the one of
the most popular method in this field of computation
morphology finally state methods ok so this
was very very popular earlier first the language
like english also and and later on for other
languages like indian languages another european
language so even now if you talk about processing
the morphology methods are one of the most
popular choices so fine so in this lecture
we talked about composition morphology what
are the linguistics terminologies and and
what is the process as such what is the n
l p perspective there and in the next lecture
we will talk about how do i use final state
methods for this processing ok
thank you