so welcome back for the third module of this
week so in the last lecture we were talking
about computational morphology ok so so in
this module we will talk about how do we use
financial math methods for doing this morphological
analysis ok so i will just go in briefly into
what these models do so starting with what
is a finite state automaton ok so if you have
taken a course on formal languages automaton
theory or theory of computation you might
already be aware of what is a finite automaton
i will just briefly tell what is what what
is this ok if you haven't taken a course that
course you might just want to quickly see
that in one of the ah one of the books for
that course
so what is a finite state automaton so it's
kind of a directed graph ok so so in this
in this figure you are seeing ah there is
a finite automaton that is having six different
nodes so these are the nodes here are called
the states ok and there are edges between
the nodes and they are the edges are labeled
with certain symbols so for example you are
seeing between node zero to one there is in
there is an edge with a with the label of
c ok and they may also be empty if for certain
category of these automaton there are certain
started states so for example here the node
zero is the started state and there are certain
accepting or final states that are noted by
maybe ah having in having a double circles
like on the node six you are having double
circle this is an accepting state or the finite
state so they can be more than one final state
very easily so now what do the finite state
automaton do so they are they they recognize
a regular languages that is the language that
is specified by the regular expressions so
any regular expression you can always convert
into a automaton financial automaton
so now if you see the automaton that is provided
on this slide what is the language that it
at that it recognizes what are the words that
will be passed through this and by seeing
that you can also see how the automaton actually
works so if you give an input like c o l o
r to this automaton what will happen so it
will start with the started state you will
take the first character see from a started
state on the input character see you will
go to the state one from this graph now state
one you take an input o that is the next in
in the input and you move to state two and
so on and as you end with the with the phoneme
character r you end up with the state six
in this graph
so given an input like see c o l o r it is
accepted by this automaton but what happens
if i give a word like c o l o u r you can
see the a path you can go from four to five
and five to six and this automaton you can
accept c o l u r so it will accept two words
c o l o r c o l o u r but what happens if
you give it is some other word like co l r
so you will see c o l will go to state three
but if you take r there is no path from three
that takes an input r so it can't move further
so this input will not be accepted by this
automaton so what so given an automaton final
state automaton what it does it it recognizes
if a finite so not finite a regular language
ok so if you give any string from the regular
language it will accept that means this will
end up in one of the accepting states but
you should give it any other string that is
not in the language it will not accept so
this will not end up in any of the accepting
states
so now how are these finite state automaton
used for doing the morphological analysis
so what is the idea the idea is that when
you when you combine various morphemes there
are certain changes that happen at the boundary
mainly concatenation and this is very very
regular [fina/phenomena] so if or one want
to capture that two words like boy and car
can be made converted into plural by adding
an s i can simply have a state for the noun
where boy and car both come together and then
i have a single single edge from there with
s marking that there is a plural and now you
think about all the possible plural that you
can make in english all the singular nouns
can come to the same state and then you have
a single arrow that with s and that will convert
into fluid so th so that very efficiently
captures the process of converting in from
singular to plural and as long as this is
regular this is very very straightforward
then how do you do that
so here is an example in this slide so so
only three states are shown here q naught
q one q two q notice the starter state and
q one and q two other accepting or finite
states many other intermediate states are
not shown we will see that in some of the
later slides so from q naught to q one the
regular nouns like car boy bag etcetera and
then so all of these are also words in english
you can now add a plural morpheme s to convert
them into plural so go going from q one to
q two but as such what happens if you have
a irregular noun like goose to geese so that
cannot go to q one because to goose if you
apply as you will not get its plural form
so for the irregular nouns you have a different
path that goes from q naught that it to q
two again there will be some intermediate
nodes for individual characters of phonemes
in in that in the language in the world so
both the singular plural will go to q so q
one and q two both will accept the words in
the english
similarly this is in f s a financial automaton
for english adjectives ok so you have some
prefix like un then you have the actual adjective
root like happy and then certain suffixes
like er e s t l y so you see here we are also
showing some lot of morpho tactics that what
kind of morphemes follow other kind of morphemes
ok so now what kind of words that you can
generate by using this automaton so you can
say un happy unhappy ok a starting from q
naught or from q naught you taking go to q
one and you have happy and er happier happiest
happily and so on ok so sick is generated
words like happy happier happiest real from
q naught you take an absolute transition go
to q one then you have the adjective root
real that can q two is a final state so you
can generate real if you have generate unreal
from q naught you take un that will give you
un plus have the word real and go to q two
you become you get unreal ok similarly all
other words you can generate by using this
particular automaton
so yeah so as we already said in these examples
we also seen some english morphotactics that
is what kind of morphemes come after another
kind of morphemes in in english no no but
what do i do about regular in regular roots
in english how do i capture that information
in this automaton so can we include the lexicon
also in my automaton so thats what we was
see if i also want to include word like words
like car cars bag everything in inside my
automaton how do i do that so this is what
we have seen so from q naught i take all the
regular nouns to q one all the irregular nouns
directly go to q two ok but now i want to
include the lexicon so let's take a very very
simple and a small lexicon so i have the words
like bag boy and dog as the regular noun and
man as the irregular noun and we want to generate
all the so i want to recognize all the singular
and plural form so what do i do so you see
here from the state q naught i am now having
all the possible other individual states that
take the regular singular nouns to q one ok
so i have different nodes for b and then the
be shared among bag and boy ok similarly there
is a different state for going to doc and
finally all of these they go to q one all
the regular nouns in the singular form and
then you get you can have s added to that
this becomes plural
so you have dogs bags and boys together what
do you do for the irregular nouns you have
a different path man and m a n and m e n they
again go to q two directly now given this
figure can you recognize the words like boys
easily yes i start with q naught when i get
the word b i go to the next state o i go to
another state why i go to q one and s i go
to q two so i can recognize boys i can recognize
boy m a n m e n all this can be recognized
by this automaton i can further expand it
to include other words my vocabulary ok but
the education here is this the goal of morphological
asks that we started with so what is this
automaton doing given a word in english it
will tell me whether it is a singular or plural
word in english ok assuming that you have
taken care of all the words in your vocabulary
while building this automaton so it can recognize
various words ok so so that's what we have
written here so what are the properties of
f s a s so so they are very very elegant ok
so that is the recognition problem can be
solved in linear time what do i mean by that
given give give me any input string so you
can find out whether automaton recognizes
the string or not a linear time linear in
the length of the string ok because every
time you are making if you are having a word
like boys you are checking if from the start
state if you go if you take input b where
do you go o y s and then finally if you end
up in the accepted state you will accept the
string otherwise you will not of course this
will happen only for the deterministic automaton
but as in the elegance of itself we know that
every non deterministic finite automaton can
be contributed to a deterministic finite automaton
and there is in a simple algorithm for that
so we do not have to worry about it even if
we have started building an n f a i non deterministic
automaton i can convert it to d f a where
the linear time you can find out whether a
string is accepted or not similarly i do not
have to worry about getting the minimum mode
of states of the automator ok because the
again there is an algorithm that converts
any automaton into it the equivalent automaton
that has the minimum number of states ok
so yeah so this is why we say this is very
very elegant you can convert an n f a to d
f a and in d f a you can convert in into the
minimum number of st since very very elegant
and we have seen that it can work as a language
recognizer given a regular language it can
can tell me a new given a new string whether
this is in the language or not but so coming
to my previous question is it what we need
in the morphological analysis so answer is
no this is not sufficient for the morphological
analysis we so so take the word boys remember
what are the different morphology analysis
we talked about we talked about finding the
lambdaization ok is like the simplest one
lambdaization i want to find out what is the
lemma for the word boys i want to find out
the word boy can the d f a help me to obtain
the word boy it it can't it can only tell
me that boys is a word in my in my defined
regular language this this is there so this
is either single plural but it cannot tell
whether boys is what is the lemma forward
by so i need some some other more model that
can give a word can also give me what is the
lemma or the root form so for that so f s
a s are language recognizer or generators
so we need instead transducers that can help
me do morphological analysis ok
so what are transducers so transducers are
very very similar to final state automaton
except that they can help me translate one
string into another ok so now what happens
there how do they do that the model is very
similar to f s a but now in each edge of the
f s a instead of having a single phoneme as
the label i have the input phoneme or input
characters symbol and the output character
symbol so it translates one character symbol
to another character symbol so that that solves
my problem of going from the input string
like boys to an output this string like boy
ok
so let's take the example on the on on the
on the same lexicon of forwards and they are
plural so earlier we saw the final decision
automaton where we were having each edge label
within input character only so finally it
could recognize whether a word is there in
the language or not but now we have the transducer
where each other is labeled with the input
as well as the output character so you see
here so here m m e n and e is the input a
is the out so once you give an input like
m e n to this transducer the output you will
get is m e n the actual lemma ok that is how
they can solve the morphological analysis
problem
now some small details that what might be
the problem that that you might face while
doing that so for example here is an input
so we are calling it the lexical label cat
i want to cat i want to convert it to a it's
now but a plural form so i know cat cat gives
me cats ok but what happens if i take a word
like fox fox will give me foxes ok so there
will be they are changed at the at the boundary
you adding an e between fox and s so now there
are many ways in which you can handle it one
is you have you take cat has a regular know
and then have a regular plural to that and
fox as irregular noun separately this is one
possibility
but the interesting idea is if you can use
a two level morphology that is between the
lexical form cat plus non plus plural and
the surface form that is cats can i define
an intermediate form that is cat there is
an s but in between there is some placeholder
that can be null or e depending on what are
the phonemes available in the stem and the
surface so that is instead of going from lexical
to surface level directly can i go to the
individual level first this is my first label
and then i transfer from intermediate label
to the surface level in the second level of
morphology so this is my two level morphologic
so example is so the motivation example is
for cats and foxs so instead of going from
fox plus n plus p l two foxes i go to fox
and some placeholder n n s and this is the
end the now i can have a second label rule
that says if my damaged fox of x is h s will
there be some addition in the in between will
there will be sudden change in between that
can be taken care of by a separate module
similarly cat there is a placeholder n s i
can find out what should be the actual surface
from given this intermediate form
so here is an example so i have in my vocabulary
words like fox cat goose ok and i am generating
the singular and plural form so what are you
seeing here from from fox to generate the
plural form same with cat i add a placeholder
as and the end of the character ok so so that
is here now so this is my intermediate form
so that means at this point i am not distinguishing
between fox and cat they are behaving very
very similarly so i need an additional process
to find out given this intermediate form what
should be the surface level form ok so so
this is this is the two level morphology i
go to fox s there is something in between
that may be null or something else intermediate
label and then from intermediate labeled you
go to the surface level ok
now what do you think the transition depend
depends on from intermediate or surface label
so it will depend on what are the ending characters
of the stem and the starting director of the
affix now given these what should be the replacement
character ok so you can have these simple
rules in this notation this is also called
k notation for condensed context as sensitive
rules ok so that so rules is that a letter
a h converted to b if h visited by c and followed
by d ok so this is if you remember the context
sensitive grammar so that is what i am saying
h converted to b if preceded by c and forward
by d that means whenever a comes between c
and d then you convert a to b ok this is the
context sensitive rules so this kind of spelling
change rules you can apply to go from intermediate
label to the surface level you can use this
rules to to do the conversion
now so after talking about this two level
morphology in general when people design the
morphological analysis for the for a given
language they follow two different kind of
approaches ok so so they are also called the
linguistic approach and engineering approach
so what is the difference between the two
ok so in the linguistic approach what will
happen you have the stem stem is already defined
in the in the in the lexicon or or the language
and you have an affix that is also defined
so to the stem you will apply the suffixes
h but the surface changing rules will be taking
care of separately by the rules of this kind
that we have just seen so there will be rules
of this kind that will define the the surface
how what are the changes that are happening
at the surface label on the other hand engineering
approaches you won't have the separate rules
for spelling changes they will try to find
out the minimum possible unit of the stem
that can be used and to that what other and
the affixes can be big and in in that case
that can be applied to the stem ok let's see
one example that makes it clear so so the
idea is that engineering approach all the
phonetic irregularities will be factored into
the endings so here is one example from check
so so what you are seeing here so they are
various words women owl draft iceberg wrapper
and fly for each of these you have the actual
word and so that is like for women z e n and
or it's s o v so here the root word and there
are various affixes are applied in various
grammatical functions that are abstracted
using s one s two s three so on and p two
the various grammatical ah functions ok you
might treat them as singular plural and and
so on
so to a given root word where is affixes have
being applied so what you are seeing here
are the final forms ok so for the initial
two words they seen pretty pretty regular
so you have the word s o v you apply a y e
n o for getting different different forms
similarly for z e n s k i c you see some difference
right they are in red so what is the difference
that you are seen so now the the suffix why
has been changed to i in the case of h two
similarly the accent is gone over e from me
and you are getting the single sim simple
e so that is why it's in red ok so this is
a irregularity this is ok but what happens
if we go to icework with k r you see in the
case of s three even the stem that's a change
so on are you are getting an accent and for
p two you are getting another word another
character e in between k r so you are getting
k e r so now so so on you will see such changes
even vapor and fly so now the question is
how does one capture all this all the changes
all these irregularities in the case of stems
and the suffixes
so now in the linguistic approach what will
happen i will take the same route word so
for example here i will have s k i c as the
root word and k r as the root word and the
same set of suffixes so y a y e with an accent
you know are my suffixes that is my root and
the suffix pair i will add these and whatever
a spelling change rules i will try to enumerate
whatever different spelling change rules by
taking what is the previous character previous
to previous character i will try to define
the spelling changes in that way that is a
linguistic approach what will happen in engineering
approach i try to find out the part of the
stem that is common across all all these variations
so it's ok with the first three z e n s o
v n s k i c but with k r i will take only
k as common i will not take r because r is
getting changed into something with an accent
or with an e n r so i will take only k h common
is part of my stem and everything else remaining
i will convert into my stem that i might add
and that you see in the last three so you
have only k p n m as the actual strength and
everything else goes into the suffix so this
is what is engineering approach so by doing
that you do not have to worry about handling
the spelling change rules separately you are
you handling them here itself ok
so there are various tool kits set available
for doing the morphological pricing for example
at and t f s m library that is very popular
again the open f s t tools is very very popular
for doing the morphological analysis for a
given language so so this is this was about
our computation morphology using finite state
methods so i have very very briefly talked
about what our financial methods and how do
we how do you use that for computational morphology
so in the next lecture we will talk about
in the same process a more popular problem
about part of speech tagging so what is the
problem part of speech tagging and what are
the different computational models that you
can use to handle that ok
thank you