so welcome to the fourth module of the of
this week ok so so as we said last time we
will be starting with a very very popular
problem of part of speech tagging if you remember
this was one of the processes that we talked
about when dealing with morphology so you
can do lamentation you can do morphological
analysis you can also tagging so what was
the thing that was that was different in tagging
that you are not doing morphological analysis
if you remember you will also finding out
among all the possibilities what is the actual
ah particular morphological degree that this
four things
so you also doing the disambiguation here
ok so this is my problem of part of speech
tagging that given a set of words ok so that
means a sentence of document whatever can
i identify what is the actual category for
each of the word i have to give the unique
answer for each one so each one so if we take
example for english text so given a text of
english can be sentence or whatever can identify
the part of speech of each and every word
that is the problem of part of speech tagging
so so if i have a sentence like the boy put
the keys on the table and i have four possible
part of speech tags so very very ah coarse
label like noun and pronoun v for verb and
p for pronoun the first p here is for prepositions
and d det for the determiner so you can map
the is a determiner and boy is a noun put
is a verb the is a determiner keys a noun
and on is a preposition and the is a determiner
and table is a noun
so each word you can map to one of the four
one of the four tags so this is a problem
that given a sentence you have all the individual
words can identify and define what is a in
grammatical category for each of this word
so now ah so one one natural question that
you might have is ok so how many different
part of speech tags are there ok so firstly
let us see what are the different things that
will go in the part of speech part of speech
tag categories ok firstly you will have the
open class words ok that are sort of content
words so they are like nouns verbs adverbs
adjectives they are they are there they will
have their own part of speech text so they
are the the open class words are those that
we are the content mostly and so why do we
call them open class because you keep on adding
new and new words ah in in the language we
have coin ah we have seen a term for this
right so you have words like google photoshop
skype they come into the language all so these
are coming into nouns or verbs in the in the
language so this is open class you can keep
on adding new and new words and then you have
the closed class words like pronouns here
very fixed set of pronouns determiners very
a fixed ok then prepositions connectives and
all that they are very fixed they are all
functional words and they are closed class
ok and as you know they are they are used
to tie various concepts the sentence together
ok
so i need some part of speech categories for
open class words some categories for closed
class words so one possibility can be i can
choose very very coarse grained categories
right like here so i can take noun so i am
also giving some examples here like chair
bandwidth pacing all these are nouns i can
take verb study debate munch all these are
verbs then adjective like purple tall ridiculous
they are adjectives adverbs unfortunately
slowly proportion of by to they become my
preposition pronoun i me mine and then determiner
ok the a that those
so maybe i can just use it very very coarse
label ah part of speech tags but think of
the perspective when a of language pronouncing
so what is helpful to me to take a very coarse
label or to go to the more fine grained label
so here what will happen i can find out which
word is a noun but if i to tell it's a singular
noun a plural noun i cannot tell if i have
even if i have the tagging information so
i might want to prefer a tagging scheme where
i also go to some sort of grammatical details
of the word ok it is a noun ok and and is
it a verb is it a the third same person singular
verb is it it is a verb plus a past tense
and so on even noun is it a proper noun
so i might want to go into finer detail but
again i cannot go into very very finer details
so again they ah otherwise there will be too
many part of speech tags so there are various
ah is schemes that are available so they have
their own part of speech tags definitions
so but given a sentence if you have to do
part of speech tag tagging you need to first
defined what is your tagset what is all the
possible categories among which you have to
choose it and there are various standards
available ok
so yeah i can choose very very coarse tagsets
like only taking noun verb adjective adverb
or i can take a good enough set that gives
me some additional grammatical information
with each of the word each of the word ok
so one for very popular part of speech tagset
is university pennsylvania upenn ah treebank
tagset that contains every forty five part
of speech tags and we will see examples also
and there is a very nice tutorial on these
part of speech tags in terms of ah how what
is the difference between this part of speech
tag verses at part of speech tag particle
versus adverb how are they different by giving
examples so that i recommend as if you want
to get more information in in the sense of
how they are used in various sentences you
can look at this this site
so here are some examples of ah the treebank
the upenn treebank part of speech tag so what
are the part of speech tags they used and
what are the various sort some example words
here so for example in this if i see ah conjunction
so and but are all j conjunction they they
give a tag like c c one two three we are cardinal
numbers they give a tag like c d a da det
they are determiner give a tag of d e t then
additional there foreign word then off in
by they are preposition yellow adjective then
bigger so again with adjective you have comparative
superlative so you are add adapting some more
information there let's start a marker
now if you see at the nouns ok you have a
tag n n for only the noun is a singular noun
a masculine sorry it's a singular noun ah
for plural noun you have a tag like n n s
ok if but now you see there an extra text
for proper noun you had separate tags so once
you know the tag you know it's a noun or it's
a proper noun and whether it is a singular
or plural you get all this information so
that is the that's why getting it into some
finer details is helpful so you have four
different text for nouns
similarly so if i am escaping those i am going
to the verb directly so here text like v b
for the base form of the verb then v b d for
the past tense v b g for gerent v b n for
past participle and then third singular present
is v b p and third singular ah and is like
v b z ok non third singular versus first singular
there are two different forms so you have
different forms of verbs so again that they
give you various grammatical information and
then you can see other sort of part part of
speech tag that are available in to upenn
trees ah ah tag tagset
so let's take an example then so we have taken
a taking a sentence and if we tag it by upenn
tagset how does it look like so the sentence
is the grand jury commented on a number of
other topics so now here the word does determiner
grand jury adjective ok so jury would be a
noun commented becomes a verb so you have
seen the part of speech tags on is a preposition
i n a is determiner number is a noun of is
a again a preposition other ah adjective and
topics they come in noun in plural form ok
so this is the information that you get by
the part of speech tags
now the question might come come that why
are you worried about solving this problem
of part of speech tagging it is a hard problem
or a trivial problem can i define for each
word in my lexicon what will be it's part
of speech tag it is a very very simple problem
no so so the problem occurs because each for
does ah does not have a unique part of speech
tags and it might depend on the context in
this the word is being used ok so so what
i am saying is that a word might have multiple
part of speech tags and only by seeing the
context you might be able to identify what
is the actual part of speech tag is being
used in this particular context
so let's take an example so i have the word
like back ok so what are the part of speech
tags that this simple word like back can help
so if i take the sentence like the back door
what is back here what is the part of speech
tag of back so it is an adjective now if i
take a word like sentence like on my back
it's not an adjective anymore it becomes a
noun in this case yes now i have it win the
voters back of the sentence it becomes in
win back ok so it becomes in adjective and
if i have a sentence promised to back the
bill now this becomes a verb ok so the same
word back can be used in multiple part of
speech tags
so so immediately you can see the problem
that given the context find out what is the
appropriate part of speech tag is be used
ok so to determine the part of speech tag
for a particular instance of a word is my
part of speech tagging problem ok
now what are the various ah information that
we can use for doing this for how co how common
is this first of all how common is this problem
how how many words are actually ambiguous
in terms of part of speech tags so if i see
if i want to see that from the data ok so
so this is your this so this point i just
want to say something like once you encounter
problem in in in language or any other field
the first thing that you might want to see
is that how common is that problem if it is
a very very rare problem maybe it's not worth
to spend too much time you can have simple
rules for solving that but it says if it is
a very very common problem then yes you might
have to tackle it using certain models
so similarly here the disambiguation part
is speech tags so then it happen only for
ten words if it happens for only for ten words
i did ah need not worry about building some
models and all that for solving this problem
but if it happens for say ten percent of the
words then yes there is a real problem and
i need to ah think of some model for solving
it ok so now if let us see from the corpus
how common is this ambiguity problem so if
i take the brown corpus so what we see here
forty percent of the word tokens are ambiguous
and twelve percent of the word types ambiguous
so i i hope you remember the distinction between
types and tokens tokens are the all the passes
all the occurrences of different words so
same word occurs multiple times are multiple
tokens ok so forty percent of word tokens
are ambiguous so what we are seeing saying
is that in a corpus if i am encountering and
tokens forty percent of them are ambiguous
that's a huge number forty percent of all
the words that occurred in the corpus ambiguous
ok so that means the real problem
now if we want to just break down of the ambiguity
type that how many ah unique words have um
different number of tags so what we see here
so roughly thirty five thousand types have
only one part of speech tag now three thousand
seven sixty types have two tags and two sixty
four have three tags and so on and there is
one word like is still that has got seven
different part of speech tags in the brown
corpus so so yes getting six seven tag is
very very rare but getting two and three tags
is quite common especially two tags is very
very common in the brown corpus
now now the next problem so we have solve
that this problem is ah frequent yes this
is not a real problem but how bad is this
problem what do i mean by this so can we always
identifies for a given word is one tag more
likely than an another so let's take an example
of the word race race can be a noun and a
verb when the brown corpus race at race occurs
as a noun ninety eight percent of the time
but as a verb two percent of the time
so if i have a simple model that always assigns
the word race to a noun that will im immi
immediately achieve a ninety per eight percent
accuracy write for this particular example
at least so that means whenever i am trying
to design a model i should be able to think
of what is in what is simple baseline uninitialized
compare if i'm making computational model
that is working even worse than this baseline
it may not be very very helpful ok so respite
this can be my simple baseline for testing
any of the model that i will propose for this
particular task
so so a tagger for english that simply chooses
the most likely tag for each word can achieve
good performance so it can be ah even more
than ninety percent ok so so always it's not
good to look only at the final numbers it's
also ah good to see how much you are improving
over maybe some of the simplest baselines
and some other models that that are there
in in the literature so at least the simple
baseline how much you are able to do better
than the simple baseline
say an any new approach should be able to
should be should be able to compared against
the simple baseline now how do i decide the
correct part of speech tags so yeah one thing
is a it might even be difficult for people
in some cases right it's not a very very easy
problem always so here in this slide we have
three sentences this is shaffer never got
around to joining all we go to do is to go
around the corners and chateau petrus costs
around twenty five hundred ok and all the
three words three sentences you have the word
around and you will find out what is the part
of speech tag ok and you will see this is
not very very easy if you will just ah look
at these sentences is not easy to find it
what are speech tags
so i will just suggest that you go to the
tutorial once and so the tutorial that i i
talked about earlier so that all talks about
what are the differences between various part
of speech that will give you some idea on
how to find out the actual part of speech
tags of around in this case so what we will
see here before in the first case it is a
ah the particle second case it is a preparation
and third case it is in ah adverb ok
now what is the relevant knowledge that we
might need for this part of speech tagging
problem that we might need to give to our
models ok so for example some words might
always be in one part of category like arrow
is always a noun so i can have this knowledge
some words are ambiguous like fly flies ok
and what like like it can it is again ambiguous
so what might help is what is the probability
that a word occurs at a particular as a particular
part of speech tag the baseline that you are
talking about this might be helpful for our
model also that given a word what is the most
probable tag for this word this is one thing
that we might use
now what is the what what can be the other
information that is useful so take the word
leg flies ok if you do not give me any other
word i may never be able to tell with full
confidence what should be the corresponding
correct part of speech tag unless you tell
me the sentence where it occurs ok same was
with the word like saw that was one of the
earlier examples ok unless you give me the
sentence like peter saw her i cannot tell
the saw is actually a verb and not a noun
so that means i need i need to do something
of the word itself how come how common it
occurs with some part of speech tag then another
i also need to know about the context in which
the word is occurring and how can i use the
context to desegregate the actual part of
speech tag
so so i need the local context in the sentence
so for example the information that to determiners
really follow each other so if my model is
saying two words the determiner determiner
which is not allowed ok similar two based
forms of the word they do not follow follow
each other they they should not come together
similarly ah my model can tell me that a determiner
is always followed by an adjective or now
this can be useful information that if the
previous word is a signed determiner it is
a highly likely the next row will be adjectives
or noun so all this we want to encode using
our models as well
so what are the various approaches so so we
will try to use all this knowledge but what
are the various approaches that we can use
so for all the problems that we will be is
dealing with in this coarse mostly you can
always use a rule based approach ok so so
this visual some of the earlier models that
work that were used in n l p so we are given
a problem some language will sit together
find out what are the symbol patterns or sing
simple kind of if then else rules that one
can write down to to solve this particular
problem ok
so what would be a rule based ah solution
to this problem ok for doing the part of speech
tagging disambiguation problem so what i will
do i find out for all the words that can have
multiple part of speech tags what is one particular
thing that that can help me decide whether
to use one tag or the other ok and this and
given a new context i can again use this is
is that particular ah contexts appearing here
or not then i can have a statistical tagging
that is i get a training corpus ok so this
is a standard model so i have a corpus training
corpus that has the tag text by tag text i
mean i have the sentence and with each word
i also have the actual part of speech category
now using that can i learn what is the actual
part of speech tag for each individual word
and this ah in a new sentence can i learn
some model so this is my statistical tagging
so ah so they are again different variation
different various models so one simple model
is ah t b l tagger that was one of the earlier
model proposed for part of speech tagging
so that is i am given a any corpus of tag
text can i learn some sort of transformation
rules that this word has a particular main
category most probable category of part of
speech tag but given the context if this most
probable text should be changed to some other
tag so can i use some rules from a corpus
training corpus itself and then the probabilistic
models where i will i will have a probabilistic
in the position of what is the most likely
sequence of tags for a sequence of words
so we will go go through t b l tagger very
very briefly and then we will devote a lot
of time on the probabilistic taggers so what
is t b l tagger transformation based learning
so let's try to understand the idea first
so i have a sentence like the canvas rushed
it ok so how the model will process so this
is my training data set so i also know what
is the actual part of speech tag for each
of the individual word
now if you the first thing you will do is
to find out for each individual word what
is the most likely part of speech tag so in
other words the can was rested ok so if you
find out a more slightly tag for the word
can it will be a model work and mostly occurs
as a model work ok similarly rush ford rusted
it would be a verb in the in the past tense
that is the most popular ah probable tag so
i will write down the can was rested ok now
i will see in my actual training sentence
what are the actual ah or thus rejected are
assigned to different words so i find this
is correct this is incorrect this i am sorry
this the most probable tag will be m d moreover
is incorrect in this and as i will have a
noun this is fine but this will be instead
v b n is a participant past participial ok
so these two are incorrect so i need to write
some moves so that these can be transformed
so one symbol can be m d changes to n m sorry
to n n when preceded by d t remember the rules
that we saw in the previous previous lecture
so it needs to be if preceded by something
and there is nothing so we are not putting
any restriction what is being followed so
this is a rule that i can use so now what
will happen in a new case whenever a word
is assigned m d if i see the previous word
is determiner i will change m d to n n ok
this is the rule i am running from this example
similarly i can rule a learn ah learn a rule
here v b d goes to v b n whenever preceded
by reading this can be another rule so this
is the idea i have training corpus i find
out for each for what is the most likely tag
whenever they do not match i will write down
some set of rules and then i keep on doing
that and i might put down a separate data
set simple small data set for testing how
good my finally tagger text so this is my
t b l tagger ok so this is what we have seen
now what is probabilistic tagger in probabilistic
tagging i will have a probabilistic interpretation
of what is the most likely sequence of tags
that should be used for a ah for a given sentence
so let me just briefly talk about what in
general the probabilistic tagging models to
so in these models we have some data that
is some observations d and a certain class
ok so in the case of part of speech tag what
is the example of d n c so d are the words
and then tags are my classes i want to assign
various classes that that tags to different
words so tags some a classes
now you take a different problem like text
classification what will happen the documents
all the sentences if you are doing classification
or documents a sentence is they become your
data and you have your classes so suppose
using sentiment analysis so the sentence is
your data and the class is positive negative
or neutral if you are doing text classification
in terms of a sports visage politics and so
on there is categories the document or the
vertical instance of the text becomes your
data and that becomes your class a sports
and politics and so on so you have a paired
observation of ah a data and a class
now they are two ah different families of
probability models that can be used for solving
these problems ok i will just briefly talk
about these two families and we will take
a examples from both of these for this problem
ok so and and you will be able to use that
for many other applications n l p also ok
so what gives raise to two different families
that is whether you generate the data from
the class or the class from the data so what
is the philosophy of your model ok
so let's try to ah understand that from this
ah so so from this slide so we have two different
types of models one is a generative model
and and second is a conditional model so in
generative model what will happen so you have
appear data and the class so generative model
you will assume that the class is there and
the class generates the data ok so this is
the philosophy from the class that it i generated
so examples are like nigh page modular hidden
markov models so your class is given and data
generated from this
in the discriminative condition models what
will happen that your data is there and you
assume that hidden state is a generated from
the data so that is the the minor difference
between that so in the condition in the joint
model you first at the class you first generate
the class and then you generate the data from
the class ok so that is so so to give a simple
example if you want to use a joint for generating
modules for text classification what will
you assume if i am going to take a document
i will first think over what is the topic
i want to write say politics i think about
the the class and i am given this class what
is the probability that i write all these
words ok so from that class i find out the
probability of different different words so
i that's how my model is defined in the case
of conditional model given the observation
directly i want to find out the probability
of the class ok
so so so this difference tells me whether
so how do i actually go about solving these
models ok so ah so they are the models like
s v m s perceptron that are ah not probabilistic
so they are not in division one of these so
they are also discriminative classifiers now
this picture will help you understand that
two models again so you see the directions
are different in the in the pic pictures in
the first direction in the first in the left
hand side picture so direction is from the
class to all the data points ok so first the
class is generated then all the data points
so you generative model
in the second one is a conditional model so
given the data you want to find out directly
the probability of the class ok so first one
example is nalve bayes second one example
is logistic regression ok so so a joint model
will give you probability of so d l the data
and the class together and you will try to
maximize the joint probability and condition
of mo model you will directly want want to
find out the probability of the class given
a rate ok so we will take examples of both
of these in the in the next modules so what
is a ah joint model that can help me solve
the part of speech tagging problem and what
is the condition model that can help me solve
the part of speech tagging problem ok
thank you