so hello everyone welcome back friend for
this lecture five of week three so so in the
last lecture we we started with the problem
on part of speech tagging ok we defined the
problem image ah given a text that can be
a sentence ok so you need to find out what
is the actual ah part of speech category for
each of the individual word so there may be
many various ambiguities but you need to resolve
the ambiguities and find out the unique part
of each tag for each of the words
and we said that you can solve it using rule
based methods or some probabilistic methods
we also discuss that the the methods can be
ah generative or discriminative and then they
they differ in the in the philosophy of the
model so in general generative model the class
comes first and it is assumed that the words
are generated the the data is generated from
the class and in the discriminative model
you directly find out the probability of the
class given the data so we will in this lecture
we will start with the ah generative model
that is hidden markov model and see how it
can be used for solving the pub task of part
of speech tag so this a probabilistic model
so so starting with what is my problem so
i have some n words w one two w n in my corpus
that i observed in and i need to find out
the participation text for each of these words
so suppose that you have to find out the sequence
capital t so that assigns t one to t n for
all of these n words now each of these t i's
that a participant text can belong to ah the
my my actual say suppose i am using the university
of when we tag set so it can take any of those
forty five value age so there are many many
different values that these this sequence
can take i need to find out the actual ah
and ambiguous tag sequence given this ah word
sequence as my input
so now how do i start solving this problem
as per the ah as per this ah probabilistic
model so so so the idea is that among all
the possible sequences of part of speech tags
that this word sequence can take i need to
find the one that has the maximum probability
so i can write it like that so this is i have
to find out t hat that gives you the maximum
probability argmax overall possibility probability
t given w so i need to find out the purpose
sequence that gives the highest probability
now so as we have already said t is nothing
but t one to t n and w is nothing but w to
w i so i can write it as argmax t one to t
n given w one two w n ok this is what i will
be doing so in generative model remember what
is the idea idea is that the class or the
the tags come first and then my words are
generated from there so i cannot find out
the probability of tag given the word but
from the model i can find out the probability
of word given the tag so i need to invert
this the direction of the probabilities here
so instead of finding t given w i need to
find i need to use w going
so what is the theorem popular theorem that
i can use i can apply bayes theorem so instead
of directly opening it here i can try same
argmax t p w given t p t given divided by
p w ok and p w it's common for all these sequences
the probability of the sequence so this is
again it does not matter so that will give
me argmax over t p w given t and p t ok so
this because an using generating model so
first my class that is my t comes and then
my sequence is generated w that's why i have
to take it in this format probability w t
p t
now i can try and open this so this will be
so let me just take this particular thing
and this will be the probability w one to
w n given t one to t n probability t one to
t n ok so now so i can again use chain rule
to write that ok so that we can see in the
slide ok so so i can i can you write it as
using the chain rule so this will be nothing
but probability so multiplication over all
i is equal to one to n w i given w one to
w i minus one t one to t n and probability
t i given t one to t i minus one ok this is
simply by using the chain rule i can write
it like that
so now so it is very difficult to get the
estimates for all these probabilities that
we are thinking it so that means i need to
do certain simplifications over this formula
so what are the simplifications that we do
so so one simplification that we do here is
that so in this formula we are saying that
the probability of the word the current word
so you see we have a sequence of words w one
to w n and correspondingly we have a sequence
of x t one to t n whatever w i what i am saying
the probability of this word depends on all
the previous words and all the tags so instead
of that because the generative model i might
say that this probably depends only on the
current deck ok this is simplification that
i can make so this i can simplify as
probability w i given t i ok so this is one
simplification then here we are saying that
the probability of t i the tag t i depends
on all the previous tags so again i might
simplify it by using some markov assumption
that it depends on either the only the previous
tag or previous to previous tag so if i take
only the bigram assumption so i will set t
i depends on t i minus one so in terms of
this model i will say that t i only depends
on t i minus one ok and here i will simplify
it using probability t i k one t i minus one
and this is my bigram assumption
ok so now if i if i make the simplification
what is the model that we actually see
so this is the formula that we came up with
so i want a a tag sequence that has that gives
the highest probability for this particular
form and we make some simplification that
is the probability of a word appearing depends
only on it's part of speech tag remember this
is genetic model so the word is generated
from the part of speech tag so first the part
of speech tags are generated and then the
tags are giving each an individual word so
we are making this assumption that the word
is generated only from it's own part of speech
tag ok then so this gives me the first ah
simplification second one i will say that
the probability of attack depends only on
it's forward previous tags
so if i make the bigram assumption it will
depend only on the previous tag ok so this
will give me this function so together the
same the simplification will give me this
formula so i want to find it tag sequence
that gives me the maximum probability for
this particular formula ok so now once we
have come to this formula so what is this
model actually ok
so first let us see that it can be easily
compute these probabilities probability w
i given t i and probability t i given t i
minus one so how will you actually compute
these probabilities so one way is that you
are given a corpus where you know all the
words you also know what are their part of
speech tags somebody has manually annotated
each this this data file now given this data
can you compete this probabilities so for
example computing probability t i given t
i minus one if you want to find out how many
times this tag t i comes after the tag t i
minus one so you will compute it by using
the maximum likelihood estimate that is the
number of times t i minus one and t i come
together in the corpus divided by the number
of times the word t i minus one the tag t
i minus one comes ok so if you see here in
the slide so p t i given t i minus one can
be found by this by using these counts count
of the two texts together divided by the count
of the previous tag only
so if i want to compute probability n n given
d t i will say number of times d t occurs
followed by c n n n divided by number of times
d t occurs and this if i have the numbers
i can compute this probability what is the
other probability of the compute i have to
compute probability of word given the tag
ok so so the complete probability where i
given the tag i will find out again how many
times this word occurs with this tag divided
by how many rimes that tag occurs so this
again from my corpus so if i have the numbers
i want to compute probability is given v w
z i will find out how many times the word
each occurs with the direct v w z divided
by the number of times the tag v w z actually
occurs in my corpus so here if i have the
numbers i can compute these probabilities
so all the probabilities that are required
for this model can easily be computed if i
have a data where i know the words and the
part of speech tags for each and individual
words
so now let us see how we can use that for
some disambiguation it's not the complete
model just to give you some idea so once we
have this how we can use that for some disambiguation
so i have a sentence a part of a sentence
here secretariat is expected to race tomorrow
ok and the ambiguity here is in the word race
so whether the other word races in noun n
n or v b you see everything as the same here
now what are the probabilities as from my
model that differ in the two interpretations
so if you see the first interpretation
what is the second interpretation what are
the probabilities that are defined in the
first one you find if the probability of the
tag v b given t o versus in the second you
find probability of n n given t o then in
the first when you find probability of n r
given v b and second you find probability
of n r given n n in the first when you find
probability of race given v b and second you
find probability of race given n n and because
in your model you are multiplying all the
probabilities that means you will multiply
all the prob all these three probabilities
in the integration one and all three in the
interpretation two
so whichever multiplication gives you the
highest value will decide what is the actual
ah part of speech tag of race that should
be used here it should be v b or n n so if
you have the corpus you know all the probabilities
you will multiply you will find the number
and this will tell me whether i should prefer
interpretation one or interpretation two ok
suppose i take some numbers so here so difference
is because of these probabilities suppose
from my corpus i find some numbers so i will
i will see here is that ah the the um the
possibility here is that the word race should
be a verb not as a noun and if you see the
sentence to race tomorrow the race should
be race the word race should be used as a
verb not as a noun although ah noun is a more
common category count part of speech tag for
race then verb
but because if the context it is more likely
to have race edge verb in this case ok so
that is how we can disambiguate in one part
in this simplistic case but in general for
the whole sentence even if you do not know
any of the tags we can try to use this model
to find out what is the actual sequence of
tag that should be used
so now so coming back to this question what
is this model ok so what are you seeing here
so you are seen so you have a sentence so
that is the words that's what you are observing
and then there are certain tags that assigned
to each of the individual words so in this
model you have a probability of of going from
one tag to another tag and then from a tag
you get a word so can you find can you think
of what is the model it corresponds to what
is the actual model so if you have come across
hidden markov model where you have the states
and from one state you transit to another
state and so on and in each state that is
hidden you can emit the observation ok so
the word here is observation so this is nothing
but the hidden markov model
so what are hidden markov models so just to
give the idea in brief so here you have the
tag transition probabilities t i given t i
minus one you have the emission probabilities
so that is word observation probabilities
probability w i given t i and so this is so
using this whatever we are describing is a
hidden markov model ok now to to tell you
what is hidden markvo model so let me just
quickly tell you what is a markov model and
how a should markvo model different from a
markov model ok
so what is a markov model ok so this markov
model is best explained using this simple
example so in markov model what happens you
again have a states but the states are also
your observations suppose you are studies
the weather the weather on the current day
and the weather can be sunny rainy or foggy
these are the three different kinds of weathers
that can happen on a given day now what what
you are you will get you will get you will
have these three states you will know given
that today is sunny what is the probability
that tomorrow will be sunny or foggy or rainy
so this is state transition probabilities
you will obtain ok so so suppose q n is a
variable that denotes the variable on the
n th day and using this model we can find
out the probability of q n the weather on
the n th day given all the previous days back
and here if you use the first row mark markov
model so so we say this will depend only on
the previous days back q n will depend on
you n q n minus one so let's take one simple
example so here so the you are seeing the
state transition so so that says that if today's
weather is ah sunny then tomorrow will be
sunny with the probability of point eight
and if today is sunny tomorrow will be foggy
with a probability point one five so you can
see that from the edges that go from one state
to another state also from the table that
is shown in in this
so now once you are given this probabilities
you can do certain you can do certain computations
for example suppose you have to find out given
that today the weather is sunny what is the
probability that tomorrow is sunny and day
after is rainy ok so let's use the variable
and i want to find out probability q n plus
two day after is rainy q n plus two is to
rainy and tomorrow is sunny q n plus one it's
sunny given q n sunny
so how would you compute that so if you simply
is the channel you will say that is nothing
but probability q n plus one is equal to sunny
given q n is equal to sunny times probability
q n plus two is equal to rainy given q n is
equal to sunny q n plus one is equal to sunny
ok and now because you are using a first row
markov assumption so this will be equivalent
to so this you will compute using probability
q n plus two is equal to rainy given q n plus
one is equal to sunny now so you have to compute
this probability and this probability and
that you can obtain from the state transition
graph so if you go to the previous slide you
will find out probability sunny given sunny
is point eight m probability rainy given sunny
is zero point zero five ok so once you multiply
this you will get the answer is point zero
four so here so you will get the answer is
zero point zero four so that gives you the
probability that tomorrow will be rainy and
sorry tomorrow will be sunny day after tomorrow
will be rainy given that today is sunny so
that is how you use the markov model
now this is the markvo model so what you see
here you have the states so in this case the
weather so on a days is a solidus state and
transitions are happening among the states
but what is your observation that is also
state so you also observing the weather that
is shear state you are observing that now
remember the example of participate text what
are we observing we observing the words then
when i give you a text i you only observe
the words but what is hidden that is the text
the text are hidden so that's where the hidden
markov models are different from markov model
the states there are not observed they are
hidden variables and what is observed is different
so you have the words are being objective
and from the state you can emit the words
so this is the idea so the generative model
would be so you are starting from some state
state one you keep on transiting to other
states as three and so on and v is a state
you also emit a word emission one emission
two and so on and these emissions are nothing
but your observations these are your observations
so you need to find out the underline sequence
of a states given the sequence of observations
so now so yeah so this is the difference we
have seen for markov mode chains the output
symbols are the same as the states so the
word sunny is ah both a state and the observable
so what happens in part of speech tagging
words are the output symbols but the hidden
states are part of speech tag ok so so hidden
markov model is nothing but an extension of
markov of chain so in which what happens that
ah the output symbols that you are having
are not the same as the states so states are
different from the output and we actually
do not know what should we are in until we
try to use our model
so what are the elements of an hidden markov
model so so what do you need from hidden markov
model so you need a set of states yes you
need the probability of transiting from one
state to another state in your the probability
of emission given a state which words will
be emitted with what probability ok and you
might also need what is the beginning of a
state and ah and so on so if a if you try
to correspond a hidden markov model with the
with part of speech is tagging so we need
set of a states in our part of speech taking
case so the tags are the states we need an
output alphabet that is then what are emissions
so the words are the emissions with the initial
state so in our case that is the beginning
of the sentence we need the transition probabilities
that is given a previous tag what will be
the next tag and we need the emission probabilities
that is given this tag what will be the word
so now so once we have this we can also give
a graphical representation to our ah hidden
markov model for part of speech tagging so
what is happening see here we start state
so here by start steady shown from the start
state you have a probability of transiting
to any of the other tags so what does that
mean you can start the sentence with some
particular tags so this probably should depend
on what is the tag that is more likely to
start the sentence and once you have this
tag what is the next likely tag and so on
so this is your state transition graph so
this is what is shown in the slide so when
we are tagging the sentence you are actually
walking on this a state graph from one state
we are going to another state and so on and
they are very transition probabilities that
you can have over this state graph and this
you can model by using probability of a state
t n given t n minus one
now what does is missing here with each now
within the hidden markov model with each a
state you also have the word emission so from
history you also want to know what is the
probability that you will output or emit a
particular word ok so this is what is additionally
at ah ah needed here so in the graphical representation
now with these states like to i should also
the probability of different words emitting
from that state so here all the words is in
the vocabulary are are written and given the
the particular state what is the probability
of ah out putting or emitting that particular
word in the vocabulary so that you need to
define for all the very possible ah states
in your graph
so now once we have both these what is my
problem so so i can define so if you remember
i can define all these probabilities once
you give me a corpus that contains a set of
words and ah the their corresponding part
of speech tags if you give me that i can find
out all these probabilities so i can define
these graph once here once i have a corpus
what is my problem at runtime i am only given
a an observation that is i am only given a
sentence that is sequence of words i have
to find out what is the corresponding part
of speech tag sequence that should be ah that
should be used for this word sequence ok so
that is suppose i am given a ah sentence like
this is the part of the sentence promised
to back the bill ok there are five words here
so my problem is to find out what is the sequence
of x that would be used for this sentence
so how would i approach this problem given
the state transition graph that i already
have now for each word so so one thing to
simplify this i will do is that for each for
i will i will find out what are all the possible
part of speech text a word can take ok
so we will be talked about this said that
some words can take multiple part of speech
tags ok but but none of the words went beyond
seven part of speech tags ok and mostly the
words were having if they were ambiguous they
were having two or three part of space tags
so for a word if i can identify what are the
part of speech tags so i can only use that
to have my set of possibilities so here for
example i will say the word promised can take
only v b d or v b n past tense of participial
it can be only one of those i have to dis
dis disambiguate among the two the word to
can have only one part of speech tag back
can have four tags the can have two tags and
bill can have two tags ok these are all the
possibilities now each four can take any of
these possibilities so now can you just quickly
see how many possibilities are there so if
you see here i have two times four eight times
two sixteen times two thirty two possibilities
of the part of speech tag sequences
now i have to find out among these which is
the most likely sequence of participation
tags that is being used so now so so how will
i solve this problem one neither might be
i enumerate all the possibilities and for
each possibility i compute the probability
separately so i have thirty two possibilities
and i compute thirty two different ah so for
all the possibility i compute the full probability
that is one one possibility but firstly this
is not very efficient and think of some sentences
which might have ah say fifteen twenty volts
this this will just go exponentially with
the number of words ok so this is not a good
solution so i need to have a solution where
ah it does not grow exponentially with the
size of the sentence ok so so what will be
a good algorithm for for doing that so ideally
i want to come up with the actual part of
speech tag sequence like here it will be v
b d t o v b d t n n from all the possibilities
and how will i do that and that's what we
will be discussing in the next lecture that
so this is the viterbi algorithm
how do i apply in my hmm model this will be
algorithm to come up with this part of speech
tags sequence in efficient manner ok instead
of doing something naive implementation that
is ah exponential and that is actually not
feasible for for doing it at for for a large
corpus so that will be the focus in the next
lecture
thank you