so welcome back for the fourth week of the
course so in the last week we had discussed
a lot about part of speech tagging and what
are the various algorithms as such one can
use to solve this problem and we started with
one particular classifier that is h m m model
for doing part of speech tagging so we had
gone through the basics of h m m and what
are the different probabilities then one need
to use to be able to come up with the the
ah best sequence given a new sentence so what
do you mean i mean by sequence given new sentence
i want to find out what are the part of speech
tags for each of the word in the sentence
so there are multiple there are many many
possibilities and you need to find out what
is the best probable tag sequence so we formulated
this problem as noisy in the noise channel
model framework and then we came up with the
hidden markov model by using certain assumptions
so in the last class so we had also discussed
a bit about what we will be doing at run time
when we are given a sentence so let me start
from there and we will see a particular algorithm
on the viterbi decoding to find out the actual
tag sequences in a very very efficient manner
and then later on i will go to the parameter
learning part so we had talked about it in
the in the last week also but we will devote
sometime over that in this week
so so we had seen this figure in the last
week itself so we have the sentence promised
to back the bill and i want to obtain the
part of speech tag sequence for the sentence
so how do i start i first start by finding
out what are the probable part of speech tags
for each of the individual words in the sentence
so further word here promised the two possible
tags are v b d and v b n it can be past tense
or the participle for the [wor/word] word
to there is only one part of speech tag possible
for the word back there are four part of speech
tags possible we have seen that in one of
the lectures for the word the there are two
part of speech tags possible for the word
bill there are two word of speech tags possible
so i start by enumerating all the possibilities
for each of the individual words in the sentence
now i want to find out what is the actual
part of speech tag sequence for this word
for this sentence now looking at this picture
how many different possibilities can you see
ok so if you start from any of the part of
speech tag for the word promised and go to
any of the participant tag for the word bill
any particular path denotes a possible tag
sequence so if you try to count the number
of possibilities ok so it will be two times
one times four times two times two ok it will
be roughly thirty two possible part of speech
tag sequences and among the study to i have
to find out what is the most probable tag
sequence
now how should i do that so one knife method
would be that i enumerate all the possible
sequences so all the thirty two sequences
i compute the probability for each sequence
so now you know how to compute the probability
by using the h m m kind of model so we did
one simple example in the last class and find
out which of the tag sequence has the highest
probability that will be a naive method you
might even do that for if you have say only
thirty two or fifty possible text sequences
but think about the sentences that might have
ten to fifteen words and some words might
have five to six different tags so you will
see that it will grown exponentially ok so
enumerating all the sequences and computing
the probabilities is not an efficient solution
so you might want to do something more efficient
so that you can find out what is the most
probable tag sequence in a very very ah efficient
manner ok so what should be in good algorithm
so so let me take this this figure this example
to to give you the intuition on what kind
of algorithm would be used for finding the
actual tag sequence so to do it efficiently
ok so the idea here is that if you are enumerated
all the thirty two possibilities you are doing
some computations again and again ok so can
you try to reduce the time by doing it in
a dynamic programming approach where you first
store computations for the smaller paths and
use that for the larger paths so we have seen
one particular example of dining programming
in in the case of added distance
so we will try to use a similar concept here
for for decoding the actual tag sequence and
this will be called viterbi decoding ok so
looking at the picture so how you can save
the computation time ok so let's take this
sentence here now let's let me take two different
paths so one path that is there in the actual
sequence s v b d t o v b d t and n m and let
me take another path that is v b d t u then
j j then d t and then n n ok so there are
two paths that we start with the same tag
and end with the same tag ok so so so in v
b d to v b n n p sorry d t n n and v b d t
o j j d t n n ok so now they are two different
tag sequences ok and i will i want to find
out probability of both of these to find out
which one is better now what is the idea of
viterbi decoding the idea is that so you are
ending with the same sequence here d t and
n m ok so let us look at only till that point
tell d t because after d t the computation
will be the probabilities will be the same
ok
so this is one way of saving computation ok
in both of these the composition of d t will
be the same so you can save on that but what
is more important here so when you arrive
at the tech d t in one case you are coming
from v b another case you are coming from
j j ok so there are two different ways you
are coming to d t in these two sequences let
us suppose that at this point ok i can store
for the word or further tech d t what is the
best way of arriving at d t is it via this
path or is it via this path so i suppose i
can find out at this point what is the best
way of arriving a d t is it this path of that
path
if i can store if i can somehow find that
the later computations will so for the two
paths the later computations will be the same
ok so then i do not need to compute these
probabilities again for the next sequence
so if i can store at this point that the best
way is coming from v b and not from j j so
then i am doing it for the next next steps
that are going by d t i do not need to explore
this path so this is the idea suppose i write
them as steps so step one two three four and
five at each step for each part of speech
tag if i can store what is the best previous
tag from which it is it should come so what
which previous tag will maximize the probability
of arriving at this particular tag then the
computation of shared for the same path and
i do not need to repeat the same computation
again again so in this particular example
once i can store at step four for d t the
best way is coming from v b and not from j
j when i go further i need not worry about
this path at all i can simply continue with
this path ok because if this probability is
p one this is p two the next probability will
be shared it will be times probability of
n n given d t and probability of bill given
n m ok that will be shared across the two
paths so if i know at this point p two is
higher than p one i can probably fo i can
forget this path for going via d t and this
is the idea this i will do for each of the
speech step
so similarly for step three for each of the
four part four part of speech tags like for
v b i will so so here it is easy because for
each part of speech tag it can come only via
t o ok so it it is important for this case
because for d t it can come via four previous
tags so i needed store which of the previous
tags it is coming from which has the highest
probability similarly fine and p which of
the four previous tags has the highest probability
so that is what i am going to do a d c step
for each part of speech take i will store
what is the best probability of arriving at
this part of speech ok
so let us look at the formulation so intuition
is that so as i have explained we are recording
what is the optimal path at each state for
a given step ok what we are storing what is
the cheapest cost of arriving at a particular
ah state that means that has the highest probability
in the cheapest cost now once we have found
out what are the tags at different points
we also want to write down the sequence so
i also need to store a batteries so this is
the highest probability so what is the particular
part of speech tag that gives the highest
this highest probability ok so i want to store
this delta j s what that is the cheapest cost
or the highest probability to step j at step
s and also the backtrace from that state to
the best predecessor ok so for the previous
example that we were seen for d t the best
predecessor was v b and not j ok
so now so this i am doing at any step as for
state j how do i use that to compute for the
next step ok so let us again look look at
it so suppose i have stored delta j s ok so
here s is three and j is my state it can be
v b j j n n and r b so i have stored for all
these part four different part of speech tags
what is the cheapest cost of arriving at this
point what does that mean i i know at this
point which path is better v b d t o v b or
v b n t o v b ok so i know that for all these
four different part of speech tags so i store
the step for this step for this state what
is the optimal cost other what is the most
probable path so this cost i have or this
probability i have now how do i use this probability
is to compute for the next step say want to
compute delta j plus one s how will i compute
that so now delta g s would have taken care
of the word back already so what are the things
that i added for going from
so i am sorry here this should be stepped
yes so this is delta j s plus one ok so this
is a stap s plus one i want to find out probability
delta j
so i know the probabilities are step s now
what is the additional information the transition
from this is state to this state and the emission
probability of this word given is the state
so i can compute it using delta j s plus one
is delta i s times the probability of this
tag sequence that is probability of tag t
j given t i this is the probability of tag
sequence transition and the emission probability
that is probability of word edge step s plus
one given t j ok
so this i am doing for some ith state but
there are four p there can be some n number
of states so i will find out the max of those
among all the states at the previous step
i have delta s i multiplied with it the transition
probability and the emission probability at
at step s plus one ok and the max gives me
what is the best path at this is state j at
step as for this one ok so now suppose out
of these four i found out this is the best
path so we will also like to store what is
the best predecessor ok and this is nothing
but orgmax of this function ok so i call that
size s plus one that is orgmax of the same
function ok and that is what i am also storing
and that's all this will continue so what
will happen at the end i am at a step five
ok and i know what is the probability so let
me write down delta n n at five and delta
v b at five i know both these probabilities
what is the best way of reaching at this state
what is the best probability of reaching at
this state at this fine i can just take the
maximum of these two and this will give me
the the best probability of any possible part
of speech tag sequence and then i can use
the backtraces from here to obtain the actual
part of speech tag sequence and this is my
vita by decoding algorithm
so if we see that formally so yes so i am
i am storing at each step s what is the cheapest
cause of the best probability of reaching
there also the predecessor and using that
i am also computing the probabilities for
the next step ok that is so that is similar
to what we have seen here the probability
at the previous step transition probability
and emission probability then i take the max
over all the previous possible states also
show the predecessor for the next step and
how do we end once we have gone through the
sentence end i will have the probabilities
for all the states possible at the end the
ending word i will take the maximum of those
n backtrace from there and that will give
me the optimal automat tag sequence for this
particular sentence ok
so i hope this algorithm is clear so let us
take a simple example so that you can become
much more familiar with that how do you use
this video decoding algorithm finding problem
so what do you see in this in this problem
i have a sentence
the light book ok and you are given some sort
of emission probabilities first that the word
the can come from the tag determiner or noun
so they are two possibilities determiner noun
the word light can come from noun adjective
and verb ok possibility by using vita b decoded
algorithm so how do we start so i have three
steps one two three ok so i want to store
at each step for each state ok so let me call
it delta one at step one similarly delta two
as step one ok so what is the this probability
so this will be what is the probability that
the tag determiner occurs in the start of
the sentence multiply with the probability
of emitting the from the tag determiner ok
so let us see how these probabilities given
in this case probability of determine occurring
in the start of the sentence so in this question
in the la in the last ah sentence it is written
assume that all the tags that have the same
probability stop in the beginning of the sentence
so probabilities are given implicitly ok so
now the question is it how many tags would
you assume so here you can take any assumption
so in this question you are shown only four
tags determiner noun verb an adjective so
assume there are only four part of speech
tags and each one has equal probability of
occurring at the start of the sentence so
what will the probability of determine occurring
at the start of sentence it will be one by
four ok similarly for noun one by four times
probability of the given determiner and that
is given here h point three ok i am probability
of the given noun is given as point one so
this is your delta two one and delta one one
so you can also further write them oh point
zero two five and this will be point zero
seven five so better write them as two point
five into ten to power minus two seven point
five into ten to the minus two ok
so you have delta one one del two one now
you go to the next step ok so now here you
want to find out delta one two in step two
what is the best probability of reaching noun
noun noun you can reach via either here or
here ok so you need to compute both the possibilities
and take the max over that so let us compute
this probabilities ok so what will be that
so first will be delta one one times probability
of getting noun from determine
times probability of light given noun s and
second one will be delta two one times probability
noun given noun times probability light given
noun ok so let us compute these two probabilities
so you will take the max of these ok so let
us compute compute these probabilities so
this would be
so let me take it here seven point five into
ten to the minus two probability of noun given
to determiner so that is that we can see from
the table given to us noun given determiner
point five and light given noun each three
into ten to power minus three ok and this
gives me three point seven five into three
eleven point twenty five into ten to the minus
five and the second one becomes two point
five into ten to power minus two times probability
of n given n this is point two into probably
at given and that will be three into ten to
the minus three ok and that is point five
one point five one point five into ten to
power minus five ok and from these two you
can say that this one is higher than the next
one so this is what you will take so you can
store delta one two h eleven point two five
into ten to power minus five ok and you will
also store the backtrace that is coming from
this path ok same thing you will do for adjective
and verb adjective again there will be two
possibilities coming from determiner and noun
for work there will be two possibilities again
you compute the probabilities using the formula
and store what is the best probability so
it will be delta three at step two delta two
h step ok
so this is what you will store also you will
store the backtrace once you have done that
now we'll go to the final step so where you
will store delta one step three one means
noun here and delta two at the step three
again you will compute that by taking all
the three possibilities times the transition
and all so this will be max over three quantity
this will be max over three quantities again
you will find out the two values delta one
three and delta two three and how will you
actually determine the finest sequence you
will take the max of this suppose max comes
out to be this one then you will go to the
predecessor ok suppose the predecessor was
this one you will go to hear suppose predecessor
of as this one and so on so you will find
out this sequence assuming this is the these
are the best fervent ok
but i hope the idea is clear that how do you
actually do this computation so i would encourage
that you you complete this particular exercise
on your own now coming to the the point of
learning the parameters so what are the parameters
do we need in the in the so we need three
different parameters ok so we need the probability
of starting the sentence ok that is let me
call this in the in the in the language of
h m m the pi that is what is the probability
that a particular tag or estate start the
sequence ok so i want this probability pi
i for all posh tags ok then i need the probability
of transition from one part of speech at another
ok so this my transition matrix i need all
this a i j transiting from probability t j
given t i s and i need my emission probabilities
that is probability of the word given a tag
so you can use it using a matrix b so i need
all these three probabilities to actually
use this viterbi decoding algorithm at runtime
if i do not have these probabilities i cannot
teach you viterbi decoding
so the question is so these are my parameters
of the h m so how do we actually find out
these parameters of my h m so here i am saying
there are two different scenarios that you
might have ok so first scenario is where a
label data set is available what do you mean
by a label data set you have a set of sentences
available to you for each sentence you also
know what is the actual part of speech tags
sequence so what is the part of speech tag
for individual world somebody is manually
labeled it for you so this is a label data
set this one scenario second scenario is you
only have the corpus but you do not have any
data where the sentences are labeled with
the part of speech categories ok so i have
the tooks is a clear so scenario one where
you have a label data set a scenario to only
corpus but no labels so what i am saying for
these two scenarios you can find the parameters
in different manner so suppose you have scenario
one you have a label data set so what you
can do for finding the parameters of h m m
so this is something we also took them the
in the last week
so for example if the label data set i want
to find a parameter like them the transition
probabilities probability of tags a given
tag i how will you find that the label data
set you will have all the possible tag sequences
that actually occurred in the corpus now from
that you will find out number of times t i
n t j occur together in the corpus divided
by number of times only t i occurs so this
was what we said as maximum likelihood estimator
you can use that to find this probability
same with all the other probabilities pi i
as well as p you can find using maximum likelihood
estimate
now problem comes when you have the corpus
but no labels ok so now there are no labels
so how would you actually find out probability
of t j given t i when in the in the data there
is no label on which word got a tag t i or
which one got it at t j so you cannot compute
it directly from the from from any labels
so what is the method that you will use for
learning the parameters when the corpus is
available but labels are not available and
that is what we will see in the next lecture
ok
so we will be using baum welch algorithm to
estimate the parameters of the hidden markov
model when the labels are not available ok
so this is similar to expectation maximization
algorithm and you will see what is the addition
for this algorithm and how we actually apply
this ok so hope in this lecture you understood
how to apply with viterbi decoding when the
parameters of h m m are given ok and so you
can do that for and in the next lecture we
will discuss how do we run the parameters
when the labels are not available
thank you