so welcome back for the second lecture of
this week so in the last lecture we were ah
discussing viterbi decoding for h m ms and
in the end we discussed the problem of learning
the parameters of h m ms and we say that when
the label data set available we can simply
estimate using maximum likelihood estimate
ok by by the label data set but if the label
data set is not available then how do we actually
learn the parameters of the system and we
said we will be using some sort of expectation
algorithm and in this particular case this
is called baum welch baum welch algorithm
so baum welch algorithm as i was saying this
is a well known e m algorithm to estimate
the maximum likelihood for the parameters
of the h m m ok so ah so what are the parameters
of h m m that you want to estimate ok let
we just formally define them and then we will
see how do we estimate them using buam welch
so in in the h m m model so we have a hidden
state at every time point and an observation
variable ok so here i am using capital x t
to denote the random variable that is the
hidden state and capital y to denote the observation
variable ok so both x t and y t can take many
many different values for our part of speech
tag is each x t can take one of the part of
speech tags and each y t can take one of the
possible votes ok
so this my my ah hidden variable hidden state
x t and the observation y t the parameters
are a b and pi that we discussed last time
what is a so a is my state transition matrix
so given given that the previous state was
i what is the probability that the current
state will be j ok so here the t as such does
not matter what matters is that the state
j occurred after state i at any any given
time point then i have the parameter pi that
is what is the probability that this particular
state is starts the sequence so probability
of x one that the the first state beam the
i x state that is my pi a and then thirdly
i have the emission matrix so where the entries
are what is the probability of observing this
particular word or this observation given
the current state ok so this i am denoting
like b j y t at the state j what is the probability
of i am meeting the observation variable or
observation y so either three parameters three
set of parameters that parameters i have learnt
so
now what is given to me ok so i was saying
that we are given the coppers not labeled
but the seek the word sequences are given
so this is this can be seen as y observations
are given different sentences are given i
knew what are different words occurred in
the sentences so i can say that i am given
a set of observations in data ok so here i
can say that i am given a set of observation
sequences that the first observation was the
word y one then y two up to some y t where
y t denote the end of the sentence so i am
given a set of observation sequences and my
aim is to find out the optimal set of parameters
theta that maximize the probability of this
observation so these observation sequences
so that is where i am using buam welch algorithm
find out what are the optimal set of parameters
theta that will maximize the pro probability
of likelihood of observing this observation
that's why i am using expectation maximization
algorithm so what so what is the main intuition
of of e m so idea would be i want to estimate
the parameters a b n pi so what i will do
i will start with some random initial ah probabilities
for all all these parameters i will initialize
them with some random values so i have all
these probabilities ok
now using this initial values i will try to
find out what are the probabilities of various
state paths so i give on a given sequence
what is the probability that a particular
state would have occurred given these parameters
so once i have obtained the probabilities
of different state paths or different states
a different point now i i got this this probability
i will use that again to compute to re to
re estimate my parameters so i will get started
with theta zero i get some theta prime ok
now i will again use the theta prime to complete
my state paths probabilities again use that
to compute recompute my parameters until it
somehow converges ok
so this is my trade devaluate first use some
parameters theta to get some likely from the
data for the hidden variable here that is
the states once you have that that likelihood
or the probabilities use that to compute my
my theta ok so so what we are doing here so
i am start starting by choosing some initial
values of the parameters a b m pi ok and then
i have to repeat the following steps until
convenience what is that firstly determine
what are the probable paths ok that x t minus
one that t minus one object point i see the
state i at tth i see the state j and so on
what is the probability of various state paths
now once i have these will teach count the
number of times so what is important expect
a number of times because we are only computing
probabilities we are not finding the actual
paths so count the expected number of transitions
a i j as well as the expected number of times
various emissions b j y t m eight ok so using
these state paths can you do that yes i know
what is the probability of x t minus one is
equal to i h t is equal to chain i can use
it to compute an expected value for a i j
and this is what we will be doing so will
compute a i j similarly i al already know
the observation so i can also computes unexpected
vanish for b j y t what is the probability
that i see objection y t for the particular
state j so once i computed this a i j and
d j y t i will again estimate my parameters
theta using these these computed values ok
now i will go back in the loop i have this
theta i will compute the probabilities of
various state paths ok again compute a i j
b j y t and again compute theta and i repeat
that until convergence
so now what is so so all these are interesting
here like firstly once you are given some
set of parameters theta it can be either the
initial parameters or some intermediate parameters
how do you actually compute different the
probabilities of different paths how do you
actually do it and for that we use a forward
backward algorithm that is the ah main concept
of this algorithm ok so let us see what is
this forward backward algorithm ok so in forward
by back backward algorithm we have a forward
procedure and a backup procedure ok so so
far for explaining let me just take show it
on paper ones so what is happening i am observing
this sequence y one y two y small t y t minus
one y t this is my observation ok and correspondingly
so you can say this is y one is equal to y
one first observation y two is equal to y
two and so on ok and correspondingly there
are states so is my observation and then there
are states so there will be some state x t
this is y t observation is my state x t is
equal to y it can be any of the possible states
x t now what do i do in this forward backward
algorithm i compute two different probabilities
one i called as the forward probability this
is the probability of observing y one to y
t plus and x t is equal to i give my parameter
theta so this is my alpha t for the i of the
state the probability that i am observing
y one to y t and at t h point the state is
i given a parameters theta
ok y one is equal to y one y two is equal
to y two y t is equal to small y t and x t
is equal to y given parameters theta this
is my forward ah probability then i compute
a backward probability what is that this is
the probability of observing this given this
state ok
so this is my alpha i t and there is beta
i t that is probability that y t plus one
is small y t plus one up to capitol y t is
y t given x t is equal to i and theta so these
are two different probabilities that i state
so what do you see here so i am taking just
a state at a particular time t a particular
state time
now why do you actually compute this alpha
i t and beta i t how does that help now i
have these probabilities i can simply multiply
these alpha t times beta i t to get the probability
that i observe the sequence and the i of the
state ok and to actually compute the probability
of c saying that at t h time point the state
was i i can margini marginalize it by all
the possible states that can happen at time
t ok so i can multiply sigma i t beta i t
and divide by all the possible sigma j t alpha
j t n beta j t to compute the probability
of seeing state i at time point t and this
is thats how this forward and backward probabilities
help ok so you will see that in detail ok
so right now just the formulation so i am
this higher the sequence i divided in two
parts for a given t this is state i i have
the forward probability alpha i t and a backward
probability beta i t alpha i t is this further
sequence and the state beta is the ending
sequence given this is state the previous
state x is equal to i ok so now so this is
my alpha i t ok so now how do i compute these
values of alpha i t i want to compute this
for all possible i's and all possible values
of t so this is a forward probability so i
have to start with the first point so how
do i actually compute alpha i one ok what
is that so alpha i one from this equation
which probability of observing y one is equal
to y one ok and x one is i given theta so
what is the probability of x one is equal
to i given theta that is pi i ok this is my
pi i and this probability would be emission
from x one from the either state so this will
be b i y one ok so this is how i will compute
the initial one alpha i one for all possible
states i
now at some point of time ok at some point
t plus one how will i compute alpha j t plus
one given the previous alpha i t i have completed
so alpha j t plus one ok so t plus one means
the probability of seeing the sequence up
to white t plus one and the state x t plus
one is j so how can i compute that using the
previous alphas so i have the i have the previous
alpha that gives me this so alpha i t at the
previous time step i had some state i i have
the transition from i to j so times a i j
and now i have the emission for the t plus
oneth observation that is b j y t plus one
and this i can obtain from any of the previous
states so i have to sum over all the possible
states ok so from all the previous states
at the t h time step i can be an estate i
i have the transition probabilities and the
emission probability for t plus one and that
is how i can compute sigma alpha j t plus
one from all the alpha i t h so this is how
you can compute your alpha then because a
manner starting from alpha i one
what will you do for your betas ok so this
is a backward processor so what is my beta
i t this gives me the probability of ending
the sequence with y t plus one two y t given
the state i a time this is my backward procedure
now this i again compute aggressively in alpha
i was starting from the first word i was campaigning
alpha i t in betas because the backward procedure
i will first compute beta i capital t t is
the end of the sequence and what will the
beta i t so beta i t would be probability
of so given that previous the t h point state
is i having a sequence on t plus one but there
is no word from t plus one so this will always
be so this is always be one this will be a
null sequence so this is always one
now i have to compute it recursively for all
other beta i at time point t ok so here i
am going backwards so you assume that you
have completed all the beta j at time t plus
one and you want to use that to compute beta
i at time point t how will you do that so
this is very similar to what you did in the
case of alpha so we can see this so this is
beta j at time t plus one transition probabilities
from i to j and the emission probabilities
probability for the t plus oneth observation
and you sum over all the possible states at
times so very very similar to what you did
in the case of forward procedure so that's
what you will do in the backward procedure
for computing beta h in a recursive manner
ok so now you have the a way that given the
set of parameters minus theta you can compute
all this alpha and beta ok so all the alpha
i t is an beta i t you can complete now remember
what is the next step in the algorithm you
want to find out what are the best possible
paths or what is the probability of various
paths that is what we intended by doing this
alpha and beta let us see how exactly we can
compute these probabilities of various paths
so i want to compute the probabilities of
say probability x is equal to y given my observation
and parameters theta also i want to compute
x t is equal to y and x t plus one is equal
to j given y n theta i want to compute both
of this so if i can compete both of this i
can i can compute all the parameters i can
complete my transition probabilities using
that i can compute my initial probabilities
using that by taking t is equal to one and
you can also compute my ambition probabilities
so now my problem is once i commuted alphas
and betas can i compute these probabilities
ok so that is what we will see next
so i am giving these some some names so firstly
i have this gamma i t that gives me the probability
that at t th point the state is i given my
observations y plus theta parameters and similarly
i have zeta i j t that is probability that
at t th point i have state i t plus one point
i will change a given by n theta so gamma
i t is written terms of multiplication of
alpha i t and beta i t ok divided by summation
over all possible sigma z alpha j t and beta
j t over all possible change so now how how
do we actually come up with this ah equation
of gamma i t and and zeta i j t let us look
at it ok so here i want to compute probability
x t given x t is equal to y given y n theta
so now i will computed using probability x
t is equal to y y given theta divided by probability
y given theta ok the simple conditions ok
so if you follow that theta this is nothing
but x t is equal to y given by x t is equal
to y y divided by probability y this simple
the condition probability row
now this one i am writing is summation j is
equal to one over n equal to one to n probability
x t is equal to j y given theta ok so now
you can see the symmetry in this equation
now what i what i have to show that alpha
i t times beta i t is probability x t is equal
to y y given theta and that is very easy because
what is alpha i t this is probability y one
to y t plus x t is equal to i what is beta
i t probability of y t plus one to y capital
t and now x t is equal to y is already given
for beta and this is given my parameters theta
ok and this is what we are seeing here this
is my alpha i t times beta i t and this is
marginalizing over all possible states that
time bind so this will be sigma j equal to
one to n alpha j t beta j t so this gives
me the equation for gamma i t similarly you
can see for zeta i j t that is for probability
of x is equal to i x t plus one is equal to
j y given y n theta so in the same way you
can write it as probability x t is equal to
i x t plus one is equal to j y given theta
divided by probability y given theta that
will marginalize over all possible i n j ok
and you will say probability x t is equal
to i x t plus one is equal to j y given theta
for all possible values of phi n j
now what we have to show that is that this
is actually this formula ok now so what is
this so you are given state at time point
t and time point t plus one so what you are
actually doing is that using the forward procedure
from y one to y t and you will also get the
state at state i at time point t and you will
use the backward procedure because you are
given the state at time t plus one state j
beggar procedure for from y t plus two up
to y capital t ok so this is what is cap captured
in alpha i t and this is captured condition
on j in beta in beta j t plus one then you
will compute the probability of transition
from i to j that is a i j ok and y t plus
one given j that is your d j y t plus one
ok so this equation is nothing but probability
of x t is equal to y x t plus one is equal
to j y given theta this whole sequence is
there and these two states are also and similarly
you can see for the for here this is over
all the possible values of i and j ok
so i hope this is clear that once i have completed
all the possible alpha and beta and the parameters
are the previous parameters of the ah we can
compute this gamma i t and zeta i j t th that
are probability of state at a given time and
a sequence i and j at time t and t plus one
ok this we can compute using alpha and beta
now coming to the last part that is once i
computed some probability is over by possible
state paths how do i estimate my parameters
again ok i have started with some initial
parameters computed this now i want to re
estimate my parameters theta so how do i do
that so now i have to estimate my pi i a j
and b i v k so how do i estimate this pi i
is probability of seeing the state i at time
one so now from these parameters which one
can give me this value probability that x
one is equal to i the second get from gamma
a one ok that is that can give me my pi i
is probability that at x x one is i so this
is to estimate my pi next thing i have to
estimate is transition probabilities probability
of going from state i to state j now i have
completed this ok so how do i compute my e
i j e i j would be at all possible times how
many times you are having the sequence i n
j so this will be summation over t zeta i
j ok jee ji zeta i j t is each i followed
by j divide by over all the times when you
are seeing this t ok so when you are seeing
the state i and this you can compute using
your gamma i that is summation over t gamma
i t and that will give me my a i j all the
possible cases where all the all the probabilities
of i and j having together at any point divide
by all the probabilities of anyway this is
my a i j and similarly how can you compute
your b j say v k that is at state j you are
emitting v k how can you estimate that so
for that you have to find out whenever you
are in state j is the observation actually
v k how many times we are in state j by the
observation is we can divide by number of
times you are in state j ok so this is so
here the nominator is easy that is number
of times you are so this b j v k a number
of times you are in state j this is gamma
j t numerator number of times or the probability
that you are in state j times the observation
is actually v k ok
now so at time t the observation is small
y t ok so i can use some sort of a simple
notation or indicator function one v k is
equal to y t so indicator function ok what
do indicator function so one v k is equal
to y t will be one if v k is actually y t
and zero otherwise listen to my indicator
function so now whenever if v k is y t whenever
i observe y t i will add it otherwise it will
be zero and this is this will give me the
emission probabilities so i could estimate
my pi a i j as well as b j v k using this
zeta i j and gamma i i which i computed using
my forward backward probabilities and this
is one complete pass of this algorithm ok
now i have these parameters i will plug these
again to compute alphas and betas again compute
my gamma and zetas and again estimate the
parameters until it converges ok and this
is the buam welch algorithm for for landing
the parameters of h m m when the label data
set is not available so this gives you a very
nice handle on ah h m ms so you can apply
h m ms when you have the label data set very
easily by by learning the parameters directly
from h m ms maximum likelihood estimate and
data beta decoding but even if you get a new
ah problem or a new language furtherer you
have to compute part-of-speech tax but you
do not have the labels you can use it this
buam welch algorithm to estimate the parameters
of a h m m and then you should have enter
the code to to actually given a new sentence
find at part of speech tag sequence
so and you can use that for any other sequence
label task so this completes our discussions
on h m ms that are that were one of the very
popular models for ah this part is fish tagging
in many other sequence labeling task but they
they have certain limitations and that is
what we will discuss next then that what are
these limitations and how do some other models
some so we will go to now some discriminative
classifiers like maxim and role models they
get rid of these limitations so this is for
h m ms let us lets let's look at maxima into
the models in the next lecture
thank you