so welcome back for the third module of this
week so in the last week we have in the last
module we had finished the discussions on
hidden markov models how do we learn the parameters
and how do we use that for estimating the
part of speech tags sequences for a given
sentence hidden markov models for generative
models ok and if you remember we discussed
this distinction between generative model
and discriminative model so we will see a
discriminative model maximum entropy model
for this sequence labeling task but before
that let me start with some sort of motivation
and why do we move from h m m s to maximum
entropy model what are the limitations of
h m m
so then problem with the h m m s also this
is known as the markov model tagging is handling
unknown words suppose at run time you get
some unknown word that was not there in the
corpus because the prob the emission probabilities
will not be known there is no where you can
come to you can actually use the viterbi decoding
so what do you do in that case so you might
want to use some sort of morphological cues
ok suppose the word we word is ending with
e d you might think that over this might be
a past tense of a word that we did not encounter
in in the corpus or suppose you are finding
capitalization in the middle of the set of
the sentence you might think that this might
be a proper name name
but how do we actually include that in hidden
markov models second so we use the first order
markov assumption where each tag dependent
on the previous only on the previous tag so
this does not take care of certain certain
situations for example here i have two sentences
is clearly marked was such he clearly marked
so what you seeing here ah marked in one case
is a past participle in the first case second
case it is a verb in past tense but just the
previous context is not sufficient to tell
this ok so so so because in h m m s we are
only using this the previous context this
might not be sufficient to handle this particular
case
so how will you ah take care of this issue
so you might want to move to a higher order
h m m say it second order ok so you can use
a high order model but this is just one some
some limitations suppose you want to use what
whether this is the first word in the sentence
ok or you ah you want to you want use any
arbitrary arbitrary think like ah whether
there is a verb ending with e d previous to
this word you want to use this information
there is no way you can use that in in the
case of achievements so that's where we we
move from achievements to my explanatory model
that allow very very heterogeneous set of
features so you can use a lot of different
of your wishes from the data for your model
so so what is the important distinction so
now in the maximum entropy model so they are
discriminative as compared to ah generative
models which are as means you are allowed
to identify very very heterogeneous set of
features not only the tag given the previous
tag or the word given the tag you can use
any sort of features which might which you
think might contribute to the choice of part
of speech tags ok
so so for example whether this is the first
word of the article this is something that
you can use as a feature in in maximum entropy
model or whether the next word is t o you
can use the next word as a feature whether
one of the five previous five words is a preposition
this is again something that you can use as
a feature in maximum entropy model but here
h m m cannot make each of this
so what maximum model does it combines all
this various heterogeneous features in probabilistic
framework ok to be able to come up with the
actual part of speech tag sequence for a given
sentence so so this is the maximum entropy
model so this is how you write the probability
of so why is the class that is one of the
the probability for any of the tags given
x is my observation it can include anything
in my in my context it can load load the current
word previous word next word anything in the
sentence ok you can so you can define your
context while you are dealing with maximum
entropy model you are saying that i can i
can use all this information in my features
given this i want to compute the probability
of my class and here discriminative model
so i can directly compute the probability
of class given the observation ok so i can
compete y given x and how do i i compute that
it is simply x is a logging in model so summation
over lambda i and f i x y now f i x y are
my various features that i have identified
over my observation x and my class y and lambda
is are the weight is the weight given to the
feature f i so each feature f i is given a
weight lambda
so i i i summed over all the possible lambda
is fi's and taking the exponent and then i
do some sort of normalization so that probability
y given x adds up to one for all the possible
classes y ok this is a normalization constant
so this is the very very simple form of maximum
entropy model so so let me tell again so z
x condition on the parameters lambda is normalization
constant so this is nothing but this exponent
you sum over all the possible class x y ok
for all the possible class x y you compute
this and add this so once you do that you
are you are ensuring that probability y given
x will added to one for all possible values
and lambdas are my features the weights given
to my different features
now x de denotes my observed data and y and
y denotes my class now what is interesting
is that what is the form of form that the
features in maximum entry model can take as
opposed to something like h m m what are the
features so what is interesting here you are
seeing f is is a function of x and y both
in the observation in the class so i am defining
my feature on on both of this and we are all
binary binary features so let us let us see
what are my features so in maximum entropy
model my feature send code elements from the
context x and the tag y now context x is now
this is something that you you must be careful
about context is not my current word w but
is taken around the word w ok i can define
my context it can be the sentence that contains
w it can be it's previous three words next
three words it it is something that can be
defined on the on the current word ok and
y is the tag that i have i am predicting
now what are my features these are binary
valued functions over x and y and this is
like f x y is one if a certain conditions
condition hold on x and y and zero otherwise
and here is one example what can be some conditions
like i am having the current word w if the
word w is capitalized and my tag y is n n
p then my feature f x y will take a value
of one otherwise it will take a value of zero
that is one sort of feature ok similarly you
can define any arbitrary set of features that
we have z so it can be f x y is equal to one
if one of the previous five words is as a
tag of preposition and the current tag is
save up this is one sort of a zero otherwise
so like that you can define an so you have
a lot of freedom here in defining and choosing
your features and once you have completed
all these features the model learns the the
weights for all these feature features the
the weights lambdas and then this is very
very simple function to compute the probability
of ah plus given any observation ok
so let's see some other examples for the features
ok so this is again for any generic sequence
labeling task so here it is for finding named
entities so it can be here like location drug
and person three different named entities
and some examples are given like in arcadia
arcadia is a location in quebec location taking
zantac zantac is drug and saw sauce you so
you see you as a person and now you are defining
certain features so let us see certain features
like the first feature is my tag is location
so my class y is location previous word that
is on x previous word is in and my current
word is capitalized
so what are all the cases we have this feature
will be one it will be one here in arcadia
previous what is a in and it is capitalized
and the tag is location it will also be one
for second case is capitalized previous word
is in and the tag is location next feature
so y is location and w has an extended leg
in latin character so you can see that you
are using a very very arbitrary set of features
ok but possibly you have some some hypothesis
that this features will be helpful for this
task operating the predicting the tag for
this word so this is this feature so for which
of the case it will be one so it will be one
for the second case it has an extended latin
character ok the and the tag is location
third feature y is a drug and the word ends
with c and there will be one for taking zantac
yes the word w ends to the c so you so you
can see some some examples of what kind of
features you can take but important thing
is to know the intuition that you can choose
any feature around the word w and that involves
also the current class so how do we so now
once i have all these features suppose the
the learning has taken place i know all the
parameters lambdas how do i go about tagging
my sentence with that x so i have the words
in my corpus w one to w a and i i want to
find out the tags document tags so what i
will do i want to find out tags sequence t
one to t n
so any sequence will have this condition probability
right so n so t i conditioned on x i for i
is equal to one to i now this is x i not w
i x i is my context around the word w i and
this is independent so i can use this model
to find out what is the optimal tag sequence
i can do it independently for each word and
then i will find out tag sequence ok so so
as we have said my context x i includes may
also include some previously assigned tags
for a fixed history and i will be using a
beam search algorithm for finding the optimal
or the most probable sequence this is something
we will take up in the in the next ah lecture
in detail that how do we actually come go
about doing beam search in maximum entropy
model ok
so yeah just a brief idea here in beef search
beam search what you do actually so you have
ah positions in the sentence a starting from
one to the end so at each position we will
keep only the top k possible sequences and
next time starting from this k ah k complete
sequences you find out what are the next k
based sequences ok so so let me just quickly
say so i have from suppose my sentence as
n words so what is the idea suppose my size
beam size is k so at point one i will keep
top k sequences so at point one i will have
only one part of speech tags so that means
i will keep top k part of speech tags at it's
position one now when i go to position two
now i will have a sequence now two might have
some some other possibilities of part of speech
tags so what i will do i will find out the
probability of each of these k with all part
of speech tags here and you store top k sequences
again ok so tag one tag two some case top
k sequences again at three i have some possibilities
top k times these probabilities this possibilities
again you store only top k out of this and
you keep on doing that ah until you are here
so here you will to choose the best one and
that will give you the complete sequence so
important here is that at each point you are
is storing top k full sequences which starting
from the initial point so here you will you
will you will find some t one t two you will
find some t one t two t three and so on top
k at it's time so we will look at this in
detail in the next lecture so for now let
us look at the basics of maxent maximum entropy
model so what is a maximum entropy model so
maximum entropy model have this particular
principle that is you are given the observation
and you have certain hypothesis so ah you
take what is given to you but do not make
any additional ah assumptions so that is take
the model that satisfies all the questions
that you having but does not take any other
ah assumptions ok
so so what does that mean so you are given
a collection of facts yes and you want to
take a model that is satisfying all these
facts or you are saying that is consistent
with all these facts but otherwise it is not
making any further assumption that is after
being ah after satisfying all these constraints
it is as uniform as possible or in other words
for all the possible models that satisfy a
given set of constraints choose the one that
is the most uniform of all
now what do i mean by this let's take a simple
example so here i have an so this i have a
simple example i have an english word in and
i want to make some transition system that
tries to mimic some so it is translating from
english to french ok and i want i have some
data already with me from some actual translator
who who translated some sentences from english
to french
now so i want to model the this expert translators
decision that how do i i translate this word
in to any french word now how do i start so
so suppose you have a vocabulary of all possible
french phrases ok and you want to estimate
probability p f so that is what is the probability
that that french phrase will be a translation
of the english word in so you want to compute
that for all the possible french phrases they
might be say millions of french phrases so
so what you will do we will start by collecting
a large sample of instances of expert decisions
ok
now from this facts you will try from this
sample you will try to observe some ah some
facts for example so so the goal would be
extract some facts from the sample of instances
and then use these facts inside your model
ok so firstly you have to extract the facts
so in our scenario this will be equivalent
to finding out the features that is my facts
and once i found these features or the facts
i use them rightly in my model
so let us see what are the different sort
of facts i can find out for example this can
be my first clue so i find that in all the
samples i have seen the translator always
translates in into one of these five phrases
dans ah a au cours de pendant so they are
five different french phrases where the translator
is translating so now now this is now this
is helpful to explain what is the my maximum
entropy model now i want to find out the probability
of the probability distribution over french
phrases all so suppose i have ah say one million
french phrases so f one to f ah million ok
so i have one million french phrases i want
to compute this probability distribution i
want to find out the probability distribution
given this constraint that is the translator
always chooses among from one of these five
phases so what is my constraint this would
be so let me call these ah f one f two f three
f four or say dans ah and also let me call
these probability say f one plus probability
f two plus probability f three plus probability
f four plus probability f five is equal to
so this is my constraint
now so so now given this constraint i have
to choose one model so suppose i have only
this much information from the data now what
is the model that i should choose among all
the possibilities now firstly do you think
there are infinite number of possibilities
in which i can choose my model that satisfy
this constraint so of course probability for
f six to probability f million will be zero
ok because if any if any of this is nonzero
this constraint will not be satisfied
yes so because all all the probabilities need
to add up to one so that means all this has
is this is anyways easy but what are all the
models that will satisfy this constraint so
you can see there are infinite solutions for
this for this equation so you can choose p
f one any number from zero to two one and
you can always find some f two f three f four
f five that will satisfy and same goes for
f two and so on so there are infinite models
that satisfy this constraint
now what maximum entropy model does among
all the models that satisfy this constraint
it takes the one that is most uniform now
among all these models what is the most uniform
model so that is you are not making any dimensions
given this constraint take the model that's
most uniform so it is easy to see in this
case that the most uniform model will be one
that gives p f i is equal to one by five for
i is equal to one to five ok for all these
five phrases gives the probability one by
five and everything else it gives a probability
zero so this is the most uniform model given
this constraint yes so allocate the total
probability evenly among all these five phrases
that is the most uniform model subject to
our knowledge
now is this the most uniform model overall
suppose i didn't have this constraint what
was the most uniform model as such the most
uniform model will be that gives equal probability
to each of the million french phrases so it's
gives the probability of one by million to
each of these that is a most uniform model
so the model that i have obtained which is
giving probability one by five to each of
these five it not the most uniform model it
is most uniform given this constraint ok given
this constraint this is the most uniform model
and this is the idea so so i will take some
facts some observations given the observations
i will find out what is the most uniform model
let's take let's go further so this was easy
in this case so where we had five phases only
knows i got a second clue that the expert
chose either dans or en thirty percent of
the time ok so we were supposed f one and
f two so now i have so this is my constraint
one so now i have constraint two p f one plus
p f two is equal to zero point three now given
these two constraints what would be the most
uniform model so if you just take a quick
look you can see that the most uniform model
will be p f one is equal to point one five
p f two is equal to point one five and f three
f of five f five which will get point seven
divided by three and that will set both both
the constraint this will be the most uniform
model ok so this is not as uniform as this
model so as you are getting more and more
observations you are going far from the most
uniform models but you are coming up with
some other models that i as uniform as possible
but satisfying these constraints
now what happens if you get a third clue like
in half of the case cases expert shows either
dans or an so that is p f two plus p f three
is equal to point five that is three you know
immediately you will see that it becomes difficult
to just look at this equation and try to solve
for what is the distribution that is most
uniform and that's why we we need to understand
the the concept of maximum entropy so i want
to find out the model that is most uniform
doing the constraints that is equivalent to
finding the model that is having the maximum
entropy among model ok
so now so yes how do we so as we get more
and more ah clues it becomes difficult to
see which is the most uniform model so for
that you have to understand how do we measure
the uniformity of a model and that's where
we use the idea of entropy so some of you
might have already come across this term of
entropy so what is entropy entropy measures
what is the ah uncertainty of dis dis distribution
so so going to the basics so suppose i have
an event x that occurs to the probability
of p x ok
so entropy measures what is the amount of
surprise in this event so if it is very very
surprising then ah the entropy will be high
if it is like very obvious then entropy will
be low so for an event when it is ah more
surprising when the probability is low probability
is high and the probability hi high it is
like obvious ok so then the entropy will be
low but when the probability when the so the
interview will be low but when the probability
is low so there is a lot of surprise in that
even if that happens then the probability
entropy is high so that's why entropy is ah
log of one by probability ok
so the probability is low entropy will be
high so for a distribution how do we compute
the entropy for a distribution so i just take
the expected value of surprise that is summation
over p x log one by p x ok so so i take the
expected surprise over all the possible values
of p so this is a very very a standard formula
for entropy minus summation p x log p x now
so here we are talking about distributions
in the case of distributions when will be
the entropy maximum so if you look at this
formula
so let's take one simple example of coin tossing
ok so i am tossing a coin so it can be head
or tail let us say that head has a probability
of p and tail has a probability of one minus
p ok so what is the entropy of this model
it will be minus p log p minus one minus p
log one minus p and if you actually so these
are all based on too if you actually go on
plotting this as a function of p from zero
to one you will find that the entropy it starts
increasing it becomes the highest at p is
equal to half and it starts decreasing afterwards
now can we intuitively understand this
so what we are saying when both head and tail
have equal probability then the entropy of
them of my model is the highest what is entropy
it measures how much is the surprise ok so
let's take a point like this so at this point
what will happen so head has a probability
very low probability but tail as a very high
probability so you more or less no ok it will
probably tail when you toss a coin it is probable
most probably be a tail so there is not ah
so there is not much more surprises that are
coming but when both head and tail have equal
probability then you are very very confused
you do not know whether the it will be head
or it will be tail so the amount of so expected
surprise that you will get is the maximum
ok so this is the idea so this is a distribution
over only ah this two variables p and ah this
p n q are you can say this have p n one minus
p
but even if you take any any n number of variables
the reservation will be having the maximum
en entropy wave whenever it is the most uniform
ok so this gives such the intuition that why
we chose the most uniform model for getting
the maximum entropy now coming back to a maximum
entropy model so we want to among all the
possible distributions we want to choose a
model that maximizes by entropy ok
now so i want to maximize entropy subject
to certain constraints right so we will have
certain constraints from the data and these
constraints are nothing but my features so
i will select some features and i will make
sure that the the ambiguous probability from
the data that i am finding for the features
is similar to the probability that my model
is giving that and subject to this constraint
i will ah i will maximize my problem my entropy
as you also seen as we keep on adding constraints
one by one the entropy of my model decreases
ok it comes close to my data initially might
start with the most uniform model that is
giving the equal probability to everything
but as you keep on adding constraint one by
one you come close you go far far away from
the most uniform model so you decrease your
entropy and you come closer to data so this
is the idea so give us some constraints we
want to come as close as possible to the data
but otherwise we want to obtain the most ah
most uniform model in terms of maximum entropy
so coming close the data in this case means
finding the ah empirical probabilities of
these features and ah i am trying to make
it trying the model probabilities to be close
to this so this is my maximum entropy principle
i am given some n different feature functions
f one to f n i want my probably distribution
p to lie in the subset in the subset of all
the possible distributions that satisfy this
constraint ok so all the all the ah probability
distributions that satisfy this constraint
among those i want to choose the one that
is having the maximum entropy ok so what do
i mean by satisfying this constraint so what
is the empirical count of or expectation of
a feature so empirical expectation means how
many times this features actually ah this
x y actually occurred and f i x y was one
in my data ok so p hat is my ah empirical
probability
now what will be my model probability so it
will be so model probability p f i it will
be summation x y p x y f x y now this p x
y because we are computing finally p y given
x i can write as summation x y p x p y given
x f x y ok and because we are not computing
p s n l model i can probably approximate it
with the ah empirical count of x so this gives
me the model probability of the feature so
i want to make it closer to the p tilde f
i that is the empirical probability of the
feature ok
so i have the empirical count model count
and i want to select the distribution that
is most uniform subject to this constraint
ok so now so i am computing this probability
distribution so what will be the maximum entropy
model that is the one that gives me the high
entropy h y given x and that if you do some
quickness that will be minus sigma x y p x
p y given x log p y given x ok and again we
will approximate this by p tilde ok so this
is my maximum entropy model and i want to
maximize it subject to constraint that this
and these are equal so this gives me the model
maximize this h subject to these constraints
ok
so for that we use the trick of being the
lagrangian ok so so i want to now a k lagrangian
p or lambda that is my h p plus summation
i lambda i p f i minus p tilde f i so that
is i want to maximize this sorry so i want
to maximize this yes subject to this constraint
ok
so now if i put these values inside this so
i will get plus sigma lambda i
summation x y p x y stepwise p tilde x p y
given x f x y minus summation x y p tilde
x y f x y ok this is my ah lagrangian and
i want to maximize that so i will i want to
find out this distribution that maximizes
this so let me just substitute this fifty
everywhere (Refer Time: 36:00 ok so in term
what you are doing you are maximizing it with
respect to this d and that you can do by differentiating
it with respect to d ok and then putting it
to zero and that will actually give you the
the equation that we have seen that is p lambda
y given x that is our t in this case it will
come out to be exponential over summation
lambda f i x y divided by the normalization
constant ok this is simple exercise that you
can do you can just differentiate it with
respect to this parameter t and you will actually
come up with something close to what we have
seen in the formulation of maximum entropy
model and this normalization constant is nothing
but something that that makes this probability
p lambda y given x summation over y to one
and that gives me the normalization constant
um ok
so this is my maximum entropy model so you
are you have to the the important part here
is to find out the set of features once you
have a set of features you can use this particular
equation to compute the probability of a class
y given the observation x so next in the next
lecture i will try to take up ah is a problem
that will make the idea of maximum entropy
model for that clear then we will see how
given a new sentence we use this maximum entropy
model to come up with the tag sequence and
there we will study this beam algorithm beam
search algorithm ok so see you then