so welcome back for the fourth model of this
week so in the last model we had started talking
about the maximum entropy classifiers what
is the basic principles for using this maximum
entropy classifiers ok and we saw that we
can use any hidden new set of features that
were not allowed in the earlier model like
h m m so today i will start by taking a simple
example that will give you some idea on what
how maximum entropy classifier actually works
for a simple classification problem and then
we will see how it can be used for a sequence
tagging problem that is i am given a sentence
so this is by problem for part of speech tagging
and given the sentence for each of the words
i have to find out what is the actual part
of speech tag for that
so right now what we had seen in maximum entropy
classifier it gives me a probability on the
class y given a context ok so for each individual
word for the context around that word i can
predict what is the appropriate part of speech
category but once i am given the sequence
how how this model will be actually utilized
so there it has a special name called ma m
e m m maximum entropy markov model and we
will see what is the algorithm for ah using
the classifier that we have discussed for
a sequence tagging problem
so now i starting with a simple problem on
how to use maximum entropy classifier so the
practice problems so you can try it on your
own but i will try to give you certain hints
so problem says so ah you want to use maximum
entropy model for part of speech tagging and
you are trying to estimate probability tag
given word and in this hypothetical setting
you can assume that there are only three possible
tags determiner noun and verb and the word
can belong to any member of a set v that is
your vocabulary and vocabulary contains the
words a man sleeps and some additional words
so it in this problem it does not matter how
many words are there in new vocabulary
now the constraint given is as follows so
the distribution that you will find probability
tag on word should give the following probabilities
probability of determiner given the word a
is point nine probability of noun given the
word man is point nine tag v given sleeps
is point nine d given any word other than
a man or sleeps in the vocabulary is point
six and same for that to to constraints that
are given here so remember that's what we
did in the case of maximum entropy classifier
you are given the data and from the empirical
distribution you expert certain facts and
now you want to find out a distribution that
resembles that empirical distribution ok
so now i want to find out probability i given
word such that these constraints are followed
so now how do i go about building mu maximum
entropy classifier this is the problem so
now it is said that all other probability
that are not given suppose that take some
values such that probability i given word
is one for all possible tags this is the normalization
constraint the probability for all the possible
tags for a given words should added two one
ok now there are certain questions here so
the first question says is that so you are
given this problem settings now try to define
what will be the features option maximum entropy
model given the constraints ok and the problem
says that markov features as some f one and
f two and each feature should have the same
format as we explained in the last class ok
so that is each feature your function of x
and y x is the context around the word and
why is the particular class or tag then the
next questions is for each feature f i assume
a weight of lambda i now write down the expression
of the following probabilities so what is
the probability of d given get cat in terms
of your model parameters so the parameters
are mainly lambda one to lambda six similarly
find out probability of n given laughs probability
of d given man finally the problems is what
should be the values of the parameters in
your model lambda one to lambda six such that
you have to the distribution as shown in the
question ok
so this is by problem so let me try to solve
it ah in any steps so this is the first problem
what should be the features of five model
such that they resemble this distribution
so ok so these are the actually certain facts
from the data so let me write down the first
fact probability d given a is point nine ok
so now i want to find out some features f
x y such that it can try to match this particular
constraint so x is on my data so this was
my on by word and the context and y is the
tag ok so now what am i observing in this
in this particular example i am observing
that when the word is a then the tag that
i i i give it d with the probability of point
nine so what kind of feature will will try
to model this so my feature should be effects
y so i can use a feature word that is my x
is equal to a and tag that's my y is equal
to d ok that encodes both a and d that are
that i am observing in this empirical data
ok in this we can call as your f one what
is a and tag is d so this is a binary feature
so whenever you will see word as a and tagged
d you will put it as one so to express it
you can say f one is equal to one if this
happens is equal to zero if this does not
happen ok i am not writing it in this in this
paper
so now i have to define some other features
right and the hint is that six feature will
make my task easy so that is like sufficient
hint you have six possible constraints and
you have to define six feature one for each
for each constraint so lets take the second
constraint second constraint is probability
and given man is point nine ok so for this
constraint what will my feature again so f
two would be word is equal to man and tag
is equal to n noun same way you can do for
you third third case so f three will come
out to be word is equal to v and sign word
is equal to sleeps and tag is equal to v now
what would you do for your fourth observation
what is that probability d given word is equal
to zero point six for word in vocabulary minus
a man and sleeps ok for any word other than
a minus sleeps so what would your feature
again you will have a similar feature f four
word is in so let me call this as v prime
v minus a man sleeps let me call it as v prime
ok this is my v prime so what is in v prime
and tag is equal to d ok similarly my f five
will become word in v prime and tag is n f
six word in v prime and tag is v and these
become my six features that will try to model
the distribution
now then so this is how you will select the
features given certain facts about the data
so so see here i am not doing anything from
matching this these numbers right now so that
i will try to do using my lambdas that the
feature weights set that i have to choose
so the next part of the question says is that
now give weights so suppose this is lambda
one it has a weight of lambda one lambda two
lambda three and so on so each feature f i
has a weight of lambda i now try to find out
some probabilities in terms of the model parameters
so let me take out the first question itself
that is probability of d given cat i want
to write that in terms of model parameters
so what will be this probability d given cat
so now in terms of my maximum entropy model
how do i write this par[par/particular] particular
probability it should be e to the power sigma
lambda i f i divide by a normalization constant
and z should be such that this will add up
to one for all the three tags so probably
d given cat cat plus probability and given
cat plus probability we given cat should be
one so let me take this particular y ok let
me focus only on this and i will talk about
z later so now so this is sigma lambda i f
i x y x here is cat and y is d
so now f x y so each of the six features are
binary features so they will take either one
or zero and lambda one once are just given
to me and then then um the values are not
given so i can just take lambda one lambda
two and so on so now what will be this value
ok so let me take the first feature so first
feature is here word is a and tag is d in
this case my word is cat ok so clearly this
feature is not one so for f one x five it
will be zero so lambda one times zero plus
lambda two times what is my second feature
second feature see is [sage/say] says that
word is man and tag is n again this is zero
f three word is sleeps tag is v again zero
f four so my feature f four is word is in
v prime is this word in v prime cat is not
either a man and sleep so it is in v prime
and tag is d so this is actually one so word
is in v prime and tag is d so lambda both
four times one is i will not write f four
f four is one in this case plus lambda five
now you will see in feature five and feature
six the tags are different they are n n v
so they will again be zero plus lambda six
zero this comes out to be lambda four ok
so now what is my probability it will be e
to the power lambda four divided by z now
how do you find out z now to find out z you
have to actually compute the other two probabilities
also so you have to compute probability n
given cat probability v given cat ok and then
you can make this plus this plus this is equal
to one let me quickly do that so what will
happen for when you compute probability and
given cat the first three features again use
a word a man on sleeps that is not here from
fourth features they are using the words in
v prime so the word cat and n v prime so the
features can be one from f four f five f six
but now i have to see the tag for f four the
tag was d for f five the tag was n and for
f six the tag was v ok this was n and this
was v so for n given cat f five will be one
and v given get f six will be one so can i
write probability and given cat this will
be e to the power lambda five given z and
this will be e to the power lambda six divided
by z ok now you can compute what is p d given
cat because this c will add up to one so put
in the constraint e to the power lambda four
plus e to the power lambda five plus e to
the power lambda six divided by z is equal
to one so that gives you z is equal to e to
the power lambda four plus e to the power
lambda five plus e to the power lambda six
so this we can write as e to the power lambda
four divided by lambda four plus e to the
lambda five plus e to the power lambda six
that is your probability of d given cat in
terms of your model parameters
now in a very similar manner i will suggest
that you try out the other two cases what
is the probability of n given laughs and what
is the probability of d given laugh so again
we have not use of the of the probabilities
point nine and etcetera that were given in
the in the in the constraint of the of discussion
so that i have to use in the last point what
values with the parameters in your model take
to give the distribution as described above
so that is what values a should takes us that
probability d given a is point nine so ok
need to you may leave your final answer in
terms of equations so let me try to take only
the first try to satisfy only the first constraint
what should be the constraint on my lambda
such that the first constraint of probability
d given h point nine satisfied ok and the
idea is very very easy you will suggest night
like we found out probability d given cat
we will now try to find out probability d
given a ok and that will be e to the power
lambda one yes because first feature is one
for this case divided by z ok now what is
z so for finding out z i have to find out
probability v given a n probability n given
a now brought this probability v given a ok
so again i will write one divide by z into
something e to the power lambda one times
f one and so on now the word a is given only
in the first feature yes first feature says
the word is a and tag is d so the word is
a is given it is not given in feature two
feature three
now what about the other features f four f
five f six they all talk about words in v
prime whether word is not there so the any
of the feature cannot be one four for this
case this case so all of them will be zero
so it will be simply it small zero ok all
the features are zero same happens with n
given a ok so they are one by z one by z and
this tells me that probability d given a should
be e to the power lambda one divided by e
to the power lambda one plus two and there
should be point nine to satisfy the constraint
and that you give me the value of lambda one
similarly you will do for all the six cases
and write down the questions ok so hope that
gives you a good idea on how do we actually
start building a maximum entropy classifier
in the data and how do we compute the probabilities
now i will i will take a very specific case
so that is by the paper written in nineteen
ninety six by ratnaparakhi on using maximum
entropy model for part of speech tagging so
what i will show is that what kind of features
they use for part of speech tagging ok so
now this model is there now what is important
to understand is that given a problem what
sort of features i should use to get a good
performance ok model will work well if few
features the features that you have chosen
you have chosen make sense for this particular
problem so for part of speech tagging problem
what are the kind of features that he had
used now given a new problem again you have
to go back and find out what should be the
interesting features you know now the format
of features how you should define your features
but what are important features will always
depend on the particular problem that you
are solving so as we had said so in in the
maximum entropy model you choose a context
around the world from where you can choose
your features so in this case what is the
context they have chosen they have chosen
the current word the next two words the previous
to words and the tags given to the previous
to words ok and that is interesting how do
you use this kind of features in the time
in the time at the time of decoding when given
a sequence you are trying to find out the
tags because you do not know what is the best
tag for the previous word ok so we will look
at this ah this problem when we talk about
the such algorithm the beam such algorithm
that how do we make use of previous tag and
previous previous tag there are to be assigned
that are not yet assigned fully ok but here
use always features in in all this ah context
for defining his features
now what are the form of features so yes just
to give you another example features will
depend on the history or the context and the
current tag so it can it is one if the current
word has a suffix of i n g and the tag is
v b g that is one kind of feature the suffix
of the current word and the tag so what are
the other other features ok so now so what
is one interesting thing here we divided it
features into three parts some features are
only for those words that are not rare that
a very very common second sort of features
are those words that are rare why do why does
it define separate features for the words
that are rare because these words may not
be seen again data but i might see some other
real words so can i use some some of the properties
of these words instead of using the word directly
ok so further words that are not rare they
occur many times uses a word directly w i
is equal to x and its current tag this is
the form of feature but the if the word is
rare he does not use the word directly he
says x is a prefix of w i length of x is less
than equal to four so he uses all the prefixes
of the of the word is starting from one two
three and four same for suffix now how will
that be helpful using the suffix so for example
i have e d but overall the word is rare so
can i use the fact that the word and sanity
ok that's why we are using the suffix here
similarly for prefix ok i can have something
like i n for making the up opposites for an
adjectives and so on ok so this can be captured
by using this kind of features whether the
word contains a number or in uppercase character
or in hyphen ok this for rare words
now he just some other features for all the
words so what are the features the previous
tag is x and the current tag is t this is
very very generic feature right the previous
two tags are x and y current tag is t previous
word is x and current tag is t previous to
previous word is x current tag is t then similarly
for the next for the next next words ok so
now let us see what will be the form these
features will take so this is the generic
form of the features now let us take a simple
context and see what are the forms these features
are going to take so this is one context ok
i have a sentence the stories about well heeled
communities and developers and the tags are
d t n n all the the part of speech tags are
given to me so this is for my label data
now what are the values these features will
take so firstly i will differentiate between
the rare words and not so rare words ok so
what can be the rare words here for example
the word well heeled here is a rare word ok
and other words like stories committees developers
are not rare so for the words that are not
rare what feature am i using the current word
and the tag so my feature could be the word
is a stories and tag is n m s so for the word
well heeled i will use the suffix and prefix
so w is a prefix of the word and tag is j
j w is a prefix and tag is j j similarly e
d is a suffix and tag is j j so ok and then
there will be some features for all the words
like for about and well heeled what would
be the feature the previous tag is i a i n
and the current tag is j j the previous two
tags are nns and i n and the current is j
j the previous words or the word stories and
well heeled about and well heeled so on so
you can use all these features so here are
all these features right
so this is prefix and suffix for the real
word well heeled and there are other things
like w i contains hyphen that is in the case
of well heeled and tag is j j ok so now thats
how you will write down all your features
from your data and you will learn your parameters
lambdas and all and at run time you will ah
use again these features in the parameter
to finding the probability of the tags ok
so hope this gives you some idea and how can
you choose your features for a given task
now let me go to the search algorithm for
for this maximum model so so this we had discussed
earlier also but we did not discuss in full
details some given a sentence w one two w
n these are the words and i want to find out
the probability of tag sequence t i t one
to t n ok
and we said that we can write it in this form
multiplication of probability t i given x
i x i is the context for each individual word
now the the problem here is so and you can
use some tag dictionary that says for each
individual word what are the possible tags
similar to what we did in the case of viterbi
decoding for h m m now what is one particular
problem in this case so as such it looks as
if you can do it independently for each each
word right for the first word i can find out
what is the best tag multiplied with best
tag for the second word and so on now what
is one problem with this approach let me just
give you one simple example ok so this is
a hypothetical example let us say that we
have word one word two word three ok and word
two can take two tags i n and j j and word
three can take lets to keep it simple that
it can take it take like v b z and maybe something
else like v b g ok maybe they may not be possible
but just a hypothetical case
now suppose by using this algorithm or doing
it independently we found out that for w two
i n give some probability and j j gives some
probability now in w three what might what
could happen some of the features might depend
on the previous assigned tag so how v b z
you might want to use what is the tag assigned
in the previous word ok so that means choosing
the probabilities the best probability at
this point may not be ah may not be the best
so choosing the tag at this point may not
be the best because at at the next step you
are using the tags and the probabilities can
change this can happen that i n in giving
the better probability at this point but when
combined with v b z j j gets a better probability
this can happen ok that means i can find out
the probabilities but i have to use the probabilities
and the tags in the next step also ok so this
is not fully independent i cannot just choose
i n and forget about it i have to remember
what is the probability next time i will choose
i n v b g j j v b z and try to compute the
probability for v b z multiplied by the previous
probabilities and that's and how we do that
I will show you in the beam search algorithm
so what is the bean search algorithm so so
your test sentences containing words like
w one two w n ok and later say that for the
i th word as i denotes the z highest probability
tag ok this is top tag sequence up to the
word w i now how does the algorithm work so
you have the words w one to w n forward w
one you have s one one s one two up to s one
n top n highest probability tags ok so will
come to the probabilities and this is easy
again you will use the features here which
feature is one which feature is zero then
you will do the normalization you will compute
all these probabilities for the each of these
tags now the the important thing is how do
you go to w two ok so one thing to to understand
is that you can probably not keep all the
possible tag sequences because assume that
each word can take on an average k tags so
if you have n words the tag would be of the
order of n to the power sorry k to the power
n yes k to the power so
so this will be exponential in the length
of the sentence so you cannot keep all the
tag sequence so you might have to make the
choice of the best sequence is available at
this point that's what we do in bean search
so at each point i will select what is the
top set up capital n sequences at this point
and how do we how do we select that so that
is the next part of the algorithm so initialize
i is equal to two ok so now you have to second
word generate tags for w i given s i minus
one j as previous tag context and append each
tag to s i minus j to make a new sequence
and then continue for all the tags now what
does that me [me/mean] initialize i is equal
to two that is your second word now generic
tags for w i s given s i minus j as the previous
tag context what is i minus j i minus one
is s one n j so let me take this as the previous
context and suppose this has again some tags
like ah i will just write some tags t one
t two t three so s one one and t one becomes
the first sequence s one one and t two becomes
the second sequence and s one one t three
becomes the third sequence similarly s one
two t one becomes forth sequence and so on
ok so is so in this case there will be three
times n sequences so this you can take any
general case this may not be one tag this
will be a sequence up to this point so we
all the first sequence at this point
now for each of the sequence you know what
are the previous tags that have been assigned
yes so i know what are tags assigned at this
point so i can use all the features so if
a feature says t i is equal to something and
t i minus one is equal to something else so
i can check if t i matches this and the previous
tag matches this then only it will do one
other wise zero because i'm choosing the context
i can compute always feature i remembered
it features i can compute the probability
for all the sequences and now what i will
do i will select at this point what are the
s i one to s i n whatever top end sequences
at this point ok and again i will go to the
third word again its tags combine with all
the sequences and choose top end from here
so what will happen u [u/use] use your space
will not do exponentially you will always
have have top end sequence is at any given
point so finally when you go to the the final
word you will get the top end probabilities
or all the probabilities and you will select
the best sequence and now because the sixth
is sequence contains the tag from by starting
you will find out the part of speech tag just
from the choosing the best sequence at the
last word and that is your algorithm so find
n highest probability sequences by above loop
set this accordingly and repeat if i less
than equal to n and return to highest probability
sequences x n one for the last word and this
is your maximum entropy this we markov model
ok instead of maximum entropy model is generate
classifier that can do for each word individually
but when you are trying to applied for a sequence
labeling problem for a sequel you use this
maximum entropy markov model
ok so this was maximum entropy markov model
for you now in the in the next lecture i will
take one simple example of this search and
i will quickly cover the the model of conditional
in the fields that is one one of the state
of the arts in sequence labeling task and
what we will sure there is some problem with
the maximum trophy model that condition of
fields try to handle ok so thank you i will
see you in the next class