so welcome back for the final lecture of this
week so ah we are talking about the problem
of part of speech tagging and the methods
that we are discussing our generic methods
for any sequence labeling task so input is
a sequence like here sequence of the words
and output is again a sequence were for each
word i going to predict what is a corresponding
part of speech tags so we talked about hidden
markov models and also maxent model so in
general in maxent model we talked about how
do you we use that simple classifier for a
sequence labeling task so we will call that
the maximum entropy markov model ok and the
formation was very easy that is if predict
the tag for each word and then multiply the
probabilities for the whole sequence there
was one ah problem though that because we
we need the sequence of the we need the tag
of the previous word in certain features to
assign the tag at this this particular word
we will need to use beam search algorithm
and we also discuss what is the beam search
algorithm
so what i will do in this lecture i will take
a take an example there we we will see how
to use beam search algorithm and then i briefly
discuss what a condition random fields and
how are the different from maximum entropy
models so condition random fields again is
a very vast topic we will not cover fully
we will only give you the hint that once you
know maxcent or m e m a models what are condition
random fields how are they different from
those so starting with a practice question
so here so so we are having the same sentence
the light book and you are given that ah for
all the three words the light and book the
top put x are determine a noun verb adjective
and verb noun ok
now you want to use your m e m a model so
for the given tag or given word w i the you
use particular context what is a context here
the previous word next word and the tag given
to the previous word this is the context so
that means all your features we will be defined
over this context so here is a example we
have showing some sample like you have given
a different features and now we have to use
the beam search algorithm to find out what
will be the appropriate tag sequence for the
sentence
so ah so what are the features giving so features
are simple like the previous tag the tag given
to the previous word is determiner and current
tag is adjective previous tag is noun current
tag is verb previous tag is adjective current
tag is noun previous word is the current tag
is adjective so on ok now then you also have
feature like the next word is light current
tag is determiner previous word is null and
current tag is noun what it means is that
this the ith word will be starting a sentence
thats why the previous word will be null so
now you are given this features and for simplicity
you are should given that each feature has
a uniform weight of one now your task is to
use beam search algorithm with the beam size
of two what do you mean by a beam size of
two at any given point you will keep only
the top two highest ah probability tag sequence
and everything else you will forget so at
any point you will know what are the top two
tag sequences till this point and overall
you have to find the highest probability tag
sequence for the sentence that is the light
book
so let we see how do we solve this so we are
having three ah words in the sentence the
light and book ok the word the has two text
two possible text it can be either a determiner
or a noun the word light can be a verb or
an adjective and the word book can be a verb
or a noun ok so now how do we start you to
find out probability tag i given w i and so
del y let me write the context x i or h i
give different notations for that so here
context is w i minus one w i w i plus one
and t is tag ok and what is the formulation
of this tag i given ah the current word ah
current here it will be
exponent summation lambda i f i ok and feature
we know is a function of input and the tag
divide by z and z is nothing but a normalization
constant so that all the text probability
let of two one so let us try to do that
when the tag is determiner word is the ok
so what so let we just write down exponent
of summation lambda i f i and lambda i is
lambda h is one here in this problem so it
will be simply exponent summation over f i
so what features are one and what features
are zero so for this word so everywhere where
we need the previous tag or the previous word
should be zero because this is the start of
the sentence so i do not have any previous
word tag or any previous word so all these
features value will become zero
now what is the feature that will become one
what should be this one this needs the next
word i is light and the current tag is determiner
is that ah will that you one so if you see
here current tag is determiner on the next
word is light so it could be one that is for
feature f i so so it is one so i will say
it is exponent or let we write e to the power
one this lambda is one divided by z let we
find out that later let if find out the the
value for noun noun so again similar to this
one all of features from f one to f six will
become zero because you do not know what is
a previous word or previous tag this feature
could have become one but the current tag
is not determiner but noun so this will also
be zero this feature previous word is null
yes that is true is a start of the sentence
and the current tag is noun this will also
become one ok so this the only features that
become the one for noun
so this is e to the power one and what is
the normalization this plus this ok so two
times e to the power divided by two times
e to the power one so both will become point
five ok so fine so have this point all the
two tags have we [bo/both] both the tags has
probability point five and any of because
i am using a beam size of two i will have
to keep both these tags so now i keeping both
this tags with probability point five point
five now let us go to the next word light
now again so i have to use probability of
verb given this history now the this stage
previous word current word next word and the
previous tag so now when i going about talking
about verb if i have to compute this features
i need to know what are the what is the previous
tag ok here it can be a either determiner
or noun so that's why i need talk in terms
of the sequences
so here i have one sequence determiner noun
determiner verb and second sequence with noun
verb so we have to take both the sequences
separately in compute the probability similarly
i will have to do the same for adjective ok
so let us try do that for one sequence so
noun verb sequence ok so what will be the
probability of ah tag i given the word so
this we can write here so let me write only
this summation lambda i f i part so this will
be
summation lambda i f i so let us go to the
features here so noun verb so let us go to
the features first features previous tag is
determiner no previous tag is noun here this
is zero previous tag is noun yes and the current
tag is verb this is ok this could be one so
f two is one f three zero because previous
tag is not a adjective f four previous tag
is the no yes previous word is the current
tag is adjective no it's verb then this will
be also not correct because the current tag
is not a adjective but verb previous word
is light noun next word is light noun previous
word is null noun so only f two is one
so this will be for this sequence it will
be a to the power one divided by the normalization
that now what will this normalization depend
on this will depend on from all everywhere
where this context is taken what are the ah
probabilities so i have to compute the probability
for this one also to find out this z ok so
i know this probability i know this function
this function and i will normalize them to
at two one so what will be for the function
for noun and adjective that is try that from
the features again previous tag is adject
determiner gone previous tag is noun but current
tag is verb noun previous tag is adjective
noun previous word is the yes and tag is which
adjective yes so this will become one f four
will become become one previous word is the
yes next word is book yes current tag is adjective
this will also become one all fill will be
zero so now this will become e to the power
two divide by z and z i can write as e plus
e square same here e plus e square ok
so now i know the probability of getting verb
at this position given the previous tag is
noun and adjective at this position given
the previous tag is noun but what is the probability
of this whole sequence it will be multiplied
by the probability of getting noun that is
half similarly here half ok so this is the
probability of selecting this sequence similarly
i will compute the probability of selecting
this and this normalized them multiplied by
point five so now i will get the probability
for four sequences so that is noun verb determiner
verb determiner adjective and noun adjective
i have the probability of sequence of this
system and then i will select only top two
from there ok so suppose the top two could
be say noun verb and determiner adjective
so what will happen now for the next step
i will consider only say determiner adjective
and noun verb and other know also their probabilities
then i will take each individual as a history
and see ok determiner adjective then noun
determiner adjective then verb normalizer
probability see will noun verb noun noun verb
verb normalizer probability accordingly multiply
this so again you will have four sequences
here you will have probability for all four
sequences and take the one that is having
the highest probability and that will be your
final ah tag sequence in this example ok
so i hope the idea is clear i am not solving
this fully but i am i will encourage you that
you you do it on your own and see that you
can you can find out what is the appropriate
sequence using the m m a model so this was
how do you use beam search algorithm for m
m a model now i will just talk briefly with
what is the problem with this ah what is the
single problem with this ah maximum entropy
model then so let we have to think about ah
condition random fields
so in maximum entropy model we do a per state
normalization that is all the mass that arrives
at a state must be distributed among the possible
successor states and this is giving rise to
a label bias problem ok so let's see what
is the intuition so what do i mean by this
so let we ah take the same example so first
let me take the same example to explain what
do i mean by normalization at each state so
take this one ok so you are computing noun
verb and noun adjective ok and you had the
features like e square and e one but you where
normalizing them by so even normalizing then
such that these two add up to one same thing
will you will do with determiner you will
make sure that these two add up to one so
your normalizing at each state ok
so why will the that we a problem so let we
just taken hypothetical example suppose in
your ah maximum entropy model you were having
a tag t one and tag t two at any given point
so next point so this one t one you can go
to go two different tags t one prime and t
one double prime and from t two again you
can go to t two prime t two double prime then
may be same they may not be same now how do
you compute this probability it will be e
to the power summation lambda i f i divide
by z z is something but the addition of these
two same here now this is what is the importance
for how how many features you were having
and so on
suppose for a particular ah choice of these
tags it happens that in one of the branch
they are having this value has zero point
zero zero two ok and this value has zero point
ah zero zero zero one ok or let us say ah
even much smaller value and this branch is
having value of zero point zero three zero
point zero four so so what will happen now
this not normalized values ok so it tells
that this summation lambda f i is getting
a higher score in these two cases and lower
score in these two cases but because you are
doing for it should normalization you will
divided by zero point zero zero two plus zero
point zero zero zero one and that will be
closed to say very closed to one zero point
nine eight or something ok on the other hand
this will be closed to point four five or
point five five so what is happening here
even though this probability was low when
i normalized this became very ah this became
very high that is one particular problem on
the other hand suppose that from t one there
was no possibility of going to t one double
prime so there was only one tag possible so
you will in independent of the context it
will always get a probability of one because
you have to normalize at each state that is
if from t one i can only go to one tag t one
prime and everything else has a probability
of zero because if normalization this will
become one so we multiply this probability
t one independent of the context and this
is called as the label bias problem and this
comes because you are normalizing at each
step that is one problem with the ah maximum
entropy markov models
so so let us see how we avoid this problem
in condition random fields so i hope this
problem is clear that you are doing normalization
at easy step at easy state and that is giving
some bias towards ah those states that are
having few transitions then the having more
number of transitions ok so ok so let me just
telling one thing so suppose i have two different
tags from t one you have two possible transitions
from t two you have five possible transitions
what will happen these will get a but there
will be a bias towards choosing this state
because this will be normalized and one of
this will gave a get a higher value and this
may not happen here because there are five
possible transitions so this get's a bias
and that is not ah what is idle so how do
we avoid this problem and conditional random
fields
so conditional random fields are under acted
graphical models and while there are many
variations of conditional random fields so
there is a generic structure we will look
at the linear generic structure
so here is shows we has here we are seen the
linear generic structure of conditional random
fields so again like in the previous case
you are having a sequence x one two x n and
these are the tags y one to y n assign to
these tag
now how they are so in what way they are very
similar to maximum entropy model they are
similar in the sense that we they use the
same for the feature functions so what you
are seeing here for the ith point the feature
function so suppose i is equal to three would
be a function over the previous tag y two
current tag y three the whole the input you
can take any any number of words before and
after x three and this is ith index ok so
feature functions are again function of the
input current tag and previous tag this is
in the linear generic structure
so conditional random fields are like ah ah
factor graphs so what happens the probability
of each ah node will depending on only its
its neighbor ok so and you can use the same
sort of features so like ah so this is what
we had discuss in maximum entropy model also
so i have a feature that is one if previous
tag is i n current tag is n n p and the current
word is september and zero otherwise so we
will see there are very similar sort functions
that we are using in maxent so so they are
same in as maxent in in that sense but how
they are different so a difference comes in
how the normalization is done in maxent model
or maximum entropy markov model we are doing
normalization for each state ok so that is
at easy state if i have multiple transitions
i will make sure that the probability for
them at adds up two one this does not happen
in conditional random fields so we will compute
ah the features ah expectations of feature
values for each possible transition whole
sequence and then i will do normalization
so that we can see from the probability function
here
so y is the whole y is a whole sequence y
one to y n given a current the current input
sequence x one to x n and lambda is the the
feature ah we its that you will learn and
this is one by z x say see a single nomination
parameter exponent summation over i is equal
to one two one summation j lambda j f j ok
so ah let us try to understand quickly what
this ah function means so here having one
up on z x exponent summation i is equal to
one to n summation over j lambda j f j and
say f j is a jth feature and this is probability
y given x lambda lambda are the feature x
let us try to understand this what do you
mean by y y is a sequence y one to y n and
x is the input sequence and there are many
such sequences possible so this is a probability
for a given sequence and this z is a normalization
that is done over all so that is a summation
over all the sequences so we can write it
as
so so this will be summation over all the
sequences i will i have this value for only
sequence y current sequence y i will add it
over all the sequence that will give me z
so sum mission over all y possible y e x p
and whatever was in set so now how do we get
this equation so remember this equation summation
j lambda j f j that is for a particular tag
ah y is a given at the ah sorry a particular
tag given at the ith position ok so i have
exponent summation j lambda j f j that is
probability of a tag y i given x i x i can
be all history at the given point divided
by z was there but forget about the now here
we are computing probability for the whole
sequence y i i is equal to one to n so so
this will be multiplication so multiply i
is equal to one to n so multiply i is equal
to one to n now if i multiplying multiple
exponent this is like so so for example e
to the power x times e to the power y becomes
e to the power x plus y so that is multiplication
of all the exponent is nothing but like summation
of what is inside exponent summation i is
equal to one to n summation j lambda j f j
ok and that is the function a and z x is normalization
over all such ah transitions all such sorry
all such ah sequences
so you are not doing normalization here so
what happens in maxent you are doing normalization
here so for for a given i you make sure that
everything adds up to one and that is not
being done here you are you are not making
sure that at each i all the tags will the
probability for the text will add up to one
now you are doing a normalization only in
the end i know the probability or something
that is proportion to probability for each
tag sequence and then i will normalize everything
by this z x and that's why this this avoids
the label bias problem so this is the function
that is using conditional random fields so
what we can see that so ah conditional random
fields have the advantage of maximum entropy
markov model they use a same sort of features
the kind of model is very very similar to
maximum entropy markov model but they avoid
the label bias problem
so c r fs are globally normalized whereas
m m ms are locally normalized so that we had
discussed and they are very widely used and
applied for many many sequence labeling task
and so so they were very closed to the state
of the art models for many of these sequence
labeling task so so what whatever sequence
labeling task that comes your mind so starting
from part of speech tagging to name and recognition
so there you can apply a conditional random
field model and lot of libraries are also
[avai/available] available so one particular
appeal that is very popular and then there
are c r a plus plus and and many other libraries
that you can use what is important is that
you understand what is the sort of features
that that you need to use ok and then the
model will will help you to train you are
own c r f so this ends our discussion on ah
part of speech tagging we did discuss a lot
about what will be the models for sequence
tagging so now so in the from the next week
we will start discussion on ah on syntax that
how do we find out what are the word what
are the word arrangement in a sentence and
how do we group them in various sort of ah
phrases so so i will see you next week
thank you