so welcome to the fifth week of this course
so we have so in this week we are going we
will be moving up the hierarchy of ah solving
this language processing tasks ok so we had
started with discussing about how do we handle
individual words how do we use how do we make
use of the word or information using language
models and then how do we assign various grammatical
categories a part of speech categories to
the words ok that is why what we are doing
till now
now we will go to next level where we will
try to see can we arrange these words in certain
groups ok so this is this is what we study
in this topic of syntax so how are the words
being arranged together ok and what can be
how we can automatically find out this arrangement
given a new sentence this will be the topic
of parsing that we will discuss in this week
ok
so what is syntax so in general syntax refers
to the way the words are arranged together
ok and also you will see what is the relationship
between various words and the word groups
that is what we will talk about in syntax
so when we were talking about language models
we had discussed what is the importance of
modeling word order so which words occur after
what are the words how we can make use of
that in assigning probability for a sentence
all finding out the next word in completion
task or in spelling correction task ok similarly
when we were talking about part of speech
task we saw what are the grammatical categories
part of speech categories so this defines
in one sort of equivalence class for words
that is all these words behave like they are
verbs behave in some some equivalent manner
ok similarly all these words are nouns they
behaving in some equivalent manner similarly
all these are adjectives so you are define
some equivalent classes
now in syntax we will find out some more complex
notions like word is constituency what are
different grammatical relations among the
words what what groups or what words are group
together in constituency ok and subcategorization
etcetera also included in this in this topic
ok and yeah just to make you understand what
is this notion of syntax so you can relate
to that if you see this particular meme so
i hope you remember this particular character
from a statics this syntax the only part of
the language it is not but important is it
is right so you can see the way words are
arranged normally in the way we speak and
how they arranged in this particular sentence
ok that was the special characteristics of
this character ok
so now so what are we are going to study in
syntax so let me give you a simple example
so i have the sentence the man read this book
ok so by syntax we are trying we are trying
to find out what are the various groups of
word ok that are coming together for example
in part of speech text we found out that the
word the as part of speech of determiner man
as the part of speech of noun read as verb
and so on ok now we are going one level up
so now we are saying this is determiner this
is noun this is kind of nominal but they both
together make a phrase noun phrase so i am
saying the man is a noun phrase similarly
this book is also a noun phrase so the there
are two noun phrases here the man and this
book but when the verb read or any verb comes
before the noun phrase it makes a verb phrase
ok so all these three words act as a single
unit of a verb phrase ok there is a no such
unit for man and read right there is a unit
for read this book and the man and then i
go up saying that a noun phrase and verb phrase
are making the sentence and this gives me
complete hierarchy structure of how the words
arranged in the sentence the sentence is nothing
but a noun phrase and the verb phrase this
noun phrase contains a determiner and noun
verb phrase contains a verb and noun phrase
which contains and so on so this is the complete
hierarchy of the sentence that i come to know
by this syntax tree and that is the what is
the topic of this week how do we come up with
such syntax tree for a for some sentences
what is the particular formulation that we
will use ok
let me start by defining some basic notions
like what is constituency so in the last example
we saw that a group of words right they act
they acting as some single unit and you can
call them as phrases clauses etcetera so in
part of speech we could have done this substitution
test so i have this sentence the there is
a fill in the blank one in the room ok and
i can i can filling any adjective the green
one the fat one and intelligent one sad one
all that can be filled in so i can fill in
any word that belongs to that particular part
of speech category now here it will be a particular
constituent it will be a particular group
of words that can behave similarly ok like
here so all these four things kermit the frog
they december twenty sixth the reason he running
for president all these are noun phrases ok
and they can occur in a given context so now
for substitution test you can substitute any
of this these four noun phrases and yeah we
will see an example where all these can come
in the same in a very very similar context
so how do we name these constituent phrases
so last slide i was showing some noun phrases
so why do we call them noun phrases or something
else so usually the names are given based
on the words that are heading these constituent
what is the head and usually speaking you
can find the head by the word that can substituted
for the whole thing ok let me take the first
example the man from amherst ok this is the
this is the phrase they are four words now
which of the four word do you think can substitute
the whole thing now that can that can be used
in the grammatical ah function of the of the
complete unit and that will be man where the
man from amherst the word man can be used
to denote the grammatical function of the
whole unit so the head here is a noun man
so this will be called a noun phrase ok because
the head man is a noun
similarly extremely clever the head here is
clever this is the adjective so this is called
in adjective phrase down the river here head
is down preposition so this will called in
prepositional phrase killed the rabbit the
head is killed the word killed which is a
verb so this is called verb phrase so like
that we are we defined what are the constituent
by taking what is the head of that phrase
now in general words can also act as phrases
so a phrase need not have always multiple
heads a single word can also be a phrase so
let us take the simple example joe grew potatoes
so joe itself it is a noun phrase ok potato
also a noun phrase they are nouns but also
a noun phrases in this case now compare the
sentence with the man from amherst grew beautiful
russet potatoes so what do you seeing so instead
of joe i have substituted the man from amhrest
a complete a four word unit that is again
a noun phrase and beautiful russet potatoes
instead of potatoes they are still noun phrases
ok so what happen in the sentence joe appears
in a place where you could a probably put
a larger noun phrase now this gives a very
nice idea about the structure of the sentence
ok in this sentence i am having a noun phrase
and a verb phrase verb phrase contains a verb
and noun phrase and noun phrase you can you
can either put a single word like joe or you
can put multiple words like the man from amhrest
similarly in that noun phrase you can put
potatoes or it become noun phrase like beautiful
russet potatoes so this gives me lots of idea
about how words are grouped in arrange together
now there is some evidence that questions
actually exist in language yes they are two
different evidences one is that this phrase
is appear in very very similar environment
so far i have talk about the four phrases
that noun phrases that discussed in one of
the various phrases like let we see this examples
kermit the frog comes on stage note it they
come to massachusetts every summer december
twenty sixth comes after christmas the reason
he is running for president comes out only
now so all these four nouns phrases are coming
in a very similar context of the word say
comes yes but i cannot take any individual
word from here and put that in the context
so i cannot take the word the and say the
comes our out or i cannot say is comes out
and i cannot say for comes out in this sentence
ok i can only say the reason he is running
for president comes out only now ok not an
individual word so this whole thing behaves
as a single unit and they occur in similar
context all the noun phrase occurring in similar
context this is got evidence to constituency
what is the other evidence so the evidence
is that this whole phrase is together can
locate many locations in the same center ok
so for example if i take on december twenty
six that is the prepositional phrase and i
can put it in many different phrases in the
sentence on december twenty six i would like
to fly to florida i would like to fly on december
twenty six to florida or i would like to fly
to florida on december twenty six all three
are valid sentences where this complete phrase
on december twenty six has we put in multiple
location but you cannot break this into two
parts and put it in phrases ok so you cannot
say on december i would like to fly twenty
sixth to florida or on i would like to fly
december twenty sixth to florida you cannot
say that so this will as a single group it
cannot be split of part ok so these are some
evidence that constituency actually exists
in the language
now what is the formal tool by which we can
model this constituency that is how words
are arranged together which words come together
which was do not come together ok and what
groups make a sentence and what groups make
a verb phrase what group make a noun phrase
how can i model all that what is the formulation
ok and if you have take any course on formal
language in automated theory all theory computation
you might already know that the formulate
that we can use that in context free grammar
ok this is the most common way of modeling
constituency so in one of the earlier lectures
we talked about the ah languages by using
deterministic finite automata of finite automata
ok so this is context for context free languages
by using by the context free grammar
now so i will not going in very very basics
i will just talk briefly how do we use context
free grammar i will also defined the notions
for the context free grammar so in the case
of context free grammar what you will have
you will have some sort of production rules
that is what we mostly interested in so what
they do the production rules will try to express
what are the way in which various symbols
of the language of group together ok and that
is our main interest in using context free
grammar which symbols are being group together
that i can use that i can find out using or
i can express using the production rules in
context free grammars
so let us see one simple example so i want
to model this language that is noun phrase
can be composed to either a proper noun or
a determiner followed by a nominal where a
nominal can be more than one nouns that is
something i want to express about language
so how do i use the context free grammar so
i will say noun phrases proper noun or determiner
nominal ok the nominal is noun or many nouns
so how i write in context free grammar i will
say noun phrase is proper noun or determiner
nominal and what is a nominal it is one noun
or more than one noun so noun or noun by a
nominal ok this is the regression here so
i can allow as many numbers of nouns as i
want by using this ok and that is my ah context
free grammar for for denoting the symbol ok
that is the idea i can express all these facts
about language how words are groups together
which groups come together by using this production
rules
so once we know that what is the ah formulation
of context free grammar very briefly said
so in context free grammar when we study when
we talk about a quadruple ok so therefore
four four important variable set of variables
so firstly i have set of terminals we have
the leaf notes in my tree whenever we see
so they will always come at the end and whenever
i get a terminal i cannot derive anything
from there so i have set of terminals so we
will see what in the case of language what
do they mean then we have set of non terminals
that help me to do the derivations ok these
are the variable from which you can further
derive in more
now so what is different in the case of n
l p what is some distinguish will make in
the set of non terminals we will also distinguish
the set p that are pre terminals ok so pre
terminals are those non terminals that will
always derive terminals so they will always
give me leaf nodes ok and with the example
that will be clear what are what are they
in the case of language
then i have start symbol from which i am starting
my derivation ok so if i have to model the
sentence i should be starting with s that
is the sentence and then i have the rules
and they always of form x going to gamma ok
and x has to be a non terminal a single non
terminal and gamma can be any sequence of
terminals and non terminals and that is the
constraint that we see in case of context
free grammar ok so this is the quadruple and
we also seeing a pre terminal that is that
is the set of non terminals in the language
what are terminals and pre terminals terminals
in the language will mainly with the final
words that i will see in the lexicon and pre
terminals will be part of speech categories
from the pre because from the pre terminals
you can derive only terminals ok
so let us see one example and then we can
point out what are terminals pre terminals
and non terminals so this is what we are modeling
earlier ok what is the noun phrase determiner
for the nominal or a proper noun and where
a nominal is a noun or a set of nouns which
i model using a noun followed by a nominal
now are you see some terminals here so there
are no words so there is no terminals so i
cannot use that to derive a phrase or a sentence
it can only give me a set of grammatical categories
so i have to include some facts on the lexicon
to make it a complete grammar ok
so so for example i can includes some determiners
some nouns and some proper nouns so here i
am including a and the has to determiners
and flight as a noun now here can you identify
what are the terminal non terminals and pre
terminals so terminals are the words in my
lexicon so a the and flight are my terminals
pre terminals are the grammatical categories
or parse category that will always give me
terminals can you see that determiner noun
are only giving me terminals so these are
my pre terminals and apart from that all the
variables like n p nominal they are my non
terminals so proper noun no example is given
but proper noun is also a pre terminal ok
it is part of speech category it will give
you some words to the lexicon so these are
my terminals non terminals and pre terminals
so now once you have the c f g you can use
that to generate various phrases or sentences
in language so for example i here this is
the c f g for non phrases so can i can i generate
a flight the phrase a flight is in this context
free grammar ok so i will have to start with
n p and i have to generate a flight so what
is the first derivation i will to do from
n p i will take this rule determiner followed
by a nominal yes now determiner will give
me a now from nominal i cannot go to flight
directly so for nominal i will have to first
get a noun and from noun i will get a i get
the word flight so n p gives me determine
nominal nominal gives me noun determiner gives
me a a a noun and a flight thats how it generate
a sequence of words using this grammar and
now you can do it for any sentence you can
define a grammar for a sentence and generate
a sentences from that ok
so what we are seeing here so there is a context
free grammar is generate a series of strings
ok and this sequence of rule expansions so
the sequence that ah that you are using starting
from n p going to determiner nominal then
determiner noun then a noun then a flight
this is called the derivation of the string
using this grammar and we use it is tree structure
to represent this derivation ok remember one
of the very first tree that we had shown as
a motivation so we will try to come up with
such trees using this derivations and when
we will be call the past tense ok
now what is the notion of grammaticality using
context free grammars the idea is that you
defined one grammar for your language ok you
have to assume that this is the this is the
only grammar so any tool that is not expressed
in the in the grammar is not allowed in the
language so now when you are given a new sentence
if you can see that there is a way to generate
this sentence using my grammar the sentence
is grammatical as per my grammar if the sentence
cannot be generated in the grammar this is
not grammatical this is a simple notion or
using this grammar whatever sentence i can
generate is grammatical and whatever i cannot
is not grammatical so it depends on the grammar
that you have designed the context free grammar
that you have designed so yes so whatever
can be derived are grammatical and others
are ungrammatical
now c f gs are interesting because they can
also model some very interesting phenomena
in in language syntax like recursion ok so
in language you make lot of big big sentences
by ah doing recursion so for example a preposition
phrase can be written as a preposition followed
by a noun phrase ok and noun phrase can be
written as a noun phrase followed by a preposition
phrase so you see there is a recursion here
yes so i can encode the noun phrase noun and
prepositional phrase is here preposition phase
can again encode a noun phrase which can encode
a proportion phrase so this is the recursion
is very very common in language ok
so let's see one example so the set example
is the mailman ate his and this is the complete
noun phrase is starting from lunch till the
end of the sentence lunch and noun phrase
is a noun preposition phrase with and this
is not shown here but this is again starts
a noun phrase preposition phrase is a preposition
followed by a noun phrase with his friend
from the cleaning staff and all this is a
noun phrase and what is this noun phrase noun
ok his friend followed by a preposition phrase
and so on the recursion is very nicely captured
by using context free grammar ok
now shall end this lecture by just saying
what is the context denotes in context free
grammar what is the meaning of context so
language we talk about context as such ok
so we say context is given a word find out
what is the context what are the previous
words and what is the ah topic and all that
so these are all define the context but this
context is nothing to do with what is context
in the case of context free grammar this is
very very formal notion ok
so ah so this is nothing do with the ordinary
meaning of word context in language so all
this means is that in context free grammar
whenever i am doing a derivation ok so whenever
i am writing a gives the b c ok or say noun
phrase give me determiner nominal whenever
i am writing a rule like that it means is
that the noun terminal left it all in its
own by itself ok it does not need any context
around it so i can always write a goes to
b c irrespective of whatever is around my
word a ok so even if i have x a earlier i
can use a to derive x b c and if i have irrespective
of what is x or any y i can always write like
this and this x and y are immaterial they
do not matter it can be null it can be whatever
similarly if i inferring whenever i see a
b c i can always infer a so this it might
have come from a independent of the context
of b c and this is what context free grammar
so if you go would go the next label of context
sensitive grammars there are you need the
context this word a can derive b c in this
particular left context in a particular right
context we do not need this left and right
context in the case of context free grammars
ok this what the context the word context
means in this case
so so whenever i have a rule a goes b c it
means that i can write a i can always write
from a b followed by c regardless of the context
in which a is found or whenever i find and
b followed by a c i can infer a regardless
of the context in which b and c is found so
so this is c f g for for us ah i am not going
to lot of basics of context free grammars
and i suggest that you can quickly look at
any of the chapters in the basic books of
ah formal languages and automated theory so
but whatever is required for our ah tasks
of doing parsing i have covered in this lecture
i will and i will cover the necessary things
in the next lecture so in the next lecture
what we will do we will start from c f gs
and we will see how we can use that for actually
doing the parsing for a given sentence in
the in the language ok so we will take a various
approaches for parsing ok so that will be
the next topic for the next lecture
thank you