so welcome back for second lecture of this
week so we had started our discussions on
syntax so so in the last lecture we had talked
about what is the formulation for doing the
syntax parsing so we had talked about context
free grammars now we will see how do we use
context free grammars for the actual parsing
so so let us take a simple grammar in in terms
of in a c f g formulation so you have in the
grammar it is said that a sentence can be
a noun phrase followed by a verb phrase or
an auxiliary followed by a noun phrase followed
by verb phrase or single single verb phrase
noun phrase can be a determiner followed by
a nominal nominal can be a noun and so on
so all the various possibilities are shown
here and similarly these are all the pre terminals
that are giving me terminals that are words
in my lexical so this is one such grammar
and now using this grammar i can write various
sentences ok so for example i want to write
the sentence
the man read this book ok so i want to write
this sentence the man read this book now how
do i what kind of rules in the grammar do
i use so that i can generate the sentence
so i have to write the man read this book
ok
so let me just do it quickly on on the paper
now the sentence can be a noun phrase followed
by a verb phrase or an auxiliary followed
by a noun phrase verb phrase or a verb phrase
in this case it does not start with an auxiliary
nor a verb so it has to be a noun phrase followed
by a verb phrase so i have to first start
by a noun phrase followed by a verb phrase
ok and i will assume that the man will come
in noun phrase and read this book come in
verb phrase
so what will be the next derivation so np
have to get the man so i have to get something
that says determiner nominal ok so so here
i will say determiner nominal and verb phrase
ok and determiner can can give me the a nominal
can give me noun which can give the word man
so in some steps i can determine to the nominal
verb phrase the noun verb phrase ok and if
i want to complete this i will say the man
verb phrase now the verb phrase i have to
derive read this book ok so verb phrase goes
to verb and noun phrase is the something like
that yes verb phrase goes to verb and noun
phrase
so i will use this and say the man verb noun
phrase verb can directly give me read the
man read noun phrase and from noun phrase
i have to derive this book so i have to again
write this determiner for a nominal this will
become a determiner the man read determiner
nominal and this will give me this and this
will give me noun and this will give me book
ok and that will give me the whole sentence
the man read this book that's i derive a sentence
using this grammar
so now once i have this derivation i can use
this derivation to denote what is the particular
syntax tree that generalizes the sentence
as per this grammar ok so same derivation
can be used for to show the parse tree so
this is my derivation and this derivation
can be shown using this parse tree in the
question of sentence you derived n p v p from
n p you derived determiner and nominal v p
verb and noun phrase noun phrase phrase to
this particular sub trees ok so this is exactly
what was the derivation that you did for the
sentence in my grammar
so that can immediately tell me what is the
problem of parsing i am given the grammar
and i am given the sentence in my language
so given the sentence in my grammar i want
to find out what is it's actual parse tree
and they may not be unique parse they may
be multiple parse tree so the process of parsing
is to find out all the possible parse trees
for a given sentence as per my grammar so
so find out all the trees whose root is the
start symbol s ok because i have to start
with the start variable in my context free
grammar and which cover exactly the words
in the input ok
now what are the constraints on which parsing
suppose my sentence is book that flight so
what are the constraint in my parse they should
be three leaf nodes book that and flight and
ms is you start at the start node and then
i have to explore all the possible rules such
that i come up with the tree is starting with
us as the root node and book that flight as
the only three nodes three leaf nodes ok so
yes the tree must have one root the start
symbol s and that tells me that i can explore
it in at least two different ways one is i
can with top down you start from s try to
find out all the possible possible trees in
finding out i can have as per my grammar and
see if there is one tree that can give me
the only the leaf nodes book that flight this
is top down
other approach is bottom up i start from book
that flight go up words what are the non terminals
and then see if any of this combination can
lead to a full tree it starting from s ok
so these are two different strategies and
that's what we will discuss how do we use
it top down or bottom up approach for parsing
given this grammar
so let's take this grammar so you have certain
rules so left hand side is mainly the rules
for ah non terminals and pre pre terminals
and right hand side are for the lexicon pre
terminals deriving the terminals ok now using
this grammar you want to find out the parse
for book that flight and we will use both
the top down and bottom up strategies for
for finding out this parse tree
so yeah this is also what is the expected
parse tree book that flight this is your whole
verb phrase it's starting from a verb and
a noun phrase so a book is a verb and and
this that flight is a noun phrase ok so i
want to come up with this parse tree given
the grammar and how do i do that in a in a
deterministic manner using the ah using my
ah top down strategy
so how do i start so i have to start from
my so start node root node in top down and
using my grammar as my grammar i will see
what is the different possible rules i can
apply at this point keep on going downwards
ok so a start by assuming that the input can
be derived by s then find out the trees that
is start with s looking at the rules that
are having on the left hand side because what
are the all are different things that s can
derive now when you are going downward in
your tree once you obtain the part of speech
category you will see if that matches the
word in the leaf nodes if it is not matching
you will go back and try out some other path
ok and if there is any trees where the part
of speech categories are not matching the
the words at the leaf nodes you will get ok
so now so let us see so i am starting with
s ok now what is my first rule so what are
the different rules from s so first rule is
s can go to n p v p so what i will do i will
try to explore that path s can got to n p
v p now from np what is the next possible
rule so next rule from n p is n p can give
me a pronoun ok n p give me a pronoun again
i will try to explore this further the pronoun
give me the so pronoun will be the first word
now pronoun is the pre terminal
now what is the first pre terminal book so
pronoun can never give me a book book is not
a pronoun so so this part is not correct so
i will go back from n p i will try to expose
some other path ok so n p can also give me
a proper noun so you see these are the rules
in sequence in my grammar a n p can give me
a pronoun n p can give me proper noun so again
proper noun is a pre terminal that cannot
give me a book so again i cannot accept this
path so i will go back
next rule is n p gives me a determiner followed
by a nominal ok so again the first word has
to be determiner that in the sentence but
the first word is book that is not a determiner
ok so again this path has to be this path
is not correct now we see in the grammar there
is no other rule that has n p on the left
hand side ok so that means i have to now go
back to the initial ah assumption that s will
derive n p v p so i have to try out the next
possibility as per my grammar the next possibility
is s can give me auxiliary followed by noun
phrase followed by a verb phrase ok so let
me do that so s s is give me a auxiliary noun
phrase and verb phrase again what is auxiliary
auxiliary is a pre terminal that gives only
does it does not give me book ok so again
this part is not correct and auxiliary gives
me anything else so again i go back and try
out something else from s and the only remaining
thing is v p
so s gives me a v p ok now i will go to my
grammar what are the rules from v p v p can
give me a verb that is the first thing v p
gives me a verb ok good now verb also gives
me book that that matches there but what happens
to the other two words in my sentence that
flight verb gives me book but that flight
is not covered in this tree so this is not
a valid tree yes that flight there is no other
no node starting from s that captures this
this is again not a valid tree so i will try
out something else with v p so next possibility
is verb followed by n p ok verb followed by
n p and verb gives me book well now from n
p i have to get that flight now again from
n p i can get pronoun pronoun cannot give
me that yes then i can get proper noun it
will also not give me that then i can from
n p i can get determiner followed by a nominal
ok and that is a determiner and from nominal
i can go to noun and this can give me flight
so that means by doing all these exploration
systematically i can come up with a parse
tree that starts from s and exactly covers
these leaf nodes book that flight in my input
so that is my top down parsing strategies
ok so hope that is clear
so we are given all the rules it starts from
s and try to explore in some order you can
take it you can try to explore in the same
order that is in which they are given to you
ok you might try to put them in the order
in which they are actually used in in language
so which one is more probable than other that
is also ok but again you take can you see
that this this requires a far too many steps
right so you you are exploring paths that
will probably never lead to the whole parse
trees so this this this may need very certain
space so we will try to ah take that problem
that how we can avoid that so this is my a
this was my top down parsing
now what do i do in bottom up parsing in top
up i start with s in bottom up i will start
with my leaf nodes i will start with book
that flight and i will try to go my tree upwards
and see which one can give me if complete
tree it is starting from s ok so the parser
starts with the words of the input and tries
to build trees from the words up by applying
rules from the grammar one at a time and parser
looks for the places in the parse in progress
where the right hand side of the rule might
fit ok in top down we were looking at always
the left hand side if the current non terminal
what is the rule in the left hand side so
that accordingly i will i am trying to generate
the right hand side here i am seeing what
what in the right hand side i already have
accordingly i select a rule in my grammar
so so let's do this bottom up parsing so i
have the sentence book that flight i will
start by seeking what are the nodes in my
grammar that can that can generate this ok
so i start by say book and the first rule
that their word book is noun ok then i go
up to noun and say nominal gives me noun fine
and nominal can gives me nominal followed
by a noun so i am going my tree upward but
now i i arrive at noun that is a pre terminal
and noun will not give me that ok so that
is not a noun so this is the inconsistency
so i have to go back and see ok what is the
next possible rule from nominal so i have
to derive from nominal nominal followed by
p p so rememberly we are seeing in which rule
this occurs in the right hand side ok and
accordingly i will take the the production
nominal gives me nominal followed by p p now
can can p p give me that flight so from p
p so from that i i try to go go it upwards
i see determiner determiner comes in right
hand side of this rule n p gives me determiner
nominal and flight again i grow it upwards
it gives me noun a nominal can give me noun
ok so this looks a nice tree
but now can i attach p p to n p so s if i
go n p upwards i will say ok s can give me
n p followed by v p this creates a problem
in that this verb phrase does not have anything
in so it cannot take me to any leaf node ok
so this is not valid if i go to this part
can p p attached to n determiner and n p again
there is no rule in my grammar that p p can
be determiner followed by n p
so i have to go back again try some other
paths we have this is right hand side v p
s s and determiner nomi[nal]- and noun noun
phrase what can they give to me s again this
does not work out so i try out something else
with v p so i say v p gives me v p followed
by a prepositional phrase again prepositional
phrase does not give me determiner followed
by a noun phrase this we will not work out
again go one step down so earlier i was saying
v p is deriving a verb now i am saying ok
v p derives verb followed by an n p does that
work yes if i can attach this v p to this
verb and this noun phrase ok and then i can
say that s can derive this v p and this gives
me the whole parse tree so this is my bottom
up strategy
i start with the words in the leaf in the
leaves try to grow them upwards by seeing
what is the rule in my in my grammar where
this occurs in the right hand side similarly
i will see here and so on and finally can
i build them as a single tree starting from
s and that strategy finally gives me this
particular tree so if we just try to compose
this top down versus bottom up approaches
so what do we see so what we were see in top
down we were always seeing wherever this non
terminal appears in the left hand side and
i i immediately do the production
so what happens that i can x i can always
explore options that will never lead to the
full parse ok i can always find options that
will only give me one word but so so all the
options were given me a parse is starting
from s in in the top down strategy but it
might happened that some options are giving
me a particular parse tree where all the words
are not covered or some extra words are covered
ok so this actual correction the actual sentence
is not taken care so in the bottom up it is
the other way around so we are always seeing
the words first you are exploring that those
paths that are covering the whole sentence
but it might happen that the the parse that
you come up with is not a complete parse because
it is not having a root at s ok so they may
not be a full parse and there are ways to
this specimen both top down and bottom up
ok
so you are seeing you are experiencing lot
many parse that are probably not valuable
and this depends on branching of my grammar
in either direction ok so to avoid this problem
and obtain an algorithm that works in polynomial
time so you will use some dynamic programming
approach ok so we have been using dynamic
programming a lot in this course so we use
that for edit distance then we use that for
coding kind of algorithm
now we will see how to use that for obtaining
an efficient parsing algorithm so so idea
is that can we cache some intermediate results
instead of exploring all the different possibilities
that are not relevant so by doing this caching
i can obtain a polynomial time parsing algorithm
for context free grammars ok and there are
different dynamic programming algorithms that
are both top down as well as bottom up and
they can work in roughly order of n cube time
where n is the length of the sentence number
of words in my input string
so what are the different approaches for dynamic
programming parsing so one very popular algorithm
is c k y algorithm that works in bottom up
manner ok so you will do it for individual
words then you are going to sequence of two
words and so on up to you go to the whole
six sentence and this is the only thing is
that it requires some normalizing of the grammar
that you will also see what is the normalization
then there is earley parser that is again
very popular that works in top down manner
it does not require any normalization of grammar
and slightly more complex than the c k y algorithm
and a generic frame work is something called
a chart parsers where ah for individual phrases
in the sentence they will see what are the
ah possible trees they were retain in the
chart and use that for ah for the higher level
trees ok so and they combined both both of
these approaches bottom up and and top down
so we will only focus on c k y algorithm that
how do we use this for finding out parser
in efficient polynomial time ok so how does
this c k y algorithm works
now before that we have seen that this requires
normalization of grammar so what is that so
to apply c k y algorithm so my grammar must
be converted to a normal form called chomsky
normal form ok and what is the constraint
in chomsky normal form so the constraint is
that all the production of my grammar should
be having of should be having one of these
two forms that is either exactly two non terminals
on the right hand side or one terminal symbol
on the right hand side so what do i mean by
that in the context free grammars
a rule is of the form a goes to gamma where
a is a non terminal and gamma can be a sequence
of terminals and non terminals this is general
c f c production rule so what happens in the
case of chomsky normal form the rules are
constraint to be of these two forms a goes
to b c all these are non terminals or a goes
to small a small a is a terminal so left hand
side is always the same it is only one non
terminal in chomsky normal form what happens
is that you put some constraints on the right
hand side so it can have a either only two
non terminals or only one terminal
so to apply c k y algorithm i must convert
my grammar in any generic context free grammar
form to chomsky normal form ok so what are
the steps involved they are what are ah necessary
for our case so so we will also see that how
do we store all the possible ah phrases what
are their parses in a triangular table in
the c k y algorithm so let me quickly see
let me quickly show how we convert a grammar
to chomsky normal form so in the left hand
side we have a grammar ok and i want to convert
that the chomsky normal form so can you quickly
see go through the grammar and and find out
the rules that are not in chomsky normal form
so all these are one non terminal giving me
a one terminal yes in all these cases so they
are pre terminal to terminal they are always
in chomsky normal form yes a non terminal
giving me a single terminal now let me go
upwards so p p gives me preposition followed
by a noun noun phrase again one non terminal
giving me two non terminals in c n f this
is also in c n f this is also in c n f but
this rule is not in c n f v p goes to verb
one non terminal giving another non terminal
so how do i actually convert this to chomsky
normal form so idea would be i will find out
what are the terminals that this derives so
verb derives book include and prefer so instead
of this rule i will add a new rule verb phrase
gives me book include and prefer ok and this
is the this is the strategy similarly here
this is in c n f this is in c n f what about
this rule nominal goes to noun again i will
find out what are different things that noun
derives book flight meal and money and i will
add a rule nominal derives book flight meal
and money this is in c n f so here again n
p goes to pronoun i will find out pronoun
goes to i he she me so n p gives me i he she
me s goes to v p is again not in c n f so
v p gives me verb and also verb n p ok so
i have to add these rules s goes to verb n
p s goes to v p n p s goes to preposition
n p ok plus for v p going to be verb at now
takes it next rule v p verb going to book
include prefer and the rule i will add is
s goes to book include and prefer s going
to n p v p is fine
but what do i do with this rule s goes to
auxiliary n p and v p ok so for this kind
of rule s goes to auxiliary n p v p where
a single non terminal derives pre non terminals
so what do i do i coin some new non terminals
so i will say that auxiliary noun phrase together
make a new terminals say x one ok so what
will be my grammar it will be s goes to x
one followed by v p and x one will be auxiliary
followed by n p and this is equivalent to
this rule and now this is in my chomsky normal
form so idea is that whenever you have a rule
where you have two more than two non terminals
you try to break them down such that it is
one non terminal another non terminal this
you can again further break down if needed
ok and this is a simple approach and if we
have a rule like this a goes to b and b goes
c you take this two a goes to small c this
is a terminal ok and also if b has something
else you need take care of everything in this
yes that's what we took we saw in this particular
example there
so now if i convert this grammar to chomsky
normal form this is how it will look like
ok so you see that here s goes to v p now
has multiple rules s goes to verb n p s goes
to v p n p and s goes to book include prefer
and so on for the other case also
so in this lecture we had seen that how do
we do a simple parsing using top down approach
and bottom up approach but they are not very
efficient so can we do something better by
using dynamic programming parsing approach
and for that we are trying we will be seeing
ah c k y algorithm so how do you use c k y
algorithm for an efficient parsing but c k
y algorithm requires normalization ah to some
chomsky normal form and we saw how do we convert
a grammar to chomsky normal form
so in the next lecture we will start with
this chomsky normal form and see given a new
ah given a string how do we parse that using
c k y algorithm
thank you