so welcome back for the third lecture of this
week ah in the last lecture we had discussed
top down and bottom up parsing approach and
then finally we came up with the dynamic programming
approach of ah using c k y algorithm and we
converted a grammar to chomsky normal form
now how once my grammar is converted to chomsky
normal form how do i c k y algorithm work
so this is the idea
so i will take a sentence i have n words in
my sentence so you will think about n plus
one lines that are separating them is starting
from zero to one ok and so once you have done
that any x i j will denote words between line
i and j and so you you will build up a table
such that any x i j will contain all the possible
non terminal that can derive words between
the lines i and j ok and you do that bottom
up
so so what i am saying you have word one word
two up to word n in your input stream so you
assume some lines like zero one two n minus
one n ok so for example x zero two is words
w one w two and so on so now what you will
you do you build up a table ok and table will
be some sort of triangular table
so this can be zero one two so this element
will denote x zero one what are all the non
terminals that derive this word between zero
and one similarly here you will write x one
two and so on suppose they want a three words
so this is x two three ok so we will write
down all the non terminals that derive this
you first fill this then you will go next
step x zero two x one three ok and once you
fill this you will use x zero three the final
one ok
now what is the where are we using the fact
that ah this grammar is in c n f chomsky normal
form i will make sure fact that at any point
this can come from only two non terminals
or a single terminal so at this point when
i am seeing at a as a individual word so zero
one will always be a individual word similarly
for one and two so this will come by a rule
capital a goes to small a a rule of this kind
ok so i will find out all the non terminals
that derives this terminal thats how i will
fill the diagonal elements the first diagonal
elements
next time this cannot come from a single terminal
because they are two words ok so this has
to come from two non terminals so i will find
out if there is a rule that gives me these
two non terminals and thats where i am using
chomsky normal form ok so finally when i am
here i will see if the sentence as generate
the whole sentence so i am catching all the
possible intermediate steps here so that i
denoted i have to ah do certain in again and
again ok
so this is the simple home exercise so in
the in the last lecture we had given you a
grammar in chomsky normal form now take the
sentence book the flight through houston and
use the c k y algorithm to find a parse tree
for that ok ah so but what i will do i will
do an example in todays class also so that
it becomes become more much more comfortable
with using c k y algorithm
so lets take this example a pilot likes flying
planes and the grammar is given to you ok
so let do that in the way i had explained
so zero one two three four five there are
five words ok and this is the line
ok and now you should understand how do we
denote these elements so this is x zero one
this is denote only the first word this is
x one two x two three x three four x four
five this will be x zero two words between
zero to two x zero three x zero four x zero
five x one three x one four x one five x two
four x two five and x three five now i have
to fill here what are different non terminals
that filled each of the individual elements
x zero one
what is x zero one my word is a so a pilot
likes flying planes so is there a non terminal
that derives the word a and if you see the
grammar dt derives a ok so you can fill in
dt here dt derives a pilot n n derives pilot
likes v b z derives likes flying so you see
there are two non terminals vbg and j j they
derive this and planes n n s ok so filling
the diagonal element is very easy the first
diagonal elements then you go the next step
x zero two now x zero two can come from x
zero one and x one two as a break up of these
two points so is there an non terminal where
or is there a rule in my grammar when the
right hand side i have dt followed by n n
and if you see your grammar yes n p gives
me dt followed by n n so i can fill in n p
here x one three comes from x one two and
x two three yes x one three pilot likes so
it comes from pilot and likes so any non terminal
that gives me n n followed by v b z and if
you see there is no non terminal so i will
fill in empty here
similarly and if v b z followed by vbg no
anything from v b z followed by j j x three
five v b g followed by n n s yes v p and j
j followed by n n s n p ok so there are two
possibilities so fine this row is done this
diagonal is done now we go to next step now
how do i derive x zero three a pilot likes
now thats why i am using the chomsky normal
form i cannot derive it at the sequence of
three non terminals because each individual
non terminal can give me at most not at most
exactly two non terminals ok so what are the
two places from which it can come so one possibilities
i can break x zero three as x zero one and
x one three one word into two words or x zero
two x two three there are two possibilities
ok so i have to check individually each of
these possibilities x zero one x one three
x zero one is dt followed by null so this
is already gone ok this is no non terminal
x zero two is n p followed by x two three
is v b z so n p followed by v b z is there
a non terminal when the right hand side i
have np followed by v b z ok and if you see
your grammar there is nothing so this is also
null so here it is null there is no non terminal
let me derive a pilot likes ok
now pilot likes flying one to four so again
one to four will be one two two four or one
three three four so one two two four one two
is n n two four is null so this part is null
one three three four one three is null so
this becomes null also two five will be two
three three five and two four four five so
two three here is v b z and three five is
v p is there something that v b z and v p
yes v p this means v b z and v p two four
four five two four is null ok so this is my
v p similarly now you will go to x zero four
now what are difference which you can break
x zero four now zero four again you to break
it in a sequence of two non terminals so it
can be zero one followed by one four or zero
two followed by two four or zero three followed
by three four there are three ways
so let us see one by one zero one is d t one
four is null so this part is gone zero two
is empty and two four is null this part is
also gone zero three is null already so this
is null ok one five one five can be one two
two five one three three five one four four
five one two and two five yes n n followed
by a v p so is there something in my grammar
n n followed by v p no so this is gone
similarly one three followed by three five
one three is null ok and one three is null
so this is gone one four followed by four
five one four is null so this is also gone
so this is also null now the only thing remain
is x zero five
now how can i fill x zero five what are different
ways so let me write down here zero five can
be zero one followed by one five zero two
followed by two five zero three followed by
three five zero four followed by four five
ok zero one followed by one five zero one
is there one five is null this is gone zero
two followed by two five zero two is there
and two five is also there this is n p followed
by v p and this is a sentence in my grammar
so s gives me n p v p so this is one possibility
already so that means this sentence is grammatical
at least there is one s that derives this
but are there any further ah s
so for that we have to look at other possibilities
zero three three five ok this is null and
zero four four five is null ok so fine so
if you see there i think we made one mistake
here there should have been another v p in
this case ok so there is v p one v p two and
then there will be s n p v p one and n p v
p two so yeah i will search that look back
into this ah calculation we did and see where
where we made a mistake ok but everything
else is the same that we did here so there
are two different s in which this ah sentence
can be parse two different ways so now once
you know this i will say that use the previous
ah example so that is book the flight through
houston from the other grammar and try to
get its parse tree
so now in this example what we saw there are
two possibilities so can you think of the
possiblit[ies] why there are two possibilities
in this case a pilot likes flying planes ok
so whether he likes to fly the plane or whether
he likes to see flying planes something like
that so there are interpretation thats why
there are two different parse parse edge of
this sentence so each individual parse with
we will denote one particular interpretation
now by using this context by this c k y algorithm
we denote all the possible parse trees using
my grammar but i have no way of saying which
parse is more probable than the other parse
i cannot assign some probabilities to them
ok so something if i have so this is the sentence
the man saw the dog with the telescope it
has two different interpretation in terms
of two different parse edges whatever i have
covered till now it cannot tell me which parse
is more probable than other
so now we would like to have a way in which
we can assign them the probabilities that
this parse edge is more probable than the
other and for that what we use is called probabilistic
context free grammars so this is simple extension
of context free grammar where in addition
to whatever we have seen in context free grammar
each rule is also signed some probability
ok so as you see in the formulation it is
t n s and r they are exactly same as what
we had seen in the context free grammar plus
there is something called p so i am assigning
a probability distribution over the rules
and only the constraint here is that from
a given non terminal the lateral side the
probability generating anything should add
up to one so if there are five possibilities
if i add all the five possibilities the rule
for all the five possibilities they should
add up to one ok so this is the constraint
so probability in the rule gives the gives
the probability of each rule p r so the constraint
is for all x in non terminals probability
of x to gamma for all the possible gammas
should add up to one ok
so let me give you an example so so this is
one simple cnf sorry simple p c f g in chomsky
normal form ah so so what do you see here
from s there is only one rule s goes to n
p v p ok so because there is only one rule
it has a possibility of one from from v p
there are two rules v p can give v followed
by n p or v p followed by pp so so the constraint
is that for the possibilities of these two
rules should add up to one so that is what
is happening here the first rule has a possibility
of point seven second rule has a possibility
of point three so there is two add up to one
now pp gives me p n p only one rule with pp
on left hand side so this is the possibility
of one p gives me only with again possibility
one v gives me saw this is the possibility
one
now all these rules in the right hand sides
are starting from the n p n p giving to me
n p pp all the words let us call as like astronomers
ears and so on so all these should add up
to one and you can see that this actually
happen point four plus point one point five
point six eight point seven two point nine
and one so all these possibilities are adding
up to one so this is the constraint that is
being followed the rules have the same format
as in context free grammar but you shall have
a possibilities now how does it help it helps
in that i can now assign possibilities to
each individual parse tree
so suppose this is one parse tree astronomers
for the sentence astronomers saw starts with
ears how do i find the probability of this
parse tree this is the parse so i know s gives
me n p and v p yes this is the first rule
that i am applying now as my p c f g the probability
of this rule is one s giving n p v p is one
so i have this one here n p giving astronomers
deriving astronomers is probability point
one v p deriving v and p is probability point
seven v giving saw is one n p giving n p vp
is point four n p giving stars is point one
eight and so on these are the rule probability
as per my grammar as my p c f g so what i
will do i will just multiply all these probabilities
one times point one times point seven times
point one times point four times point one
eight times point one eight this is my probabilities
of this parse trees
and if i get a second parse tree where instead
of v p giving me v and n p v p giving v p
followed by pp i can again compute its probability
by multiplying its corresponding rule probabilities
and i can find the probabilities of both the
parse trees individually ok
so now how do i use that to compute the probability
of the tree that is simply the product of
the probabilities of all the rules that i
used to generate this and probability of assignments
and the probability sentences is nothing but
find out all the parse trees and the probabilities
of the individual parse trees and just sum
them up ok so probability of this sentence
is the sum of the probabilities of the trees
that have this as their yield that is another
way of saying that those parse trees are used
to generate this particular string
so in the first case i had this sentence and
they were to parse trees i can compute the
probabilities of individual one so p t one
and p t two i can find out and then to find
the probability of the whole sentence i just
add up these two probabilities p t one plus
p t two and that gives me the probability
of this whole sequence
similarly if i have another sentence like
book the dinner flight and as as per a different
grammar i can compute the parse trees the
two parse trees compute the probabilities
for the individual one ok so parse tree one
here book the dinner flight is one point six
two into ten to the power minus six and book
the dinner flight will have a probability
of two point two eight into ten to the power
minus seven so one thing i can immediately
see is that the first one parse is more likely
interpretation than the second one
lets look at some of the features of probabilistic
context free grammars so why we started with
this formulation so we said that using the
context free grammar given a sentence we can
find out all the possible parse trees but
you are not able to assign any probabilities
to that so by using p c f g if for a given
string the number of parse trees are increasing
i can also assign the probabilities for each
individual parse tree so that gives me some
plausibility which parse tree is more probable
than the other one for the given string so
this is important but at the same time we
should understand that although by using p
c f g i can compute what is the probability
of the sentence by taking all the parse trees
taking the individual probabilities and adding
them up this is this just not giving a very
good ah plausibility of the sentence ok this
is only looking at the structural factors
not some lexical co occurrence
so in general to find the probability of the
sentence you would prefer to use language
model than a p c f g p c f g is good only
for find the probability of a parse tree which
parse is more probable than another one yes
if the it it helps in some cases like in real
text you might find some grammatical mistakes
so p c f g will allow that but will give you
very very low probability so in one case you
can also probably find out which sentence
has some grammatical mistake if the p c f
g is giving it low probability and yeah this
is something that i said earlier so in practice
this is not good for modeling the probability
of the sentence ok language model is much
better than p c f g so why is that the case
so a simple example is if we have the same
sentence i have two different trees one is
smaller than the other the smaller tree will
always have a higher probability than the
larger one because all the probabilities are
less than one and for a larger tree you are
multiplying the probabilities ok
so yeah the take away here is that you would
use p c f g to find out what what are all
the probabilities for different parse trees
for a sentence ok and try to choose the best
one
so now once we have this formulation of p
c f g there are some interesting questions
that we would like to explore using that so
suppose i am given a sentence w one m ok i
am given a grammar g and there are various
parse trees t is one of those so what is the
most likely parse for this sentence given
the grammar so which parse is tree t gives
me maximum probabilities argmax of probability
given the sentence and the grammar ok then
what is the probability of the sentence probability
of the sentence given by grammar and then
finally how do we learn the rule probabilities
of my grammar g which these are the three
interesting questions that we would like to
answer in the next lectures
so for example how do i find the most likely
parse of a of a sentence so one simple solution
is find out all the possible trees and take
the one with the highest probability but is
there any efficient method for doing that
what is the probability of a sentence again
i can find out probabilities of the individual
parse trees add them up this gives me the
probability of the sentence but can i do at
by extortion numerating all that and adding
it or is this some other method and finally
there is some interesting question that how
do i learn the rule probabilities in the grammar
g and the answer to this will be similar to
what we saw in the case of ah head and markov
models so there are so there are they will
be again two ways of running the parameter
one will be when the ah i am given the corpus
and some labeled parse trees i can use them
to find the probabilities under the scenario
where i am given the corpus but not the parse
tree i am only given the grammar grammar in
the sense cfg not the rule probabilities then
how do i learn the parameters so this will
be again very very interesting topic and there
you can use some ideas where that i had shown
earlier for the ah algorithm
so in the next lecture we will start trying
to answer some of these questions
thank you