so hello everyone welcome back to the fourth
lecture of this week in last lecture we had
discussed what is pcfgs and we we finally
came up with what are the interesting problems
that that we would like to answer so for example
what is the most likely parse for a given
sentence as per my pcfg grammar and what is
the probability of the sentence as per the
grammar finally we also wanted to see how
do i learn my pcfg rule probabilities ok if
you remember this was the only difference
between context free grammar and the probabilities
version is that all the production rules here
have a probability value
so how do i learn these values so this is
what we will be covering in this lecture and
in the next lecture and we will be using a
specific concept called called inside outside
probabilities ok and this will be very analogous
to what you studied in forward backward algorithm
in in terms of learning parameters for h m
m so we will go to that
so we so starting with the first problem how
do i find out the most likely parse for a
sentence and this can be solved simply if
we use the c k y algorithm for pcfg ok so
from the example that we did in the last class
i hope you you understand now how to use c
k y algorithm for the context free grammar
so today i will show how do you extend that
for p c f g
so let us take an example so we have this
pcfg so what you are seeing here with each
rule you have a rule probability as well ok
and and you can verify that all the probabilities
starting from a given right hand side will
add up to one so now i want to find out what
is the most likely parse for the sentence
the same sentence the pilot likes flying planes
so for that i need to find out what is the
probability with which i can find a non terminal
as in the final position for deriving this
whole sentence zero to five so we proceed
nearly in the same manner as we did ah in
the in the case of c k y ok so what i will
do i just take the same example how we solve
c k y in addition and what are the things
that you need to do different here
so this is what we had seen last time so if
you have to build a if you have to find out
what is the whether the sentence can derive
this whole thing i fill it starting from zero
one one two two three three four four five
then i will go further so now i just tell
what is what will differ in the case of pcfg
so now with each non terminal there will be
probability with which it can derive that
particular terminal or a set of terminals
so it is starting from the first element so
this says that the non terminal dt derives
a now i will write down here what is the probability
ok so if you go to your grammar the probability
dt gives me a it's point three so i will put
point three here
similarly for this element what is the probability
that n n gives me pilot and if i look at my
grammar this is point one similarly here what
is the probability that vbz derives likes
this gives me point four and like that i will
fill all these entries now this is ok
now what i want to show you is that how do
i fill the next entry that is zero two what
is the probability with which the non terminal
n p derives the sequence a pilot now if you
remember a single non terminal can derive
two non terminals two terminals only via two
non terminals so it has to first derive x
zero one x one two then each will individually
derive an pilot so how do i fill in this probability
value so this would be probability that n
p derives d t n n times probability dt derives
a times probability n n derives pilot ok this
probability getting my pcfg so this probability
if i see in my grammar this is point three
this probability i have already filled in
is point three and this probability also i
have filled in this is point one
so the probability that n p derives a pilot
here comes out to be nine times ten to the
power minus three and that's what i fill in
here ok and in the same manner you will fill
in all the entries if it is five it means
the probability will be zero ok and if there
is a non terminal here that means there will
be certain probabilities and this you can
get by finding out probability individually
for each of this and multiplying the probability
of this rule so that way you can incrementally
built all the stable from in a bottom up fashion
we are starting from the first element then
in the next one and so on ok so remember nearly
same as we did in the last class only the
the probabilities and the multifunctional
probabilities will change suppose you do that
for this example this is what you will find
out so these are the rule probabilities that
you will come up with so i will i will encourage
all of you that you should try this on your
own and see that you can get the same set
of values that have been shown in the slide
so now coming to the next question i am given
the pcfg as my grammar how do i find out what
is the probability of the sentence ok so one
simple solution you can always find is that
i find out all the possible parse trees find
the probabilities for each of the parse trees
and add those up that is one way ok but this
you might be inefficient if there are very
huge number of parses trees if you remember
one of the introductory slides we said that
as you increase the number of words in the
sentence or the number of phrases the number
of possible parses increase roughly exponentially
ok there was something like peclet number
with this their group and it can go go two
hundred plus parses so you don't want to sum
this get the probability individually and
then do addition you want to do something
more efficient than that and how do we do
this and that's why we use this inside algorithm
ok that is one of the main topics of this
lecture so what is the inside algorithm and
this is some dynamic programming algorithm
based on the concept of inside outside probabilities
so now i will i will try to introduce what
is that inside outside probability so this
this is very centre to understanding this
lecture as well as the next lecture so so
let us try to understand what is the concept
ok and just so that it it helps you this is
very very similar to the concept of forward
backward algorithm that we did in the case
of h m f s so what is inside outside probabilities
so i can this is parameterized for certain
node of my tree so what you see in this figure
i have a sentence with words w one to w m
ok and n one is the non terminal you can think
of it as the sentence non terminal that derives
the whole sequence of words using my grammar
now i am putting a parameter here that is
n j n j is one particular non terminal it
can be n p v p or so on so what i am saying
here assume that there is a non terminal n
j that derives the sequence w p to w q ok
again p and q are arbitrary you can take any
p starting from one to m minus one ok so what
i am parameterized here is that this n j derives
the sequence w p to w q so now with respect
to that i am defining what is my inside probabilities
and what is my outside probabilities so you
can as such you can guess this is something
outside of that and this is something inside
of that
so how do i define my inside and outside probabilities
so outside probability is that it is starting
from n one i can derive the sequence w one
to w p minus one i can derive this non terminal
w sorry n j and the sequence w q plus one
to w m this is my outside probability and
inside probability is given this n j the probability
that i can derive w p to w q as per my grammar
ok and it will then follow the same sort of
ideas that if i can multiply inside and outside
probability that will give me something like
the probability of the sentence parameterized
by this particular jth non terminal so formally
that's how i can write the outside and inside
probabilities
outside probability alpha j p q that is standard
format which we can write p q denotes the
sequence w p w q on which this parameterized
and j denotes the particular non terminal
n j here so the outside probabilities probability
of generating w one to w p minus one yes and
j p q and w q plus one to m given by grammar
and inside probabilities probability of generating
w p to w q given n j ok so this is also parameterized
by n j p q because it is arriving w p to w
q and in my grammar so that's why i define
my inside and outside probabilities
now let us take a simple example i have the
sentence the gunman sprayed the building with
bullets ok and here your p q is four and five
so you are parameterization with respect to
this sequence the building ok so accordingly
this will be particular non terminal that
is n p that is deriving the building so now
what do we mean by inside probability so inside
probabilities what is the probability that
this non terminal n p at this location derives
the sequence the building this is my inside
probability ok and what will be the outside
probability here that is starting from n one
i can derive the sequence the gunman is sprayed
this n p and with bullets this is my outside
probability ok so yeah so this is what we
have defined the outside probability alpha
n p four five would be the probability of
this sequence the gunman is sprayed n p four
five and with bullets given my grammar and
the inside probability beta n p four five
would be the probability for deriving the
building given n p four five and grammar
now this is this definition of inside and
outside probabilities now how do i actually
compute this inside and outside probability
given this sentence and suppose our grammar
is also given to me how do i compute that
so for inside probability so let us see this
is the definition of inside probability beta
j p q is probability of deriving the sequence
w p to w q given non terminal n j p q in my
grammar now so i am i will be deriving both
these probabilities in a iterative manner
so what will be the base case here so the
base case here if you see would be when p
and q are same that is i am deriving a single
terminal from a non terminal ok and that you
can find out very easily if your grammar is
in the chomsky normal form so what is the
particular non terminal that derives this
term so this would be the base case for deriving
a single term base and then i will go in a
bottom up fashion derive the inside probabilities
for higher and higher sequences so the base
case here is when p is equal to q so beta
j k k would be probability of w k k given
n j k k and g now w k k is a single word ok
sequence from k to k and i can immediately
find out what is the role in my grammar that
derives this word w k k and i put this rule
probability here and this will give me the
this probability beta j k k
now as an example suppose here my word is
building ok so this is the fifth word so i
am computing beta for five five and suppose
i take n j is equal to n n that works in non
terminal derives this word so you can compute
beta n n five five as the probability with
which the non terminal n n can derive this
word building ok and this is easily given
by my grammar so this is my base case
now what will be the inductive case so i have
to go bottom up so lets take a generic beta
j p q how do i derive it in terms of the smaller
values so let us try to do that so if i am
given i have to compute beta j p q what is
that mean it means that i have a non terminal
n j and that is deriving a sequence w p up
to w q ok and i have to compute this probability
given n j the probability of the sequence
w p to w q because i am conducting in a i
am doing it in a bottom fashion and i have
to use the proper lower values
so i will first say n j can give me some n
r and n s now n r will derive from w p to
some w d so very generic case so this can
be any possible n r and n s that my n j can
derive and again i can go from w p to any
w d so you can see what can d vary from to
so d can vary from p up to q minus one ok
and this n s gives me w d plus one up to w
q this is my recursive case ok now how do
i write down this probability so i will say
this is first the probability that n j derives
the rule the non terminal the n r and n s
so probability n j derives n r n s times this
probability now here n r is given so what
is the probability is that n r given n r it
derives from w p to w d again you can compute
this using so you can express this using inside
probability that is beta r p d similarly this
one beta s d plus one to q ok now this is
for the particular variation that i have shown
but in general d can vary from p to q minus
one and they can be any possible n r and n
s so i will have to write down this whole
thing let me call it x so i have to say this
can vary from p to q minus one and all possible
n r n s ok and i will put x here so this is
my inductive step
now what do i mean by parameterization over
by all possible r s and all possible d so
if you take the case of this simple phrase
the huge building ok so what do i mean by
various d so if i have this this is the huge
building by variation of d i mean whether
i am composing it by the huge and building
or the and huge building two possible variables
of d ok and what do i mean by parameterization
over all possible n r and n s so that the
particular non terminal that derives this
whole thing can be support this n p it can
come via say n p gives me d t n n this is
one possibility this is dtnn this is and or
we can make n p gives me d t n n s this is
another possibility so this is the parameterization
over all possible n r n s and this is over
out possible d's
so now we have seen that you can compute it
for the only the terminals first and then
the bottom up to compute it for other values
ok so now if you do a simple example so this
is again similar to what we have seen earlier
so i am given this pcfg and this is my sentence
and i want to compute the inside probabilities
here so how do i go about out it and you looking
at the table you can see that we will doing
something very similar to what we did in the
case of c k y algorithm ok
but now we will focus on filling up what is
the inside probability of deriving this from
the particular non terminal ok so let us just
try to filling some entries here
ok let me lets try only the first two this
is astronomers and this is saw ok and i have
to fill in the inside probabilities so this
would be so now in the in the in the way we
defined inside probability this would be one
one this would be two two sequence from word
two to word two this would be sequence from
word one to word two
so now when i define beta j p q so here p
and q are both one so i have to find out what
is the non terminal that derives this word
astronomers now if i see a grammar and these
derive astronomers with the probability of
point one so i can fill fill the inside probability
here beta n p one one one one you need not
to write and i am just writing here is equal
to point one ok because one one is already
defined by the particular cell where we are
similarly let us go to two two two two is
saw if i see the grammar n p derives saw n
p derives saw ok so there are two different
so that's where you can see there are two
different j that are possible here so one
is beta v another is beta n p and this has
the probability of one and this has the probability
of zero point zero four using my grammar
now suppose i have to fill this one one two
what is the particular non terminal that will
derive this this whole thing again similar
to what we were doing in c k y is the something
that derives n p and n p if i see my grammar
nothing derives n p and n p ok in the right
hand side now is there something that derives
n p followed by v or again there is nothing
here n p followed by v so this will come out
to be zero ok suppose there was something
that derives n p followed by v so i would
simplify find out what is the non terminal
that is deriving this and put the probability
as this times this times the rule probability
ok
similar to what we were doing in the case
of c k y for probability context free grammars
the only difference here is that if there
are multiple splits for same non terminal
i will add all these ok so so for example
the same non terminal so i am taking a hypothetical
case suppose the same non terminal x derives
n p followed by v and also n p followed by
n p if the probability of p one is the rule
probability this is a probability of p two
so i will put here beta x and this will be
p one times zero point one times one plus
p two times zero point one times zero point
zero four and that's why i fill in all the
entries ok
so i will i will take care of all the possible
ways in which this particular non terminal
we can derive this ok so again so if you keep
on doing that this is what you will see so
we had filled in this entry and this entry
and this entry but i will encourage you to
fill in all the entries of this table and
see if you can get to this particular term
what is the probability of the sentence generating
this whole thing ok so now if you see this
table you also get the answer for the second
question it how do i find out the probability
of my sentence use the same probabilities
and compute beta as for one to m or one to
five in this case that will give you the probability
of this whole sentence ok so this was about
inside probabilities
now how do i compute the outside probabilities
ok so if you remember this is analogous to
what we did in the case of forward backward
algorithm so now inside probabilities we are
computing bottom up and this will be computed
top down and what will be the base case base
case would be very very simple that is can
i generate the whole sequence one to m ok
and now because this is the grammatical sentence
we are assuming so only the first non terminal
that is sentence or you can write it as n
one can derive this whole sentence nothing
else can derive so that's why the base case
will be alpha one one to m is one if the so
this j is one otherwise it will be zero
so if i write down alpha one one to m will
be one and alpha j one to m will be zero if
j is not equal to one if j is equal to one
denotes the starting non terminal like s or
n one whatever ah we were using the notation
form so now this is the base case now what
will be the inductive case so inductive case
would be i have to compute it in a top down
fashion ok so can you think of inductive case
here
so now what i am showing here what are the
two possibilities of this inductive case so
let me just show it quickly on the paper so
i have to compute alpha j p q ok and i am
going top down now what is the alpha j p q
i have a non terminal n j that derives w p
to w q ok and everything else w one to w p
minus one and w q plus one to w m is there
in the sentence now i have to do it in a top
down manner so i have to use the probability
from the upper label so i would say what is
the non terminal that derives this n j with
some other non terminal and again this can
be either left child or right child lets take
the case where it is the left child so i would
say there is some non terminal n f it is starting
from p up to you have to take some w e p e
that derives n j and some n g and what is
the parameters here this is p q this would
be q plus one to e ok so this is deriving
q plus one to e
now i am doing it top down so i have already
completed this that is the probability of
this sequence this and w e plus one up to
m this i have already obtained now what i
have to obtained in alpha j p q is the probability
of w one to w p minus p n j p q and w q plus
one to w m this is what i have to obtain now
here i have already obtained this probability
and n f p e and somewhere w q plus one to
w m this i have obtained so how do i write
it in in this in terms of n f p e i will say
this is n f p e ok although they may be different
possible n f p e we will do the summation
over that later times probability of this
will probability n f gives you n j n g already
we have come here and this is deriving w q
plus one to w e because i need these probabilities
also
now now how do i how do i write down this
expression this we just did in the previous
case so this is nothing but the inside probability
ok so this would be beta g q plus one to e
ok and that gives me the probability for this
particular extraction although there are various
summations that we will have to do same case
we can do for the when this is the right child
then n g will come here and this is a huge
very very similar ok
so if you look at then in this case so this
is where it is a left child this is where
it is a right child in this case as we did
it is alpha f p e probability of this rule
and inside probability of this whole sequence
and what are these summing over all the possible
f and g's ok because it can be any non terminal
that is arriving this n along with any other
non terminal and what can what what is something
else that can vary my e can vary from q plus
one up to m so i am summing over all the possibilities
and you can similarly see for the for the
second case
so now so so what is important here you can
compute this outside probabilities by using
inside probabilities on a that means you have
to first compute the inside probabilities
use that to compute the outside probabilities
ok although computing outside probabilities
much much more difficult than computing inside
probability if you want to do that on paper
that's why we did a example only for the inside
probabilities
now coming to this point so remember when
i were saying that we have done this parameterization
of inside and outside probabilities such that
if we multiply that we had something interesting
that we can use further and the goal here
is also to compute the rule probabilities
that is my third question i was asking that
how do i compute my rule probabilities of
pcfg we will come to that in the next lecture
let us quickly see what do i get if i multiply
the alpha j p q with beta j p q ok so if i
do that so alpha j p g is nothing but probability
of w one to w p minus one n j p q and w q
plus one to m given my grammar and beta j
p q is probability of w p q given and n j
p q in the grammar so you multiply both of
these you will see that w p q can come here
and n p q is also retained here ok because
here i need n j p q to be given that is already
given to me before so this is the multiplication
ok now what does this say so it is saying
if i multiply alpha j p q with beta j p q
i get the probability of generating this whole
sequence of words w one to w m and that a
non terminal n j derives w p to w q ok given
my grammar
now suppose i want to find out the probability
that any possible non terminal derives from
w p to w q there is some consistent spanning
from w p w q in that case i will have to sum
over all possible j's that i can achieve by
summing over all possible j`s for alpha j
p q into beta j p q this is the probability
of the sentence and that there is some consistent
is spanning from the w word p to word q ok
and this is you can write in this manner ok
this is the same thing n one derives w one
m and n p q derives w p q this and this are
the same thing except this particular index
of n j
now if we go back to the previous example
that we took what does that mean so probability
is that this whole sentence the gunman sprayed
the building with bullets and that there is
some consistent spanning from word four to
word five that means there is some non terminal
they derive this sequence the word four to
word five how do i obtain it this should be
summation over all the possible non terminals
n j such that this happens the gunman sprayed
the building with bullets n j p q given g
and this is nothing but alpha n p four five
beta n p four five so here i am taking all
possible j's j can be n p v p and so on
so whatever non terminals so i multiply alpha
beta for a particular j and add overall the
possible j that gives me this probabilities
so even here it may not be very very clear
what is the actual use of obtaining this particular
probability value ok how do i use it further
and that is what we will see in the next lecture
that how do i use this inside outside probability
for learning the rule probabilities of my
probabilistic context free grammatical ok
so i hope this concept of inside outside probabilities
is clear to you and then we can see how do
use that further in the next class
thank you