so welcome back for the final lecture of this
week so in the last lecture we had started
with the concept of inside outside probabilities
and how do you use them for answering certain
questions like what is the probability of
a sentence as per my grammar and what is the
most likely parse ok so i have use the inside
algorithm specifically to find out what is
the probabilities of this sentence as per
my grammar and then in the end i was saying
that we will also use this this concept to
find out the rule probabilities of my grammar
and how do we do that again exactly what we
will discuss in this lecture
so now (Refer Time: 01:00) in general how
do you obtain the the rule probabilities and
remember this is very similar to what we were
also talking about in the case of h m m s
when i have to learn the parameters of my
h m m i can do that in two manner one where
where i am given already the labeled data
set that means i am given what are the sentences
and what is their past edge if i am given
all that so then from there i can compute
how many times non terminal derives a particular
sequence divide by number of times a particular
non terminal has been used that will give
me the probability of this particular rule
ok if there is only one rule possible from
n j this is always you want but if there multiple
rules are possible i can find out what fraction
of times this particular instance has been
used in my labeled data sets and by (Refer
Time: 02:00) that i can compute all the rule
probabilities
now so this is easy but what about the case
where the training data is not given to us
that is i have no way to find out in which
sentence what is the rule that has been used
so what is in fact given to us so we are assume
that we are given the underlying context free
grammar so i am given all the possible rules
but what i am not given what is the probabilities
for each individual rules so that means the
the particular p c f gs part the rule probabilities
is not given to us and i am given a lot of
sentences and i am the given the grammar that
will generate these sentences but not the
rule probabilities and my my task is how do
i find out these rules probabilities so so
in other words how do i find out the parameters
of my p c f gs and we will use the same sort
of idea that we did earlier that is (Refer
Time: 03:00) you are given the observation
of sentences find out the parameters of a
model that maximize the likelihood of observing
the sentences ok so this is what we are going
to do maximize the likelihood of the sentences
in the data under the p c f g constraints
and for that we will use some sort of expectation
expression algorithm
so so lets take a simple example and what
is the intuition for using this so we start
with this simple sentence like she eats pizza
without anchovies and a particular parse tree
is given to us so what kind of rules to you
see here so you have rules of the form a single
non terminal derives to two different non
terminals like s derives n and v v derives
v and n and so on and there are rules of the
form a non terminal derives (Refer Time: 04:00)
a terminal like here and derives anchovies
pp derives without n derives pizza v derives
eats and so on so these are different sort
of non terminals that are given the rules
that are given to me i do not know the probabilities
for each individual rule
now can you think of any other parse for this
sentence she eats pizza without anchovies
ok so one parse that we saw was she eats pizza
and pizza without anchovies modifying pizza
ok what is the other possibilities ok so other
could be the without anchovies does not modify
pizza it is a separate phrase altogether starting
from v ok so something like she eats pizza
with fog ok in in that sort of meaning (Refer
Time: 05:00) so yeah so she eats pizza without
hesitation that is another sort of possibility
now a single v here is giving me v and n p
so this is the different parse tree for the
same sentence
now i can what are the new rules that i have
added v gives me v n and p and n gives me
hesitation these are two new rules i have
added so now what do you see i have two different
sentences she eats pizza without anchovies
and she eats pizza without hesitation and
both have two possible parse edge and i know
what are the all possible rules now my task
is given these sentences how do i find out
what should be the ideal rule probabilities
so now for that let me first define so we
need to find out all these probabilities so
probability of this rule s gives me n and
v probability of rule n gives me pizza and
so on now (Refer Time: 06:00) what is the
p c f g requirement the p c f g requirement
is that it starting from a single non terminal
all the possible sets of right hand side that
i can generate so that is so all the possible
rules starting from a to any alpha the probability
should also added to one ok so now if i look
at my grammar so i have five rules pair and
occurs in the left hand side n gives me np
n gives me pizza anchovies and so on so all
these should also added to one
similarly three rules where v occurs in the
left hand side so all these should also added
to one and then there are some other rules
like s gives me n v n v nothing else this
would be one and so on so this constraints
i can obtain from my from my grammar i know
what are the rules and what is the constraint
starting from the left hand side all possible
rule should have a probability adding up to
one
now i have two sentences (Refer Time: 07:00)
can i compute the likelihood of the sentences
w one and w two so what do i mean by likelihood
what is the probability of generating the
sentence as of my grammar right now i am not
giving the rule probabilities but i can write
down in terms of the variable rule probabilities
so what will the likelihood of w one ok so
for the that i have to take the two possible
parse trees so here t one is the first parse
tree so here i am giving the probabilities
of both the sentences as per the first parse
tree ok so probability of sentence w one as
per the first parse tree t one and probability
of sentence w two as per the first parse tree
t one how do i compute that it is very similar
to what we saw in the case of p c f g how
do we compute the probability of a parse tree
if the rule probabilities are given that was
very easy here the possibilities are not given
but you can parameterize so you will say what
is the probability of s giving me n v and
so on (Refer Time: 08:00) up to you go to
the leaves and i do not know these whole probabilities
similarly i can write down this likelihood
of the sentence w two as per my first parse
tree
similarly i can do further second parse tree
also for both the sentences so this tells
me so if i know all the possible parse trees
because my ah c f g s given to me i will know
all the possible parse tree i can ah put my
all the rule probabilities as variables and
define what is the likelihood of various parse
tree now what is the likelihood of the sentence
it will be summation of the likelihood as
per different possible parse trees ok so probability
sentence such summation over all the possible
trees that can generate this this p phi w
t in this case for both sentences w one w
two i had two different parse trees so i will
just add the two two probabilities to get
the likelihood of the sentence and how do
i get the (Refer Time: 09:00) likelihood of
the whole corpus that has multiple sentences
for that i will come to the likelihood of
each sentence and multiply those so if i have
a sentences w 1 to w n i compute the likelihood
of each and keep on multiplying now now we
know that how do i express the likelihood
of my corpus in terms of the rule probabilities
right the only variable here are all the rule
probabilities now i can further define my
problem
so my problem would be so this is some sort
of e m approach i will start with some initial
parameters phi phi means the rule probabilities
i want to re estimate so that i obtain some
new parameters phi prime such that the likelihood
of my corpus increases now so l phi prime
will be greater than equal to l phi and i
keep on doing that until l converge (Refer
Time: 10:00) so now here we have to apply
algorithm so that we can so that we can keep
on updating our rule ah rule probabilities
this is the parameter of my system and how
do we do that if you remember that like what
we did in the case of learning parameters
for g s analogous to that what we will do
here we will start with some arbitrary rule
probabilities phi ok and use that to compute
something intermediate so in this case what
we will compute what is the expected number
of times a particular rule has been used if
the rule probabilities are as per the current
parameters i will compute the expected value
again use the expected value to compute the
probabilities so i will compute my phi prime
again use the phi prime to compute the expected
number of times each rule has been used and
again compute five dwell prime and keep on
doing that until you converge and thats why
we will be using the inside outside probabilities
so let us see (Refer Time: 11:00)
so so idea is that i start with some rules
probabilities phi and i am given a corpus
that that what are sentences that i observing
w i w j and i will obtain the new parameters
phi prime using the simple idea so this is
something that we were saying if we are given
the labeled data thats why i will compute
the rule probabilities so i am saying i can
always define probability of the rule a given
b c as the number of times the rule a given
b c a gives goes to b c or a derives to b
c has been applied in my corpus divide by
all the possible all the different times where
a derives alpha for all possible alpha and
this gives me the probability for a deriving
b c
similarly i can compute probability a deriving
w by saying how many times this rule has been
used (Refer Time: 12:00) divide by number
of times a gives me alpha has been used in
my corpus in my actual corpus but we do not
have any labeled corpus we only know what
parse are possible ok and for each parse we
can compute the probabilities using the previous
parameter phi so how do i write down this
count a derives b c number of times this rule
has been used for that i use the idea that
i have multiple sentences any sentence i can
find the expected number of times this rule
a deriving b c has been used so that is count
a deriving b c is nothing but summation over
all the sentences number of times a deriving
b c has been used for the particular sentence
ok same one for the count of a deriving w
each sentence find out the expected number
of times a particular rule has been used now
how do i (Refer Time: 13:00) actually come
up with this formulation expected number of
times a particular rule has been used in a
sentence and for that we use the inside probabilities
and outside probabilities ok
so now coming back to this inside and outside
probabilities and how do we use that to compute
the expected number of times a rule has been
used in a sentence now this must be clear
by the previous slide that if i can compute
the expected number of times a rule has been
used in a sentence i can keep on updating
my parameters this is the only bottleneck
in the previous computation and we will see
how to do that using the inside and outside
probabilities so let me give the definitions
again so inside probability is starting from
non terminal a i derive the words w i to w
j in the sentence ok so that is probability
that a derives w i to w j as per my grammar
and the outside (Refer Time: 14:00) probabilities
starting from the symbol s i can derive the
string w one to w i minus one a and w j plus
one to w n ok so it starting from s i can
derive w one to w i minus one a w j plus one
to w n now once we are given the inside and
outside probabilities we can actually compute
the expected number of times the rule has
been used and the expression comes out to
be this one expected number of times a rule
a has been a derives b c has been used in
my sentence w each the rule probability a
given b c divide by the probability of the
sentence and this very ah peculiar term that
you see that you are seeing here so you are
seeing here alpha i k a beta i j b and beta
j plus one k c now how how do i actually come
up with a term like that and how do i come
up with this expression that is expected count
is given by this (Refer Time: 15:00) so for
that let us go back to what we were discussing
in the last lecture that i can multiply inside
and outside probabilities to know something
about the probability for the sentence
so let us go back to that so what we were
saying if i multiply alpha j p q and beta
j p q what does it give me it gives me the
probability that it starting from n one i
can derive w one m and it starting from n
j i can derive w p q as per my grammar ok
so now i can use the chain rule here to write
it like that so its probability n one derives
w one m so this (Refer Time: 16:00) derives
any number of given by grammar times probability
n j derives w p q given n one derives w one
m and my grammar so now what is this probability
that n one derives w one m given by grammar
second write as the p phi w probability of
the sentence ok and what is this this say
what is the probability that this rule n j
has been used to derive w p q given that the
sentences there and my grammar is there ok
so and how many times this has been used in
this particular context only one time so can
i (Refer Time: 17:00) write down expected
number of times n j derives
w p q is used that would be alpha j p q beta
j p q given divided by p phi w ok and suppose
because i do not want to fix this p q i just
want to say expected number of times the rule
n j has been used so each time it has been
used only once for deriving w to w q so here
i will have to sum over all the possible p
and q (Refer Time: 18:00) so i will say p
can go from one to m suppose there are w one
to w m so these are number of words and q
can go from p up to m ok so this is the expected
number of times my rule and j has been used
now now what is something that i have to express
i want to find out for example expected number
of times a rule like a goes to b c has been
used or a goes to w has been used what is
the expected number of times these has been
used now for that suppose let us take the
easy case expected number of times the rule
a goes to w or a derives w has been used so
in this case what i am saying n j derives
a particular terminal here that (Refer Time:
19:00) is some p p so i can write the beta
j p p for that case and beta j p p is simply
the rule probability that is what is the probability
that in non terminal derives this word w p
so we will see the expression for that so
this one is easy
but what about this case when the rule a derives
b c so in the particular notation that i have
written suppose you want to say expected number
of times n j derives n r n s is used ok so
now what would happen so this beta j p q is
when the terminal n j derives the whole sequence
p q (Refer Time: 20:00) w p to w q and can
use any possible rules yes n r n s or n j
n z whatever it can use any non terminals
now what i am my limiting i am saying this
rule should only use this so this non terminal
should only derive n r n s ok so then i am
saying so that means my n j will derive n
r n s and this n r n s will again derive say
w p to some w d and this will derive w d plus
one to w q ok
so now how do i modify this equation so alpha
j p q is the outside probability that will
remain the same nothing has changed for outside
probability but inside probability because
i am saying this should be the situation so
i (Refer Time: 21:00) further express it like
with a particular path so i will write in
place of beta j p q i will write probability
of the rule n j derives n r n s times this
beta probability that is beta r p d times
beta s d plus one to q but now the d can vary
i have already been given that n j gives me
n r n s but they can take different possible
d s so this will be summation over d and d
can vary from p to q minus one ok so these
between p and q now if you put that can you
see that you can you can actually obtain the
same expression that was given in the slide
so if you go back to the slide (Refer Time:
22:00) thats what we have been doing here
so you see the expression we have three parameters
beta i j b so three parameters i j and k that
corresponds to
p d and q ok and this was the outside probability
and this is the inside probability for ah
the i j and j plus one k and then you have
the rule probability here ok so this expected
number of count has been derived in this particular
form and same thing you can try with the next
formula the expected number of times the rule
a deriving the w has been used in my graph
and you will obtain this particular expression
ok
so so what we are seeing here suppose i start
with some initial rule probabilities ok (Refer
Time: 23:00) so i can use the inside outside
probability so all the recursive formulation
to compute all the inside outside probabilities
for my various rules and stages once i do
that i can compute what is the expected number
of times each and each individual rule has
been used in my corpus as per the current
parameters once i have the expected number
of times rule has been used i can further
estimate my parameters by number of times
the rule used divide by number of times any
particular rule starting with that non terminal
has been used and that will give me the new
parameters again i will compute inside outside
probabilities expected count the parameters
and this i will continue until this converges
and yeah so so computing inside outside probabilities
is as we discussed earlier by this inductive
manner so (Refer Time: 24:00) so what we discussed
in this module was that what is parsing in
terms of a constituency structure and how
do you use the formulation of context free
grammar to do parsing how do we incorporate
the rule probabilities there how do we learn
the rule probabilities using this interesting
concept of inside outside probabilities ok
so i hope the by the example that we did in
the class you will be able to ah understand
how it is actual exactly works in practice
so in the next week so we will starting with
this different notion of parsing so right
now we have done a constituency parsing so
we will see there is a different notion of
parsing called dependency parsing so what
is the formulation that that dependency parsing
follows how it is different from this constituency
parsing and what are different methods we
can used for that that will be a topic for
the next week
thank you (Refer Time: 25:00)