so welcome back for the sixth week of this
course so so we had already started our discussion
on what is parsing so this is the topic in
syntax and we talked about a constituency
parsing approach ok by using the probabilistic
context free grammars so now we will use a
slight different version of parsing is called
dependency parsing so where ah instead of
what we did in the case of constituency parsing
where we were finding out what are the different
word groups in terms of noun phrases adjective
phrases verb phrases we will directly find
out what is the relation between any two words
in a sentence ok so dependency parsing notion
has ah picked up a lot in in research field
in the last few years but as such it is origin
is is very very old many many different linguistic
traditions for example in in ah for the sanskrit
the famous sanskrit grammar [FL] that are
the dependency relation between verb and different
ah words in the sentences
so for example if i have a sentence like ram
eats apple a simple sentence i will see the
verb eat is the main main verb here and what
is the relation of ram so ram is subject of
this verb and apple becomes an object of this
verb ok so like that i am so here i am trying
to directly say in this sentence if i am in
different words are these related somehow
and what is the relation between them so this
is my dependency structure
so in this lecture we will see what is the
what is the formal way in which we can define
dependency structure what are different linguistic
constraints etcetera that we we need to impose
in this structure and then we will start talking
about the some of the models that are very
popular for getting the dependency structure
it's starting from the sentence
so this kind of tree we have seen in the case
of phrase structure also called the constituency
structure so what we have seen here i have
a sentence economic news had little effect
on financial markets so they are different
group of words as single unit so economic
news make a noun phrase similarly this whole
thing makes a verb phrase and they together
make a sentence so like that what we have
seen here which words are grouped together
ok and how this whole sentence has been arranged
that's what you see in a phrase structure
now how dependency structure different so
for the same sentence let us look at the dependency
structure so here what are you seeing now
this also looks like a tree but the nodes
here are the words themselves not the phrases
and different words has been have been connected
by some edges and they label by some relation
like had and news are connected and the relation
is subject saying that news is a subject for
the verb had similarly economic and news are
related so this is economic is a noun modifier
for the word news and so on lot of different
words are connected in this sentence so in
general what we are seeing two different words
in a sentence are connected by certain relation
and this is a directed sort of relation so
economic and news are related by saying economic
is a noun modifier for news
so so in general how we can define a dependency
structure so we take another sentence here
he sent her a letter ok so what you are seeing
here so first you are seeing some five six
words or if you take the punctuation so they
are five words as such he send her a letter
five individual words so what do i do in dependency
structure so we are connecting the word in
the sentence by putting arrows between the
words so i am putting an arrow between sent
and he and these two are connected so he is
a subject for sent similarly i am putting
an arrow between sent and her so in that her
is in indirect object for sent
now what do these arrow show which arrows
are showing means the relations between words
and are also typed by some grammatical relation
so they are saying these some relation and
what is the relation it is the subject relation
he is a subject for sent and what do these
arrows connect they connect a head word like
sent with a dependent word like he and there
are some in linguistic there are some other
terms like head can be called governor superior
regent and the dependent can also be called
a modifier inferior or subordinate and usually
as you would see the dependency which will
form a sort of tree structure
now so what is important here so dependencies
you have a head that connects to a dependent
by an arrow so arrow points from a head to
a dependent so now are they said some formal
criteria for saying in a sentence if two words
are connected what will be a head and what
will be the dependent so there are some idea
they may not be applying everywhere but may
be applying it certain points so you will
see some say examples for some of these so
what are these criteria for defining a relation
between head and dependent in a construction
so first criteria you can see is that the
head determines what is the syntactic category
of the dependent or sorry what is syntactic
category of the whole construction ok
so like if i see this construction a letter
the whole whole syntactic category governs
simply by the word letter ok and that's why
the head itself so the word letter becomes
the head and this word letter can also replace
the whole construction c so in place of the
whole thing a letter i may also write simply
letter now d specifies h so that means d is
giving further specific information about
h so i if i write only if i say only letter
may not be as specific as saying a letter
ok so all these determines they give some
additional information similarly here ok so
sent is the head and letter is the modifier
so if i just simply say he sent it's not very
specific to whom did he sent so there i have
to specific particular modifier he sent her
similarly what did he sent so there i have
to put the word letter so what you are seeing
the dependence is further specifying my head
now in some cases so so head is always obligatory
i need to put head like letter is import[ant]-
is necessary to put but d i i may put it optional
in some cases so i may also say he sent her
a letter ok so so d the dependent may be optional
in certain cases
now the the word the head word it selects
my dependent d and it also determines further
the dependent is obligatory or not and in
some cases the form the grammatical form the
d takes will also dependent on my head so
this is also ah called the agreement or government
government in the case of linguistics so that
ah so like the the form that use for your
verb in in your construction will be similar
to the form of the subject and object that
we are using also with the linear position
of the dependent is specified with respect
to the head h
so so for example so ah so english follows
this as we are construct right so you get
the subject first then the verb then the object
so what we have seen the linear position of
the of the dependent is determined with respect
to the head so if i know the verb has come
so i know subject will come to the left and
object will come to the right like i want
to say sentence where i am saying i am eating
something who is eating the subject will come
on the left i eat and what do i eat say an
apple that will come on the right so the position
of the dependent it is specified with respect
to the head whether it is to the left or to
the right
now there are some cases that are clear where
you can easily find the dependencies so so
for example if i look at the exocentric and
endocentric constructions what do i mean by
endocentric and exocentric so endocentric
construction one where one of the identity
here can can actually fulfill the whole grammatical
function of the whole of the complete construction
so if you look at this verb and adverbial
relation verb modifier
so what is the example suddenly affected this
may doing some grammatical function suddenly
affected and why it is endocentric because
only one word here like affected can fulfill
the whole grammatical function for the whole
construction suddenly affected suddenly is
simply modifying that same way for non modifier
like financial markets so markets can fulfill
the grammatical function for whole thing financial
markets it's not the case for exocentric construction
like verb and subject
so if i take affect and the news affected
cannot fulfill the whole grammatical function
for news an affected i need to have the word
news so this is called exocentric endocentric
one word can fulfill the whole function exocentric
a single word cannot but the cases of exocentric
what will become the head and what will become
the dependent like if i have the verb and
subject i know that verb will become the head
and subject will become the dependent same
way verb and object verb becomes the head
and object becomes the dependent in the case
of endocentric again the particular word that
can fulfill the whole function can become
the head and the other word can become the
dependent so here verb is the head affected
and suddenly becomes the dependent similarly
here markets is the head and financial becomes
the dependent
now if you just try to compare what is the
difference between a phrase structure a representation
and dependency representation what we see
is that in phrase structure we have very explicitly
denoting what are the phrases these non terminal
nodes and labels in the case of dependency
relations what are the explicit denoting they
are words but what are the relation between
different words and what is the grammatical
category of each individual relation so in
the case of phrase structure i denote what
are phrases and what are the structural categories
like noun phrases verb phrases and so on in
the case of dependency structure what do i
represent what are the various head dependent
relations like in the case of directed arcs
and what are the functional categories that
are what are the different arc labels that
i am giving to various arcs in my dependent
relation
now formally can i define what is dependency
graph so i have to define it for ah the words
in my sentence so formally i can say that
the dependency structure can be defined as
a directed graph consisting of a set v of
nodes and a set of a of arcs now this is a
very generic way in which you define a graph
in a graph you have a set of nodes and set
of edges that are connected different nodes
now is there something more than this in the
case of dependency structure now in the case
of dependency structure so this is the labeled
graphs so what are the nodes in my graph the
nodes in the graph denote the word forms the
word that i that i am counting in my sentence
and with that i might also have some ah annotations
like what is the part of speech category of
these words i can also put in my nodes and
what are the edges they are labeled edges
with the dependence relations what is the
dependency time if it is subject object noun
modifier verb modifier etcetera
and some simple notations that we used for
this is that ah if i am saying that word w
i is connected to word w j with dependency
relation d i can use this arc w i d w j it
says that w i is the head w j is the dependent
and d is the relation ok so i can say ah eat
subject and i or he ok there is another way
in which i can note the arcs by saying this
is the headword this is the dependent word
i am denoting an arc from a head to dependent
word and putting a label on top of that this
is another way ok and this is equivalent to
saying w i d w j are in the set of arcs
there are some other conditions like ah if
i say that from i this relation from i to
j direct relation then i can i can write that
i j in my set of arcs so i am not writing
the dependency relation here but i am saying
i and j are in the set of my dependency relations
similarly i can do a closure of this saying
that i from i there is a there is path to
j ok so that means in any number of steps
i can go from i to j if and only if either
i and j's are equal or there is some case
such that i go from i to k and from k you
can go to j any number of cases this is simple
this is very standard way in which you define
the closure relations
so with the dependency labels i can define
a single dependency or i can also define a
closure of that so i hope this notation is
clear so once we have this notation what does
the total form of conditions that we can put
on the dependency graph so on the graphs so
that the denoted dependency graph for a sentence
what are the formal conditions
so what are the formal conditions so first
condition is that the dependency graph that
g that i get is connected ok by connected
what do i mean there is ah there is no node
in my graph that is isolated from the whole
graph or in other words if i take any any
word in my graph any node in my graph i can
always find a another nodes such that either
that node has an incoming link from that previous
node or an outgoing into that node ok so it
is connected to some of the node in the graph
attached it's not isolated so this is the
simple condition for saying when the graph
is connected
the second condition is that my graph is acyclic
there is no cycle in the graph so what do
i mean by that if i say that from a node i
i have a label i have a path or i have a dependency
from i to j there is no way i can have a path
from j to i so there is no way i can go back
to i if i am going from i to j i cannot go
from j to i either directly or by following
something k and this so this is not allowed
ok so because this will make a cyclic i to
j j to k k back to i so cycles are not allowed
in the case of dependency graph similarly
if i can if i can show the previous one that
means that if i take a node i in my graph
it should not happen that and they are connected
and i is isolated i can always find some nodes
such that either there is an incoming edge
or there is an outgoing edge one of these
they cannot be both right because of this
principle of a cyclicity
what is the third one third condition says
that my dependency graph g obeys the single
head constraint so what is single head constraint
so single head constraint means if i take
a node i in my graph they can be at most one
head for that ok so if i say that j is the
head for i so j is the head for i i cannot
find another k so the k is also head for i
this is not possible there will be only one
head for i node at most is called the single
head constraint
and then finally we have the fourth constraint
that is g is projective it says if from i
i can derive j and from j so i am using the
word derive here derive means from i ah i
is the head and i have the dependent j then
from j i have a dependent by some number of
edges k for any k such that j k lie on the
same side of i ok and this is the projectivity
constraint and what do we mean by that if
i were edge from i to j and from j i can have
in any number of steps i going to k then j
and k should lie on the same side of i so
that is
if i am saying this is my i and from here
i have this relation to node j ok let me just
project them i is here and j is here ok then
what i am saying is that if j connects to
any dependent either directly or indirectly
that k has to be on the right hand side only
so there are two possibilities suppose i am
taking direct connection i can connect to
k this is allowed or i can connect to a k
here ok so this denote the linear order in
the way they are occurring in the sentence
so i and j are here so k can occur either
here or here ok or anywhere else in the right
but what is not allowed is if j is related
to some k here that is not allowed because
now j and k are on the different side of i
ok so where whatever side j is k also should
be on the same side and if so if this situation
happens this is called non projectivity also
there is another term for that it is called
crossing of dependency edges so you are seeing
here this line and this line are crossing
here if i am if i am taking this particular
constraint while they do not cross if i take
this constraint or this constraint and you
can see if you can go any number of steps
they will not cross ok and this particular
constraint is called the projectivity constraint
now what is important is that this constraint
of projectivity is a many times dependent
on the particular language that you are choosing
for your dependency construction so it might
happen that there are certain languages that
do not follow this projectivity constraint
and some languages like english they very
they quite regularly follow this projectivity
constraint so this is like language dependent
so the methods that the the dependency parsing
methods that we will study in this week so
we will study one method that that needs projectivity
constraint another method that does not need
this constraint ok
so but yeah these four constraints are very
very important so that you can come up with
the good algorithm for a dependency parsing
of the sentence so yeah this is an example
of what is projectivity so if i have a link
from a to b i cannot have a link from b to
c because c is on the other side of a similarly
if i have a link from a to b i cannot have
a link from b to c ok because they are crossing
in general what do they mean these four conditions
so connectedness means that the syntactic
structure obtaining my dependency graph is
complete i am not having any isolated nodes
that are not connected to my whole structure
so in condition of acyclicity means that the
structure is hierarchical there is no cycles
inside
what is the single head constraint it says
that every word has at most one syntactic
head it cannot have more than one syntactic
head so or in other words we are saying it
is determined only by one word not by multiple
words right remember we were saying that ah
the linear position of a dependent sometimes
depends on the head so node one two different
heads to decide the position of the single
word and then they might be conflicts the
same word has only one head that determines
it's syntactic category and and in other things
ah there is no crossing of dependencies that
is the last constraint of projectivity that
we also saw
so now once we have these four constraints
what is my dependency parsing so this is how
i can define the dependency parsing i am given
a sentence x that contains words w one to
w n and i want to obtained a output as dependency
graph given this input of sequence of words
in my sentence i want to obtain my dependency
graph that follows that constraint that we
saw earlier ok so it is like single head constraint
and ah projectivity if i am imposing that
and all that so i want to obtain dependency
graph
so what are different methods that that we
will be using for this so we will we will
talk about different methods so like ah one
method will be deterministic parsing this
is a very very popular method then a method
based on maximum spanning tree and finally
you can also do it in a constraint propagation
method so in this course we will talk about
the first two methods and how you can use
that by having some sort of labeled data and
doing some learning from there so it's like
a data driven parsing and the final method
is something that you will use when if node
have any labeled data but you know what are
some of the constraints that your grammars
follows so can you can you encode those constraints
inside your dependency grammar and obtain
dependency graph for a given sentence so this
is good for the languages where if node have
a labeled data but you have the labeled data
in terms of dependency ah graphs you probably
go for a data driven approach so starting
from the next lesson we will start talking
about this data driven approaches for dependency
parsing
thank you