so welcome to the second lecture of this week
so we had started for our dependency parsing
formulation and we define what is the problem
and what are the very ah formal conditions
on a dependency graph in the last lecture
so we are given a input sentence i want to
obtain a dependency graph for that sentence
and further if we discuss that there are certain
ways we can handle this problem and in this
course we will mainly focus on the approaches
that you just that use some sort of labeled
data for this task
so it will be some sort of machine learning
task for finding out the dependency paths
for a new sentence so now so in the in the
next four lectures in this week i will cover
two different methods for the same problem
but before discussing the methods in detail
let me try to give you a basic intuition on
what we are trying to achieve and this will
also help you to understand that if you are
given a new problem and you want to take it
in a machine you want to solve it in a machine
learning based method then how you should
go about it ok
so so let me take this case so i have a sentence
that contains some words ok this is some arbitrary
sentence this is a new sentence i might not
have seen it before and my goal is to come
up with the dependency graph ok these are
nodes are different words and they have certain
relations r one r two etcetera are certain
relations ok this is my dependency graph so
i want to go from the sentence to my dependency
graph
now suppose i want to do it in a in some sort
of systematic manner by using some sort of
data so what i will do i will try to convert
that to some sort of configuration format
ok some initial configuration so that means
there will be a function that will take any
sentence as input and convert that to initial
configuration
now i will define some operations that i can
make on this initial configuration ok and
that will take me to some intermediate configuration
and i should be able to keep on doing this
operations until at some point of time i arrived
at a terminal configuration and terminal configuration
should be something that resembles a dependency
graph ok so my whole task is now starting
from the input sentence converted to a initial
configuration apply some well defined operations
and go to intermediate configuration until
you finally reach a terminal configuration
that may be deterministic may not be deterministic
so now so this is my whole thing this is my
sentence and this is my dependency graph and
operations are something i do not know but
i need to define i need to find out for a
particular configuration what are the operation
that i should take
now where does machine learning comes in here
so this looks like very deterministic what
is the problem the problem is they may not
be a single operation so i should have a way
to find out for the given configuration what
is the operation that i should take and that
i am trying to learn from the data that i
have so that's where the machine learning
comes in so we have data where we have a set
of sentences and their corresponding dependency
graphs ok
so there i can find out for what configuration
what was the operation that i had taken and
i will use that to learn for a new sentence
or a new configuration what operation i should
be taking so that given any new sentence i
can actually find out it's dependency graph
and this is just generic idea we will see
specifically how it will be used in the two
different methods that we will cover in this
course
so now the first method that we are going
to cover is a transition based parsing method
ok so so we will see it's formulation so what
is the basic idea so it's similar to the intuition
that i had provided earlier that is i have
to derive a a single syntactic representation
it's called the dependency graph via a deterministic
sequence of elementary parsing actions and
this is what we were saying as operations
i start with the sentence i keep on having
certain operations over that until i i arrive
at some dependency graph
so now in this particular case of transition
based parsing what what do i mean by a configuration
what do we mean by a configuration look like
so a configuration i will need a triple that
is s stack buffer and a set of arcs so that
is at any point i can define a configuration
in the configuration i will have a stack where
there will be some set of words that has been
partially processed then the buffer it will
contain words that are remaining and whatever
arcs i have already obtained via my ah operations
this will be in the set of arcs so at the
bottom of this slide you are seen one example
of a configuration
so this is for the sentence he sent her a
letter so this is the intermediate configuration
where you have the words sent her a in the
stack so you are partially processed at this
point the word letter and punctuation are
in the buffer they are remaining and there
is already an arc between the words he and
sent and he is the subject of the word sent
the verb sent so this is the intermediate
configuration
now how do i formally define my whole transition
system so formally so it will be very analogous
to what i started discussing ok so i need
to define what are my possible configurations
how do i go from a sentence to an initial
configuration and which configuration will
i call as a final configuration and what are
the operations i should make so that i can
transit from one configuration to another
configuration and that's why the name of transition
system also comes in so then formally we will
define dependency parsing transition system
as a quadruple that has c t c s and c t and
what are these capital c is a set of configurations
all the configuration that are possible
now capital t denotes a set of transitions
and each transition takes me from one configuration
to another configuration from c to c one configuration
in the set c to another configuration in the
set c now c s will be an initialization function
that you will give a sentence as input and
you will find the initial configuration as
output and then you will have a set of terminal
configurations so that means whenever you
reach a terminal configuration via your operations
you will stop anyway call it as your dependency
graph
now whenever you are given a sentence x what
is my transition sequence so it's sequence
will be a set of configurations it's starting
from c zero to c m and what are the conditions
on those c zero is something that you can
derive from the sentence ok so suppose x is
the sentence that you are giving as a input
and you want to find out it's dependency graph
so now what is the idea you have a function
initialization function you have apply that
function over x and you get a transition sorry
you get a configuration c zero
now you keep on applying various operations
and get c one c two up to c m and c m is in
the set of terminal configurations ok this
is my initialization function set of terminal
configurations and c zero to c m all are in
the set of configurations and what is the
relation between any two conjugative c i and
c i plus one relation would be i can obtained
c i plus one by making a transition over c
i ok for some transition i have defined in
my set capital t so this is my process it
starts with the sentence apply the initial
initialization function get the initial configuration
keep on applying by a various transitions
until you obtain a terminal configuration
ok
now as per the transition system that we have
defined what will be the initialization initialization
will be simple so i have to define what is
my s stack what is my buffer and what are
my arcs because whenever when i am starting
with the sentence w one to w n ok initially
my structure contain the set of partially
processed words so there is nothing that is
processed right now so my stack will be empty
my buffer should contain the set of remaining
input words so remaining words are all the
words w one to w n and my arc should contain
whatever dependency relation i have already
found so it will be empty this will be empty
set so this is my initialization
now what will be the terminal configuration
a termination so the idea is i should not
have any words remaining in the buffer so
my buffer should be empty so terminal condition
i can define as stack would have some may
or may not some words buffer should be empty
and i will have obtained a set of arcs so
this is important my buffer should be empty
a stack may or may not contain some words
and arcs will have some dependency relations
already
so now once you know what is my initial configuration
what is my termination condition now what
is remaining in this ah in this whole thing
we know all the possible set of configurations
so what is remaining is what are all all the
possible transitions that i can take for going
from one configuration to another configuration
how can i move from initial configuration
by a sequence of operations so that i arrive
at a terminal configuration ok
so now in this system there are four transitions
that have been defined ok so that means for
any configuration you can take one of these
four four transitions so in this slide i am
showing you the four transitions different
transitions that you can take so how you should
read it so in the left the names of the transitions
left arc right arc for a dependency d reduce
and shift these are the four transitions possible
now for each transitions like left arc you
will have what is the configuration that is
the input to that of with which you are starting
on top and what is the configuration that
you will end up with a starting from this
configuration if you apply a left arc what
configuration you will arrive at and finally
in the right if there is something that is
a condition what is the condition under which
you can apply this transition this is just
a necessary condition you need to have this
conditions satisfied to be able to apply this
transition
so for example if i see the left arc transition
what does it say it says that i can apply
it when there is stack contain some words
and i have been shown here the last word in
the stack i can also call it the top of this
stack the word is s i buffer contains some
words w j it is starting from w j top of buffer
is w j and i have some set of arcs now what
do i mean by left arc left arc means i making
a transition from w j to w i yes this is the
left arc because the words are occurring in
the in the same order that they occur in the
sentence
so there is a arc from w j to w i so what
is the head here w i is the head and dependent
is sorry w j is the head and w i is the dependent
ok so now there is also a condition here w
i should not already have a head and let us
try to understand this condition so what am
i saying my stack contains some words and
and top is w i buffer contains some words
starting from w j and i making a left arc
so the left arc as the name says it will be
from buffer to s stack and we are we have
always operating on the top words in buffer
and stack
so i making an arc from the top word in buffer
to the top word in s stack this is the left
arc now what is the condition condition is
w i should not already have a head now why
is this condition just see here i am if i
am making this transition we are saying that
the w j is the head of w i now if w i already
has a head i cannot apply this why can you
see what what particular condition in dependency
parse does it violate so dependency parse
has a single head constraint ok so it is a
single head constraint so that says each word
can have at most one head so if w i already
has a head then i cannot apply this particular
transition ok so that is left arc can be applied
only if w i does not already have a head
now suppose if i apply a left arc now i start
with a configuration like that what is my
real thing configuration so real thing configuration
would be i will remove w i from the s stack
ok it will contain all the words except w
i buffer will remain as it is and my arcs
will be i have got a new arc what is that
w j dependent each w this is my new arc ok
so i have removed w i from my s stack now
you might have this question ah why am i removing
w i from the s stack if the word is removed
i cannot put it back so i can remove a word
from the s stack only if i am sure that all
it's relations have already been captured
now so the question here is can this word
w i have anymore relations with any words
so if w i has any relation with the words
that occurs before w i it would already have
been captured at this point because these
are already partially processed words so the
only relation w i might have is with any words
after w j
now let's take a scenario take a word a w
k ok now what kind of relation w i might have
with w k it can be either an incoming arc
or it can be an outgoing arc ok now can it
can have an incoming arc from w k it cannot
yes because it can have only one single one
head so this is not possible now what is the
other condition that can it have ah outgoing
arc to some word w k now what do you think
about it is that possible now if you think
again about the formal conditions that we
are defined what condition is it violating
remember the condition on projectivity if
there is a relation from j to i then from
i the next dependent can be only on this side
of j it cannot be on that side of j ok so
this has to be either in between that is not
possible or here ok so so this is also not
a possibility so that means w i cannot have
any further relations so that's why we can
remove w i from the s stack and this my s
stack and this contain everything other than
w i buffer remains the same
now let us look at the ah second transition
right arc so now right arc is you are making
a relation from w i to w j w i is the head
and w j is the dependent there is no conditions
that you have to see here and when you apply
this particular transition what do you obtain
w j goes to the s stack so i do not remove
w i and w j goes to the s stack and i get
a new arc ok so now again you can try to think
here why we didn't remove w i from the s stack
ah why we didn't remove w j from the buffer
and remove it all together why we are not
doing that and try to think in terms of the
constraints that we are put over our dependency
parsing ok and we will come up with some nice
ah intuitions that why we are defining the
transitions in this particular manner so we
have seen we have seen the justification for
the previous case now try to justification
for yourself for this case but here the the
difference is that now the transition is from
w i to w j and accordingly i am getting a
new arc
then we have two more transitions reduce and
shift what is reduce in reduce i remove the
the top word from the s stack and the condition
is w i already has a head if w i already has
a head i can remove that and finally the fourth
transition is shift what is that i take the
top word on the buffer and shift it to the
top of s stack and these are the four transitions
now the the main thing here is when you are
at a particular configuration you might be
able to take more than one of these operations
or transitions and your task could be to find
out what is the transition that i should take
in a particular scenario so i hope the four
transitions are clear ah
let us see a particular example and how we
do apply these transitions so we will take
a very simple example so what we will have
we will have a sentence he sent her a letter
and we also know the dependency parse of this
sentence now once you are given the sentence
and it's actual dependency parse that you
want to obtain you have to find out what are
the transitions that i should that you should
be taking at each intermediate or initial
configuration so that you can end up with
the dependency graph so let us do this exercise
so here this is my sentence he sent her a
letter and there is also a punctuation mark
how do we start find out what is the initial
configuration now how do we convert this sentence
to the initial configuration s stack would
be empty buffer would contain all the words
and arcs would be empty and that is what initial
configuration s stack is empty buffer contains
all the words and arcs is empty now your task
is starts this is the initial configuration
now what is the transition that you must be
taking here so so this one is relatively easy
i cannot do left arc left arc means say arc
from he to a word in s stack there is no word
in s stack they cannot be any dependency relation
similarly right arc is not possible because
there is no word on the top of s stack i cannot
be reduce because again there is no word in
the on the top of s stack so the only transition
possible is shift i can take the top word
in the buffer and move that to to the stack
and this is what i will do i will take the
transition as shift
so if i do right how do i modify my configuration
so if i do a shift he will go from buffer
to the s stack and that is what i will obtain
now now this is my configuration now again
you defined out what is the transition that
he must be taking at this point and that's
where you will look at the dependency graph
that you want to obtain and you will see is
there any relation you want to establish between
the top of s stack and top of buffer so in
the parse we are seeing he is a subject for
sent that means you can establish a relation
between sent and he and what will be that
it should be from sent to he so it should
be a left arc relation so that means i can
take a left arc transition at this point and
if i take a left arc what will be the output
configuration i will remove he from the s
stack buffer will remain as it is and arcs
i will get one more arc and that is what is
my next configuration s stack is empty buffer
contains the remaining words and i have one
arc obtained
now you are at this configuration now what
is the transition you should take again whenever
stack is empty the only transition possible
is shift so i will do a shift ok now i have
one word in the in that stack sent and there
are some word in the buffer her a and letter
now what is the transition you can take at
this point again you will try to have a look
at the dependency parse you will see if this
is relation between sent and her yes her is
a dependent and sent is a modifier sorry sent
is the head so what is this transition from
sent to her it will be a right arc so i will
take a right arc transition and what will
be the output of the right arc the word her
should go the s stack and i will get a new
relation in my arcs so this will be my configuration
at this point i have the words sent and her
in the s stack a and letter in buffer and
i got the arcs
now am i at the point where i have some words
in the s stack i have some words in the buffer
and now i have to see what is the transition
i should be taking care so let us have a look
can i take a left arc or right arc you see
her and a are not related in my dependency
parse so i cannot take left arc or right arc
now what are the possibilities the possibilities
are i can either take a reduce or shift these
both are possible now how do i choose between
reduce and shift and there is a rule of thumb
for choosing between rule shift and reduce
and the idea is if you find the danger word
in the stack not on the top just they were
before the top any words before the top of
the s stack that connects to that word on
the top of the buffer you do reduce otherwise
shift of course you can do reduce only if
you have already found the head for their
word
so in this case should i take reduce or shift
let us take this this rule of thumb is there
a word in the stack below her that connects
to the top of buffer there is not so i cannot
take reduce i should take shift so if i do
shift that is what i get i take a shift i
now have sent her a letter now once i made
this configuration what is the next transition
i will take this time it is easy there is
a relation between letter and a this should
be left arc left arc means i removing
so now again i am here there is no relation
between her and letter so now so that means
you can choose between reduce and shift so
use the rule of thumb again is there a word
below the top in the stack that connects to
the top of buffer and you will see yes the
word sent in the s stack connects to the word
letter in the buffer so here you can do reduce
and you do reduce and you have the word sent
in the s stack and letter and punctuation
in the buffer now is there any relation yes
there should be a right arc relation so right
arc means letter will go to the s stack yes
again there is no relation between letter
and dot the punctuation what should i take
is there relation between any other word in
s stack with the buffer yes sent and punctuation
are related so i will do a reduce here now
sent and punctuation are related by right
arc and by right arc i will take the dot to
the s stack ok and this is my configuration
now what do you see should i go any further
ah once i have reach this configuration and
you will say no because what is the condition
terminal configuration the condition is that
my buffer should be empty so at this point
my buffer is already empty so that means i
have arrived at a terminal configuration and
that's where i i will stop and i have obtained
all the possible set of arcs for this sentence
so now this is an example we have seen just
to understand how to take all these transitions
but ah does that help you to solve this problem
whenever you are giving a new sentence why
a new sentence i mean you do not know dependency
graph or or you might also ask if i already
know the dependency parse for a sentence what
is the need for doing all these transitions
and that's where the the concept of learning
will come into picture so we have seen here
if we know the dependency graph we can choose
the configurations ok at run time whenever
i am given a sentence my whole task is to
find out what are the transitions i should
be taking at different configuration and this
i will learn from my already labeled data
and this is what we will discuss in detail
in the next lecture that is how do i use how
do i use this concept to define it as a learning
problem and for a new sentence how do i come
up with a dependency graph
thank you