welcome back for the third lecture of this
week so in the last lecture we had defined
what is the notion of our transition based
parsing and we we saw what are the configuration
that i should i should have what are transitions
i can take and how do i come up with a final
dependency graph and we took an example and
showed what are the transitions you can take
and how you should be taking the transitions
and then we ended with saying that how i will
be using that for getting parse for a new
sentence ok so this is something that we had
ah initially asked
so i have some sentence s s i can find out
what initial configuration is why the function
i keep on taking some transitions go to some
intermediate configuration until i obtain
terminal configuration and i said with the
data i will have some sentences and their
corresponding dependency parsing and from
there i will try to learn what are the operations
of transitions i am where to take now in this
lecture we will see for a particular problem
how we will be doing the learning part
so again let me start by giving you the basic
intuition so what will be the basic intuition
so in the last lecture you had learned that
for a sentence if you know the dependency
graph so this is my labeled data if you know
that you can run through the steps very very
easily the steps of transitions so you can
say that this is my initial configuration
and you can find out what is the transition
i should take say it is shift so you can store
somewhere this is my initial configuration
c zero and this is the transition then by
taking this transition you will go to some
other configuration c one what is the transition
it may be left arc ok again some c two it
can be shift and so on ok some c m it can
be shift or something
so this given a sentence you can easily run
through these steps and find out and what
is this c i c i is nothing but a some words
in stack some words in buffer and something
in my arc that is my c i so that means suppose
i am given a set of sentences and their dependency
graph i can store all the possible set of
configuration and all the possible by all
the possible i mean whatever i obtaining from
these sentences and their corresponding transitions
ok
and this i can have a last set so i will have
a set of all possible c i and that optimal
transition that i should be taking and c i's
of this form something in stack and something
in buffer arc now what is my problem at run
time at run time i am given a sentence s i
do not know it's dependency parse ok so i
start my transition i converted to some initial
configuration c zero that is easy of the function
of converting to initial configuration there
i have to find out what is the transition
i should take now what will be the idea i
will try to use this set of ah data that i
have i know for what configurations what transitions
word taken in my gold standard or in my ah
set of labeled data set so i will try to find
out so before going into what this is the
machine learning ah approach we will use so
what will be intuitive idea try to find out
what are the closest configurations in the
set and for those closest configurations what
transition was taken and i will try to use
that t star from there
suppose i find out the t star is the transition
that was taken to the closest configuration
here so i will use t star and once i know
this t star i can transit it to next one c
one again the question will come what is the
transition i should take so again go back
to this and choose t dash take this go to
c two keep on doing that until you will come
up with the final configuration c m and that's
why you say this is the dependency graph for
s and this is the intuitive idea in the last
lecture we have seen how do come up with this
set and today we will see how do i how do
i approach this problem so that i can come
up with this function that what is the closest
configuration from here to here what is the
transition that i should take it
so so one important idea that we had already
discussed earlier in this course is that for
example how do you find out the closest configuration
and what is the transition that we are taking
this you have to use by using a some sort
of classifier that is you are trying to classify
for a given configuration among all the four
transitions which transitions will be taken
so you are as a four class classification
problem at each point you are trying to classify
among one of the four classes and how are
you going to classify you have to convert
your input data in some representation so
this will be using some feature representation
so you will have to convert your configuration
into some sort features feature vector and
for those features you have to learn the weights
and this weight you have to learn by the training
examples again and once you have learn the
optimal weights you can find out what is the
transition at at any given point and this
is what we will be discussing in this lecture
so let us see
so now we are talking about the data driven
deterministic parsing so so i have written
here certain things like deterministic parsing
requires in oracle what do i mean by oracle
so oracle is nothing but the set of configurations
and the set of transition that i took ok so
this you have already seen in the last lecture
how do you find out configuration and transitions
now what we are going to do we want to approximate
it by a classifier so we will be learning
classifier from there and it will be trained
using the treebank data so whatever data we
have in the gold standard label data we will
use that to train our classifier also so you
will use that label data for two different
tasks first for building the ah oracle configuration
transition configuration transition second
to learn the weights of my classifier ok
now what is the learning problem now as we
said we will be given a configuration as a
input and we want to find out what is the
transition i should be taking at a particular
configuration so ideally i want to approximate
the function that takes a configuration which
is represented by a feature vectors two transitions
so configuration to transitions here configuration
is nothing but a feature vector form because
otherwise how do you compare between two configurations
so that's why you will take give it a very
exact representation in terms of ah some feature
vector form and you will learn a function
from feature vector to the optimal transition
and this is this will be your classifier and
how will you learn that you will be given
a training set of gold standard transition
sequences that we already have seen
so now to completely solve this problem or
to completely understand this problem there
are three issues that you need to understand
first is how do i represent configuration
by a feature vector second how do i derive
training data from my treebanks and third
is how do i learn my classifiers so let us
try to answer each of these three questions
so how do i represent configuration by by
feature vectors and this is something that
we had done earlier in the class that how
do i convert a a given state or represent
to a feature vector
so what is my configuration my configuration
is nothing but a stack buffer and arcs and
i want to convert that to some feature vector
and feature vector again here we will take
it a very simple form like f c t it is a function
over the configuration and the transition
and we will try to define features independent
of transition so each feature that we define
can have four copies four four different transitions
so f c t one f c t two f c t three f c t four
like that so so what are the different things
that i can use in feature so i can use things
like what is the word at top of this stack
what is the word at top of buffer they are
very important
what is the word here then i may want to use
what is the part of speech tag of these words
because sometimes some relations would might
might directly dependent on whether it is
a verb and it is a noun then there might be
a relation otherwise not so i might use the
part part of speech tag i might go to the
lemma i might want to use what is the distance
between this word and this word in the actual
sentence i might also want to use what are
neighbors here i might want to use what are
relations that i have already been established
with this word or this word ok so that means
i will define certain conditions over stack
buffer and arcs and that will i would like
to take my features
and again these can be some binary questions
that i am asking so that is is the distance
between these two words between two to five
yes or no ok so like that these can be my
condition that is my features and i will define
it for all the four transitions
so let us look at what are the different feature
models we can take in general so i am representing
configuration c by a vector of simple features
so like i can use the nodes so what is the
top of this stack what is the head of buffer
i can use the linear context that is what
are the neighbors in s stack of the top word
what are the neighbors in buffer of the top
word then i might also use what are the parents
children siblings depending on what relations
are already been established in my set of
arcs
then i can go to some other attributes like
i can use the word form i can use also it's
lemma and we can use them up part of speech
tag and various other features for example
is the is the word on top of stack ends with
e d or i n g things like that and i might
be able to use the dependency type if i am
handling a labeled dependency problem so so
yeah just a word what do i mean by labeled
dependency problem that means i also want
to find out for two words what is the dependency
relation label and if i am solving unlabeled
problem that means i want to just want to
establish a relation but i am not concern
with the actual dependency type
so i am not worried about putting the label
on the arc but just the structure of the tree
so if i am solving label problem i might also
have to see what is the relation type that
i am establishing and we will also see the
distance between different tokens as one of
the features so these are some typical examples
but it doesn't mean that you are limited only
to using this set of features and as i keep
on seeing for your particular task you might
have to think what might be some interesting
features that you you can use
so by using all these features i am putting
my binary questions i can represent my configuration
as a in terms of a feature representation
so this is my first question now what was
the second question now how do i use this
at run time but actually find the ah parse
of the sentence idea would be something like
that so let me start from here at run time
you are given a sentence w one to w n ok and
you can always go to the initial configuration
where the buffer is sorry s stack is empty
buffer contains all the words and arc is empty
ok now this is your configuration and you
are in a loop while the buffer is not empty
you keep on taking some transitions now this
is the task say run time so this configuration
c you know how to covert to the to a feature
vector because you are defined your features
so you can ask the questions at this point
and find out your vector f c t
now what is my classifier my classifier is
simple i have learned the weights of my features
assume that i have learned we will see how
to learn the weights so once i have learned
the weights of my features i will multiply
the weights with f c t and find out what is
the particular transition that is giving the
maximum value that means i know what is my
f c t feature vector and i know my this is
my f c t and this is my weights so now at
run time i am given a configuration c and
i need to find out what is the optimal transition
how do i do that an idea is that i will multiply
w with f c t i for all the four transitions
so t i is shift left arc reduce and right
arc and i will take which one gives the maximum
value argmax over t i so at run time any configuration
i can convert to f c t very easily i will
already have the weight vectors the only thing
that i have to do multiply the weight vector
with the feature vector find out four different
values four different transitions choose the
maximum or choose the transitions that has
gives the maximum value that is the transition
you will take and then if you go back this
is the transition you take and then apply
this transition over this configuration to
find the next configuration and keep on going
in this loop until your buffer is empty and
this is what your run time
now what is not clear to you right now is
how do we learn these weights right everything
else is clear so let us see so so learning
weights we will have to use the labeled data
that we have is the training data now let
us see what are the steps that we need to
do over the training data now training data
i will have the instances of this form f c
and t is this clear entering data we will
have configurations and transitions yes and
configuration i know what is the feature representation
so i convert the feature vector so i can have
f c and t f c is nothing but the feature representation
of the configuration c and t is the correct
transition out of ah it starting from c and
this i can for obtain from my oracle remember
in oracle i had my configuration and the optimal
transition so i know this configuration what
is the transition it should take so from there
i go to next step f c and t ok
now now this is something that we have done
in the last class but let me try to repeat
that again that how do we sample this oracle
function from the set of labeled ah sentences
labeled of dependency graph so for each sentence
x with the gold standard dependency graph
g x you have to construct a transition sequence
right like we did in the last class for the
example he sent her a letter such that c zero
will something that will obtained by applying
the initialization function on on x and this
is the final dependency graph ok now for each
intermediate configuration we will construct
a training instance so right we will have
c i t i c i t i and c i will go to f c i and
this is the condition for how are am i moving
in from one configuration to another configuration
so this is the same thing that that i have
discussed earlier in today's lecture that
what is the idea is starting from the gold
standard sentence and dependency graph find
out this sequence c i t i c i t i now the
only addition here is i covert each c i to
it's feature representation so that's why
i what i have i have f c i t i f c i t i
and how do you sample ah the transitions in
oracle this is something again that we did
in the last class so if you see that in my
dependency graph the current top of the word
in the stack is connected to the top of the
word in buffer so you will have a relation
depending on the direction it will be left
arc or right arc so here if the top of the
word in buffer is the head and this is the
dependent you make a left arc transition so
this is what you will store if top word in
the in the stack is head then you will have
a right arc relation yes then how do you choose
between reduce and shift if there is a word
below that of the stack such that it is connect
to the first word in the buffer then you do
reduce otherwise you shift and remember this
is that we discussed in the last lecture if
you are between reduce and shift this is the
condition that you can use
so ok so so i hope the the idea is clear you
are starting with the sentence in training
data you have the gold standard dependency
graph you keep on going through your transitions
and store it somewhere f c i t i f c i t i
f c i t i now how do i use that to learn the
weights now and this is the idea of learning
the weights so so what you will do you will
start with some initial set of weights so
so here i have said all the weights can be
initialized to zero but probably not will
zero you can initialize with some other numbers
say ah some initial random numbers or some
uniform numbers you initialize your weights
with now what are you going to do so there
are two loops here for i is one to k this
is the number of iterations that you are doing
for j in one to n one to n is the all the
set of sentences that you have in you are
training data so you are doing multiple iterations
over your training data
in j iteration what do we do you take the
sentence yes you get the initial configuration
fine now while buffer is not empty so so what
you are doing right now you are again repeating
the same stuff over each sentence in the training
data ok you start with the initial configuration
and now try to find the transition as per
your current weights so so that's where the
idea of learning comes in
so let me try to explain it here so so you
have a sentence s s now you can apply the
c s x function or and you go to initial configuration
c zero now you take a transition to go to
c now this is your sentence in your training
data that means you know what is the transition
you should take yes but i want to use this
idea to learn and how do i do that now suppose
that you are actually at the run time at testing
time so then you do not know the transition
so you will convert that to some feature vector
f c t ok now it run time how do you find out
the optimal transition multiplied with the
weights and take the argmax and let us say
this is t star this you can do that even if
it is in the training set and let us call
it t naught optimal transition
now what is the idea you are still in the
learning stage so your weights will not be
optimal so when you do this operation you
may not get the optimal transition you may
get something else and that's where you will
try to adopt your weights so you will say
if t star not equal to t zero then you update
your weights and how will you update your
weights such that you go in the direction
of the actual transition and away from the
transition of the the transition that you
obtain at the current point so simple thing
is w new would be w old plus f c t zero minus
f c t start so going in the direction of the
optimal transition and away from the transition
that you are currently ah predicting and there
can be some learning rate and all that we
are not ah discussing right now so there will
be some learning weights by which you will
do this update so you will have now new weights
again you keep on doing it for c one c one
you know what is the transition optimal transition
but you will find out argmax t start match
with this if they are not the same you will
again update your weights so you will keep
keep on doing that for all the sentences s
one to s n in your training set and you will
do it one two some k times until the weights
are converging so once the weights converged
we stop so this is what we have shown here
so you start for each sentence you have some
initial configuration while buffer is not
empty so you keep on doing the stuff find
out what is the optimal transition as per
your weights find the optimal transition from
the oracle if they are not matching update
your weights but you take the correct transition
so the next time you are starting with correct
configuration keep on repeating it and finally
you will end up with new set of weights ok
so now to further understand that let us take
a an example and that will make it clear to
you that how the learning or how the weight
updation takes place so so this is simple
example so i have a sentence john saw mary
so what do you need to do first question is
draw a dependency graph for this sentence
that is very easy yes now the next question
says that you are using the data driven dependency
parsing the same method that we have discussed
in this lecture and in the last lecture and
you already have the gold standard parse in
your training data and you have some other
information like john and mary are nouns and
saw is verb and also given you features and
you are told that initialize your weights
to five except that for left arc the weights
are five point five define your feature vector
and the initial weight vector so let us try
to do this
so how many conditions are we seen we are
seeing three conditions over my configuration
the stack is empty top of stack is noun and
top of buffer is verb top of stack is verb
and top of buffer is noun three conditions
now these three conditions i have to check
for all the four different transitions so
how many ah what is the size of my feature
vector three into four twelve so my feature
vector
so it's of twelve dimension and what are my
features so first feature let me write it
simply condition one that is the stack is
empty and same as starting with left arc transition
is left arc second feature can be condition
two and left arc third condition three and
left arc yes this is my f c t a condition
over the configuration and transition first
three elements next three elements same c
one but now transition will change still right
arc c two right arc c three right arc and
then the next elements c one reduce c two
reduce c three reduce and here c one shift
c two shift c three shift so this is my feature
vector twelve elements here
now what is my weight vector initial weight
vector we said all the elements are zero sorry
are five except the left arc is five point
five so the weights are five point five five
point five five point five and everything
else is five point o five point o and so on
that is your initial weight vector and your
task is now so this was the first question
what is my dependency parse john saw mary
so saw is here john and mary this is subject
and this is object now let us see what what
the question says further
so the next question the question says use
this gold standard parse during online learning
and report the weights after completing one
full iteration of arc eager parsing so it
says that now you have to learn the weights
using the arc eager parsing or the transition
parsing that we have seen so ok
so now let let us see how do we learn the
weights so so this is what we have defined
right now we have this features we have this
weights initially as per dependency graphs
so how will i start learning in learning i
will take this sentence i will put it to the
initial configuration initial configuration
is what this stack is empty buffer contains
john saw and mary and arc is empty so now
at this configuration c i have to choose what
is the optimal transition as per my classifier
and i have to choose the optimal transition
as per my oracle from oracle what will be
t zero oracle i will be very easily saying
that this would be shift i am doing a shift
at this point i should shift here but what
is being predicted by my classifier so let
us see what will be t star as per my classifier
so for my classifier how do i obtain t star
so t star would be argmax w times f c t for
all possible transitions so let us do one
by one so what will be f c l a what is the
feature vector when the transition is l a
so for that let us look at my feature vector
definition so this will be a binary value
at each point c one and l a what is c one
top of the stack is this stack is empty so
c one is one and transition is left arc so
this will be one c two top of stack is noun
and top buffer is verb now top of stack is
empty it cannot contain a noun so c two is
zero so already this will be zero c three
again say top of stack is verb and top of
buffer is noun again this will be zero ok
that's why i fill in my my feature vector
now let us go to this now immediately as you
move to some other transition r a this should
be zero yes because here your transitions
is l a so everything else will be zero twelve
elements ok now what is your weight vector
weight vector is here say if you multiply
weight vector with f c l a what do you get
so w times f c l a is equal to one so only
one element is one so i will multiply with
that this will give you five point five ok
now similarly now you can easily figure out
what are the other features f c r a for r
a similarly only this element will be one
everything else will be zero so what is w
times f c r a that will be five and similarly
if you keep on doing for all shift and reduce
you will find this for shift is five and this
for reduce is five yes
so now what is your t star argmax t w times
f c t that's will be left arc and what is
your t zero optimal is shift as per your oracle
and how do you learn your weights if t star
is not the same as t zero you will update
your weights and what is the late update w
plus f c t zero minus f c t star so what is
f c t zero that is f c s h so what will be
this function so suppose so s h was at the
end so it was one zero zero and everything
else is zero and this is my l a so what will
be the new weight vector so i have the original
weight vector that is this one plus this minus
this so what will be the new weight vector
it will be i am i am subtracting one here
so four point five five point five five point
five five point zero five point zero five
point zero five point zero five point zero
five point zero and now i come to shift in
shift i am adding that one so it will be six
point zero five point zero five point zero
and that is your new weight vector ok
and now you will verb with this weight vector
for the next set of configuration so what
will be the next configuration from here you
will apply shift and next configuration will
be john saw mary and phi again you will convert
it to the feature vector see what are the
what is t star that you are getting what is
t zero if they are not matching update your
weights and that you will continue until you
arrive at the terminal configuration and then
you will have the final weight vectors so
i i encourage all of you that you should try
it this full example on your own and see what
is the final weight vector that you are ah
getting and even if you are trying to see
that by using this weight vector does that
help in that now with the new weight vector
if you try it on the old configuration you
will actually attain the you will you will
be closer to the optimal configuration as
per the oracle and not what your classical
early updating
so so this is the idea of how you can use
the machine machine learning methods for this
dependency parsing by taking this example
of arc eager of transition based parsing now
in the next lecture we will we will start
discussion on a new method of dependency parsing
and we will see that again how we can use
the label data for for doing this ok
thank you