welcome back for the fourth lecture of this
week so in the last two lectures we had discussed
a particular dependency parsing that was a
transition based parsing method and we had
discussed how we can formulate parsing as
a particular particular problem where we starting
with a initial configuration and moving from
one configuration rather by using various
transitions and we modeled or learned these
transitions using some training data that
we already had so this was a data driven approach
now in this lecture we will talk about another
data driven approach here so the one main
difference from the previous one is that we
do not assume that projectivity constraint
over the dependency graph so in the last ah
method that we had covered we were assuming
that the dependency graph that we want should
be projective although later on there are
some variations proposed where this constraint
is is not required so you might if you want
to look into those so coming to what we are
going to discuss in today's lecture and in
the next lecture so this is the approach using
where we are formulating dependency parsing
as a problem of finding maximum spanning tree
now what is the basic idea so we are starting
with the sentence that is given to me so this
is the sentence for which i want to find the
dependency graph and how do we formulate the
problem firstly think about the sentence as
a set of nodes these are the words and assume
that all the possible nodes are connected
to each other we will also include a additional
node called root so that we can find out what
is the main head of this sentence now once
we start by assuming all possible connections
my problem is to find out what is the maximum
spanning tree from this all all the connections
that i can build and this i would assume corresponds
to my dependency graph and the weights etcetera
that will define for this graph will be learned
by using some training data that will be available
to me
so the the main idea here is i am given a
dependency graph so i start with a sentence
john saw mary and i i assume an additional
node like root assume that initially everything
is connected so from root there are all possible
connections to all that node and each node
has an incoming and an outgoing edge with
respect to every other node how do we learn
these edge weights this is something that
we will discuss but assume that the weights
are already given to you now your problem
would be how do i find out what is the maximum
spanning tree from this graph and this suppose
this is the maximum spanning tree then this
is what i will assume corresponds to my dependency
graph so my problem is starting from here
to come up with the maximum spanning tree
that might be dependency graph [vocalized
noise]
so now starting with some simple reminders
from graph theory on what is a maximum spanning
tree so ah you are now now familiar with what
is a graph so when i say graph this is a set
of v that is set of vertices and a set of
arcs ok so arcs generally connect to different
nodes in the graph and i so arc is connecting
to nodes i and j both i and j are in the set
v now if i talk about undirected graph like
the figure on the left so if i say that i
and j are in the set of arcs then j and i
are also there there is no directions in this
in this set of arcs
but if i see that my graph is directed then
if i and j are in the ah set of arcs then
j and i may not be in the set of arcs ok like
here i have a connection from this node to
this node but no connection from this node
to this node so now so we so what is a simple
graph and directed and what is a directed
graph directed graph can also be written as
a digraph now we can also see what is a multi
digraph a multi digraph what would happen
between a set of vertices there might be more
than one possible arcs like here you are seeing
between this node and this node there are
three different arcs so that's why you will
have an additional ah index saying i j and
k between the nodes i and j what is the kth
arc ok so it's similar to the previous one
except that between two vertices you can have
more than one arcs
now once we know what is a multi digraph let
me define the notion of what is the directed
spanning tree of the multi digraph so once
i start with the multi digraph that is set
of nodes v and there is a a sub graph g prime
that is some v prime a prime is called a directed
spanning tree if the following conditions
are followed what are the conditions in the
directed spanning tree the number of the set
of nodes are the same as the set of nodes
in the origin[al] original graph
so i will have to take the all the nodes from
the original graph ok so now what what do
i do with the edges so the set of arcs that
i take in g prime is the subset of the original
set of arcs with the constraint that the number
of edges that i have now is equivalent to
number of nodes minus one ok and the third
condition is the the graph g prime is a tree
it's there is no cycle in the graph
so let's take a example so i have two different
multi digraphs that are given in the first
and second figure and you are being shown
a directed spanning tree for this multi digraphs
so what do you see here so it has the same
number of nodes as were there in the original
multi digraph and what about the number of
connections so you see there are one two three
four and five connections and number of nodes
are one two three four five six so number
of connections are exactly number of nodes
minus one and you can take any possible ah
any possible five connections in among these
nodes such that there is no cycle and it will
called a directed spanning tree
now once we know what is directed spanning
tree we can also define what is a weighted
directed spanning tree so here what we will
do in my graph with all the arcs i will also
associate a weight so each arc is now labeled
or weighted by some numerical value and this
i will call at w i j k for the i between the
vertices i and j what is the weight for the
kth arc so in w i j superscript k is the weight
of the edge i j k now i will also define what
is the weight of my directed spanning tree
so this will be simply summation over the
weights of all the edges in my directed spanning
tree so from my multi digraph i find a directed
spanning tree definition was already covered
in the previous slide
now whatever edges i am obtaining i will find
out the weights for each of these and sum
over them and that will define the weight
of my directed spanning tree now the idea
here is for a for a given starting from a
given multi digraph you can obtain a number
of different directed spanning trees so your
problem is to find out which of these has
the maximum weight so now i by this concept
of weighted spanning tree i have also define
what is the weight of the directed spanning
tree so now among all the possibilities i
will find out the one that is having the maximum
weight
so it's starting from the graph g let us say
t g is the set of all the possible spanning
trees that i can obtained so like this is
this is an example this ah multi digraph is
given and there are these four possible spanning
trees so these are all directed spanning trees
now i have to find out which of these has
the maximum weight so this is my m s t problem
finding the spanning tree g prime of the graph
g that has the maximum weight and the weight
is written simply as summation over the weights
of all the edge of that graph ok so i find
out all the edges of that graph sum over the
weights and that will give me the weight of
the final graph
so now my problem is from my sentence whenever
i construct a multi digraph that is all the
possible connections a fix set of directed
spanning trees are possible now among those
which is having the highest weight and that
is the one that i will say as the my dependency
graph so now there are there are many questions
like ah how do i convert a sentence to an
initial configuration analogous to what we
did in the previous method then the important
problem here is how do we define the weights
of my edges and once i define the weights
how do i choose the maximum spanning tree
so these are three different problems and
then that's what we will be studying in this
lecture and in the next
so now for the sentence how do i find the
maximum spanning tree so let us see this is
the first problem how do i convert the sentence
to the initial configuration from where i
can start so what is that for each sentence
x you define the directed graph g x as v x
e x that is given by v x contains and additional
load like root and all the all the words that
occur in my sentence x and what are my edges
i i have all possible edges except for the
same node i do not have any self edge from
the node to itself
but i have edges from every node to every
other node except that the word the root node
will not have any incoming edges that's why
it is written here the edges are from the
node zero to n to one to n zero denotes the
root node from root there are only outgoing
edges and for every other node they have both
incoming edges and outgoing edges so that
is my g x is a graph where the sentence words
and the dummy root symbol are the vertices
this is my set of vertices and there is a
directed edge between every pair of distinct
words yes that's what we have seen here and
a directed edge from the root symbol to every
word from zero to one to n this is my initial
graph
so now from a sentence i can construct this
initial graph and assume that i have some
method of finding out what are the weights
of my edges we will discuss this this problem
in the next lecture how do i find the weights
but for now let us assume that we have some
method of finding the weights of my edges
so i i obtain a multi digraph now my problem
is how do i find the m s t of that multi digraph
and for that we use a very very famous algorithm
called chu liu edmonds algorithm and that's
the very simple algorithm as well
so let us see what this algorithm does so
very simple steps each vertex in the graph
greedily selects the incoming edge with the
highest weight ok so for each vertex in the
graph i have incoming edges from every other
node so what we will do in the fir[st]- what
i will do in the first step for each node
i will select the incoming edge with the highest
weight so now i will now consider only those
edges that have been selected i will see whatever
graph is resulting is it a tree or not if
it is a tree it has to be a maximum spanning
tree because each node as related the maximum
incoming edge now the problem is if whatever
you obtain is not a tree if this is not a
tree that means there has to be a cycle
now if this is a cycle then there is a step
that says you contract the vertices that are
involved in the cycle in a single vertex now
recalculate the incoming and outgoing edges
for all those the for this new vertex that
i have constructed rerun the algorithm that
is again for each vertex choose the edge with
the highest incoming edge again see if the
if whatever you have finding is a tree or
not if it is a tree you stop otherwise you
continue and you can see that you will converge
at some point why because at every step i
am either finding a maximum spanning tree
so i mean stopping or i am finding a cycle
if i am finding a cycle i will contract the
vertices ok so that means it will reduce the
number of vertices that i have in my tree
so it at some point i will have only one vertex
so that that is the point i will have to stop
anyway so this will converge
so now again here are many questions like
how do i compute the weight for the incoming
arcs and outgoing arcs so so let us see by
an example so i take the same sentence that
we discussed in the previous method also the
simple sentence john saw mary and i also know
what is the dependency graph that i i want
to obtain now how do i start -[ed]monds algorithm
so let us see the first thing would be i start
by taking all these three words as my nodes
plus root as an additional node so here we
have root john saw and mary has four different
nodes next you you make an edge between every
two nodes in the graph
so from root you will have only outgoing edges
from root you have an edge to saw to john
and to mary and for every other pair of words
you have an incoming and outgoing edges so
from saw to mary and mary to saw saw to john
john to saw and so on ok and there are some
edge weights and we are not bothering right
now and how do we achieve these edge weights
so let us see i i i am given the sentence
i have some way of finding the edge weights
and i complete i construct this initial multi
digraph
now once i have this this digraph what is
the next step of my algorithm the the next
or the very first step says that each node
in the graph chooses the edge with the maximum
so chooses the incoming edge with the maximum
weight simple ok so there are only three nodes
here that are having incoming edges so let
us see what is the edge that i will choose
so saw has incoming edge of weight ten twenty
and zero so it will have to choose there is
with weight twenty similarly john has incoming
edge of weight nine thirty and eleven so it
will choose the one with weight thirty and
mary has thirty nine and three so it will
choose thirty and then i will remove all the
other edges so i have i will have only three
edges in my graph
is this is this does the qualifier for the
maximum spanning tree or the directed spanning
tree it satisfies the first tree first two
conditions number of nodes will be same as
the original graph and number of edges will
be one less than the number of original nodes
in the graph so i will now have three edges
one for each node as the incoming edge but
that condition is there should not be any
cycle so let us see do we get a cycle or do
we get a tree
so if i do that i will get a graph like this
because saw selects this edge john select
this edge and mary selects this edge so what
are you seeing here if there is a cycle so
i find a cycle here from john to saw and saw
to john so that means so i i i am not done
yet i have to now continue my algorithm so
what was the next step whenever i find a cycle
i contract that i make a single vertex so
the idea would be so now i have a root node
then john saw mary ok so what do i have found
till now twenty thirty thirty ok this is not
a tree it is a cycle so what is the next step
i will take it i will contract it into a single
vertex so there is a word j and s let us let
us call it w j s ok this is a single vertex
now
and i will have to repeat my algorithm for
repeating the algorithm i should know to this
vertex or to this new vertex w j s what are
the incoming and outgoing edges from all the
nodes so there are two nodes now so root and
mary so from root it will have an incoming
edge from mary it will have a incoming edge
as well as outgoing edge so question is how
do i compute the incoming and outgoing weights
from this vertex and for that we have some
very different tools how do i compute the
outgoing edge weights and how do i compute
incoming edge weights so let us see how many
i have to compute i have to compute this weight
one i have to compute so now let's forgot
about this edge i have to compute weight two
and i have to compute weight three yes and
root to mary will be already there that will
not change yes so i have now one two three
edges three vertices only and i have to compute
these edge weights so how do i do that
so so yes so if not a tree you have to identify
the cycle and contract that and you have to
recalculate the arc weights into and out of
the cycle and what is the algorithm for doing
that so algorithm is that for outgoing arc
weights you take the arc weights that are
equal to max of outgoing arcs over all vertices
in the cycle what do i mean by this so here
is my contracted vertex john and saw i want
to compute the outgoing arc weight from this
vertex to mary yes so this will be equal to
the max of outgoing arcs from john to mary
and saw to mary which of these these gives
me the maximum will be final ah weight
so here let us see from john to mary and saw
to mary so john to mary i have a weight of
three and saw to mary i have a weight of thirty
so among these highest is thirty so i will
pick the one with thirty and this is the final
graph that is being shown so from this vertex
the outgoing edge to mary will have a weight
of thirty and that the only outgoing outgoing
edge for this contracted vertex this is fine
now how do i find out the weight for the incoming
arcs so incoming arcs are from root as well
as from mary yes so from incoming arc the
the algorithm is different i do not choose
the now so i have to find out from root to
this vertex so i do not directly choose the
one that is having the maximum so what i do
i have to also consider this the edges inside
the inside the tree so what i will do i will
take the incoming arc weights as equal to
the weights of the best spanning tree that
includes the head of the incoming arc and
all the nodes in my cycle so what do i mean
by that
so let's take from root from root there are
two different ways of defining incoming arc
weights either it has to be root to saw and
saw to john or root to john john to saw these
are the two possible trees ok so so what i
will do i will find out the weight for individual
trees and take which one is having the maximum
weight so let us say root to saw saw to john
this is ten plus thirty forty root to john
john to saw this is nine plus twenty twenty
nine so i will take the weight as forty and
that is the edge weight from root to saw this
is having the weight of forty
now can you compute the weight from mary to
this vertex again i will see the two different
ways mary to saw saw to john so this is zero
plus thirty choose this thirty second is mary
to john john to saw and that is eleven and
twenty thirty one so i have two ways thirty
and thirty one so i will choose one with thirty
one so it is starting from mary to john and
john to saw so now once i have computed all
these weights i have now got the the new tree
on which i have to compute my algorithm so
here what did you find this weight is equal
to forty this weight we found to thirty and
this weight we found as thirty one and this
first so now once i have find these weights
ah what is the next steps i will have to see
if each vertex now selects the incoming arc
with the highest weight do we obtain a tree
so let us see for this vertex incoming arcs
are forty and thirty one so it will choose
this arc for this vertex nine and thirty so
we choose this arc so what is my ah what is
the graph that i am seeing so let me color
only the edges by this so one edge is here
and the second edge is here yes so do you
see it's a tree it's a tree and this is directed
spanning tree so am i done so as one point
i am done because there is no cycle so i do
not have to repeat my algorithm but i still
haven't the optimal dependency graph why because
i am i am now stuck with an edge from root
to this contracted vertex and i do not know
what happens inside and i know there is an
outgoing edge from this contracted vertex
to mary again i want to know what happened
inside so how do i construct my full graph
and for that you have to go back to how you
actually constructed these connections for
this contracted vertex
so what you will do so the incoming edge from
root to john john and saw and the outgoing
edge from john saw to mary so let us see how
did we compute the outgoing edge we said the
outgoing edge should be the maximum of both
the outgoing edges so from john to mary and
from saw saw to mary and where did these come
from this came from saw so i will now see
here this edge from saw to mary that may write
it thirty ok so this is done so this outgoing
edge is from saw not from john that's how
we found it out
now it is about the incoming edge this an
incoming edge could have been from saw then
john or john then saw in our algorithm where
did it come from forty so it came from root
to saw and saw to john yes so i have to construct
now root to saw saw to john so root to saw
and saw to john ok this was ten and this was
thirty and that is my final m s t that is
my dependency graph ok so so this is the algorithm
so let us see again here so you you are at
this step where you have this contracted vertex
and you found out the maximum incoming edge
for each vertex and you obtain a tree so now
you have to go back after your recursive call
and we construct the original graph and there
you have to find out where is this outgoing
edge coming from is it coming from saw or
john and you found it is coming from saw incoming
edge is it coming for this tree or that is
root to saw saw to john or root to john john
to saw and that you can again find out where
did you find this forty it was from root to
saw saw to john
so so yes the edge from w j s to mary was
from saw so we construct that the edge from
root to w j s represents a tree from root
to saw saw to john and that is your dependency
graph so now there might be a question in
your mind that in my algorithm i have different
ways of computing incoming arc weights and
as well as outgoing arc weights they are not
the same so we need them to be different so
that we can also account for the weight for
the ah connection inside the tree but the
question is can i reverse this that is can
i say that the outgoing weight should be the
maximum of the directed spanning tree and
the incoming weight should be the maximum
among all the possible incoming weights so
i would like you to think about it but i can
give you basic intuition that why this is
the case
so let us see so suppose i have a contracted
vertex that has nodes word one and word two
so right now what we are doing we are saying
the outgoing weight is max of to a vertex
like w three it is a max of these two ok now
so we take the max here suppose there is another
word x w four i will do the same the outgoing
weight from here to w four is the max of these
two ok fine now when i have taken the max
here and i am done my with my call and everything
each vertex will choose only one incoming
edge weight so w three will choose either
this or this w four will choose either this
or this or anything else so that that means
i will know for sure whether this there is
connection from w two to w three or w one
to w three or there is no connection and whatever
i obtain even if i say that from w one suppose
my finally i find out a situation like this
that's from w one there are both the connections
are there this is valid from a because from
a single node you can have two different outgoing
edges this is fine or if w one and w two that
is also ok in no case there will be a there
will be two incoming edges for the same node
this is not allowed by the algorithm itself
now suppose i change my algorithm and say
that the outgoing edge is coming from the
directed spanning tree so that will be the
situation where i will have to see so this
edge is the max of w one to w two to w three
and the other one that is w two to w one to
w three yes similarly this will be the max
of w two to w one to w four and w one to w
two to w four fine now what might happened
that in your final tree that you obtain you
find out
this edge yes and this edge ok
now you have to go back and construct your
tree so what you will see there you will see
that this edge is coming from by following
this connection and this is coming by following
this connection so you will end up by saying
ok there is a cycle inside and this will not
terminate again ok you can also try to see
what will happen in the case of so this is
only for the outgoing edges so you see there
might be a case where you can end up finding
a cycle or may not be able to say which of
these two is the correct ah ah sign between
the edges so this case might happen this will
never arise in the way we have define the
algorithm similarly you can try for the incoming
edges would you end up with the situation
where you you are either ah violating some
principle of the dependency graph or where
you are getting the cycle and you are not
able to converge this is something i will
say that you try to take both the cases and
see whether you are finding why the algorithm
ah proceeds in this way of for finding the
incoming and outgoing edge weights so fine
so so we discuss this algorithm of chu liu
edmonds and how do we use that for finding
maximum spanning tree so what we did not cover
is how do we find the edge weights ok and
that's where the learning algorithm comes
in that how do we find the edge weight from
my dependency graph and that's what we will
see in the next lecture
thank you