so welcome to the final lecture of this week
so in the last lecture we had talked about
what is the approach of using maximum spanning
tree for dependency parsing so there we only
covered that if we have a sentence and we
have some way of constructing the original
graph multi diagram where there all possible
connection we can usually algorithm to find
out the m s t ok in thats what we covered
now important point is how do we find out
the aspects ok and thats what we will be covering
here so how do we treated as a learning problem
where we given some data where we know these
are sentences and they are corresponding dependency
graph how do we use that to establish the
aspects for a new sentence and you understand
now that once you can do that part rest part
is already defined by the algorithm so your
main task is how do you effectively construct
the aspects
now now just one thing what do i mean by the
aspect aspect is something that will depend
on the two nodes that you are connecting and
what is the relation with which we are connecting
them so this has to be some sort of a feature
representation vector over the nodes and the
label and you have to define what are your
features and once you define for any possible
connection you can find out this vector find
this vector is a separate task it does not
require any learning the way we will pick
a learning involved each features will also
have a weight assigned that will help you
to determine the aspects so feature vectors
when you multiple the weight you will get
the aspects and this weight vector for the
feature is something you can learn from your
data so that is what weight vector with this
feature set help me to choose the optimal
or the best a spanning tree that corresponds
to dependency graph that i already have in
my data if i have some weights that are not
allowing me to choose the best graph i should
a bit my weight and this is the idea that
we will see in this lecture
so we will talking about the learning part
here so the first thing that we should see
here is the arc weights that we are defining
can be written as some feature vector over
i j k yes the node i the node j and the relation
k and a weight vector and i multiply by weighted
feature i get the arc weight now we have to
see how to define this feature weight features
this is again analogues somehow to what we
did in some of the previous ah classes and
how do we learn this weight vector so here
arc weights are nothing but a linear combinations
of features of the arc and a corresponding
weight vector now what we are different arc
features you can take ok so it will dependent
on again what are the words i am connecting
so let us take a sentence like john saw mary
mcguire yesterday with his telescope and i
want to find out the head weights between
first saw and with with the relation pp ok
so this is my i this is my j and this is the
relation pp so here by the multi diagram arc
means for k you can have many variations you
can have pp you can have n subject direct
object indirect object and non modifier etcetera
we have the various possible variations so
what what would this feature dependent on
so feature would dependent on probably what
are my words themselves they are some of the
most important features if my word is saw
and my word first word is saw second word
is with and the relation is whatever pp here
ok so head is saw and dependent is with that
is taken in my one primarily feature so every
case i will have this feature i will have
an answer one or zero
then i can have a feature composed from the
part of speech tags of these words so i also
know what are part of speech tags and so the
feature can be like what is the part of speech
for the head part so head part of speech is
verb and what is the part of speech of dependent
word that is preposition and that would be
one of the most important features that i
can use because many a times the relations
are defined between various grammatical categories
like for subject it will be between verb and
a noun so if you know that the first the head
word is verb and the dependent is noun there
is a good chance they may have a subject relation
although there are other relation possible
so part of speech is one very important feature
then what else you can also use the part of
speech of the words that are coming around
this head and dependent word in between like
in between part of speech is noun that means
there is a noun that occurs in between these
two words yes in between part of speech is
adverb there is adverb that is occurring dependent
pos right is pronoun for the dependent the
right hand side the part of speech is pronoun
and head pos left is noun to the head to the
left of the head the part of speech is noun
so like that you can have again have many
different features on the neighboring words
and the words in between so you can use the
identity of the words or the part of speech
and then you might also want to use the orientation
whether the head is towards light left or
towards the right so that can be captured
by arc direction this is to the right so arc
direction is right you can also see the distance
how many words are intervening between the
head and dependent so in this case there are
three words that are intervening ok so like
that you can you can take various different
ah question or various different characteristic
of head and dependent surrounding words and
the labels and construct all your features
so this gives you the set of arc features
f i j k and now given any possible ah arc
in your graph you can construct this feature
vector yes it will be answer to all these
questions is the arc distance three or not
so answer will be one or zero so like that
you can construct this feature vector but
what is your aspect that is the feature vector
multiplied by the weight vector so next thing
is how do we use this weight vector or how
do we obtain this weight vector so as such
you can use any features over the arc i j
k and input x
so now how do you obtain my weights for that
i have to define what is my ah inference problem
so this we have already seen for a graph the
weight of a graph will be defined by summation
over the weights of all its edges and the
m s t problem is find out the graph with the
maximum weight ok among all the possible spanning
trees that i can obtain from the starting
graph take the one that is having the maximum
weight now this w i j k can be written as
w times the feature vector f i j k and w can
go outside of this equation so this will be
in other words w times summation over all
the feature vectors and take the arg max over
that and suppose i call this as the feature
of my graph the feature vector for my graph
is nothing but the summation over feature
vectors of all the edges and this is my problem
arg max w times f g over all the possible
graphs or directed spanning tree g that i
can construct from my initial graph now how
do use this inference problem to learn my
bits
so this will be my learning criteria and this
will be very similar to what we did in the
previous ah example that the previous method
also so what is the idea you have a gold standard
training data ok so you are given a training
data of a sentence and its gold standard dependency
graph so there are some capital t sentence
that is now start with some initial weights
they can be zero or they can be some arbitrary
weights ok and lets start with the ah the
first iteration now i am iterating over all
the sentences some capital n number of times
like we did in the previous case in each iteration
i go to each of the individual tree so one
to up to capital t
each sentence instance now what do i do so
i am i am in the learning part i do not know
what are my optimal weights so how does learning
work so i am given a sentence x t and its
dependency graph g t i am already given this
i know what are my features yes i know what
are my features i do not know what are my
weights so how do i proceed
so lets take a particular instance for my
learning so what will happen i am given this
sentence x t so i will apply my algorithm
as if i am doing it at run time so i will
make the root node i will make all the possible
connections somehow ok we can have any possible
connections thats not matter so now you start
by making all the possible
connections that we discussed this is my initial
graph you can that graph g x that has all
the possible connections ok this also all
the possible connections
now at this point how will you proceed for
proceeding you need to know what are the edge
weights here so now how do you obtain the
edge weights so this edge it will be nothing
but w times f i j k i is the ith word here
j is the jth word here and k is the relation
now how do you obtain f i j k this already
given to you so you know what are the features
so features will be some question like ith
words is root and jth word is something like
saw it will be either one or zero yes so your
feature vector will be some zero some ones
and this might be different for different
edges
now what else you do not know your weight
but you will have initial weights or some
intermediate weights you will use those weights
multiply by the feature vector and you will
get some number and that is your w i j k yes
and you will put back this number it can be
say ten or thirty whatever suppose you get
ten thirty twenty fifteen and so on you will
filling all the values using the same method
now once you have filled in all these values
what will be the next step so next step should
be apply chu liu edmonds algorithm yes and
obtained a dependency graph and in other words
obtained a mst ok so suppose you obtain a
graph like root here and so there are three
words so something like this suppose lets
take a simple case and like this this a one
of the dependent one way of writing dependency
graph ok and suppose this is what you obtain
from your algorithm
now where is the learning here learning is
if the dependency graph that you obtain is
if this is not the same as your gold standard
dependency graph that means your weights are
not correct at this point you might have to
modify your weights and how do you modify
your weights very simple like you did in the
previous method also you would say w new or
w old plus you want to go towards the actual
graphs and away from the so call it g prime
that you obtain from by your algorithm so
call it g prime that you obtain by your algorithm
g t is the gold standard graph
so you want to go in this direction and away
from here so it will be simply feature of
g t minus feature of g prime ok and what is
f g t this is nothing but the summation over
features of all the edges of g t similarly
here summation over features of all the edges
of my g prime and that will give you your
new weight vector of course there can be some
learning weights and all but this is just
to give you the intuition and thats all you
will have a new weight again you will start
with this new weight for a new sentence see
whether you obtaining the g t like show graph
by this algorithm if not you will keep on
updating your weights ok and this will sometime
at some point converge and some of one of
your iteration you will have your weights
roughly stabilized and thats where you stop
so now lets so hope this idea is clear lets
take a simple example to further see that
how do you apply this algorithm for learning
the weights
so let me just quickly go through this algorithm
again so i am repeating it for some n number
of iterations for each tree let us find out
g prime as the argmax over weight at the particular
instance and f g prime ok so that is i apply
my ah chu liu edmonds algorithm find out the
tree with the maximum weight if g prime is
not the same as my gold standard graph that
means i have to update my parameters and how
do i do that at this i plus one th time my
weights are initial weights plus f g t minus
f g prime this i am doing only if i am not
obtaining the correct graph i continue further
and at some point it will converge and thats
where i will return the weights and i will
assume at this point i have the ideal weights
so that whenever you give me a new sentence
i can use these weights to compute all the
arc arc weights yes that arc weights are nothing
but weights multiplied by the feature vector
and then i can i can apply chu liu edmonds
algorithm to compute the dependency graph
so let us see some example for learning the
weight vectors so we are using the same ah
sentence like the previous ah case so we are
using the sentence john saw mary ok and suppose
that this occurs in the training set now for
simplicity we are not worrying about what
are the relations between two words i am saying
that there is only one relation rare so my
features will only dependent on the ith word
and jth word that will make things easier
so here what i am showing let us take some
seven different features and some weights
that have been initialized or some intermediate
weights and suppose you are you are un counting
this sentence in your training data how will
you do the weight update
so here let us see what are my seven features
defined over any word i and j for a arc from
w i to w j so features are the ith word has
a part of speech of noun and jth word has
a part of speech of noun ith word is part
of speech of verb jth word is part of speech
of noun and so on ith word is root jth word
is verb and for this simple sentence you already
know right
so you will have [niose] root john ok let
me write it like that saw mary you know this
is a noun this is a verb and this is a noun
and this is root so now your task is suppose
you are given for these seven features the
weights are three twenty fifteen twelve one
ten twenty before the start of the iteration
now you have to determine the weights after
iteration over this example now what do i
mean by doing that same as i said in the in
the last slide so what i will do now i will
first find out all the possible edge weights
ok lets try to find some edge weights what
is the edge weight from root to john ok so
what is this edge weight this is weight vector
multiplied by the feature vector between this
root and john this might w i this might w
j now what is this f root to john this will
be a vector of size seven each value to be
one and zero and this will dependent on the
answer of my question
so let us see what are my features word w
i has a part of speech of noun now w i is
a root so it does not have any part of speech
this will be zero w i has part of speech of
verb again zero w i is root ok lets see the
next one w j is verb so here w j is john that
is noun so this is also zero root and j is
noun this will be one root and w j occurs
at the end of the sentence know john occurs
in the john occurs in the start of the sentence
this is also zero w i occurs before w j in
the sentence roots does not occurs in the
sentence so this will be zero also w i is
the part of speech of noun so it is not true
for root so we see out of seven features only
fourth one is one everything has a zero so
the feature vector here is zero zero zero
one zero zero zero now how do i get the weight
the weight vector is already given to me that
is three twenty fifteen twelve one ten twenty
so i multiple this weight vector to the feature
vector and i obtain the weight of this arc
that is twelve
similarly i compute the weight of the arc
of from root to saw so let us take some other
case like john to mary how do i compute the
arc weight again this is lets find out the
feature for john to mary ok so first one first
question again w i is the part of speech of
noun w j is noun now john and mary both are
nouns so this should be one w i is verb and
w j is noun should be zero w i root none of
the so none of these features will be one
because all the required to be root so the
all three are zero so two three four five
are zero six w i occurs before w j so john
occurs before mary in the sentence there should
be one seventh feature w i had part of speech
of noun w j is verb that is zero so only one
and six are one everything else are zero so
it will be one zero zero zero zero one zero
and multiplied with the weight vector so similarly
first element and sixth element three plus
ten so thirteen so here the weight will be
thirteen
like that you have to find the feature vector
for each edge multiplied by the weight vector
and obtain these values you will said get
some values here x y z etcetera now once you
obtain all these values what you will do apply
chu liu edmonds so once you have all the weights
you can very easily obtain chu liu edmonds
and you will obtain what is your dependency
graph now what will happen suppose you find
a graph like this root john saw mary suppose
this is your output after applying chu liu
edmonds now what you will do so you will this
is your g prime by applying chu liu edmonds
so your first thing you will check is that
what is your g t so your g t is root remember
you will first have connection from root to
saw saw to john and mary this is my g t are
they same they are not the same so i will
update my weights
and how do i update my weights should be w
new is w old plus f g t minus f g prime now
what is f g t f g t is the feature of this
graph that is this feature vector plus this
feature vector plus this feature vector three
feature vectors combined and f g prime is
this feature vector plus this feature vector
plus this feature vector and these are all
some ones and zeros so weights will be nothing
but these weights plus summation over all
these three elements of features minus all
these three elements ok and that will give
you the new set of weights and then you will
continue with this new set of weights for
the next example if you have to do
so so this is in a nutshell what we will be
doing but again i will encourage you to go
through these example fully find out all the
weight vectors yourself see whether you are
getting the same tree as the gold standard
if not how will you update your weights ok
in this will be your next exercise so here
we are not going to very much detail in in
how we are going to learn it by various learning
rates and all just an intuition that how do
you post this as an learning problem ok so
in the in the last module of using parsing
or transition parsing and this module of using
ah mst based parsing we have seen that how
we can solve a problem dependency parsing
in a detailed different manner so we treated
as a some sort of algorithmic way i was starting
from some initial configuration going to some
final configuration that resembles a dependency
graph
and in the in between for example how are
we taking transitions we will determining
by using various training data or how are
we taking the edge weights we are learning
by training data and this would help you to
also think about in terms of some other problems
that how can i pose them in machine learning
way and i was also saying there are some other
they are some other or i would say even many
other methods of for doing dependency parsing
so we will not be covering everything in this
course but now whatever we have covered will
help you to take any new approach and understand
that ok so this also ends our discussion on
main discussion on syntax so we had talked
about starting from word order information
language models to part of speech and morphological
information to various syntax in in the sense
of constituency parsing and dependency parsing
so from the next week we will start our discussions
on semantics so we will first see what is
called different methods by which being capture
the meaning the semantics so we will have
distribution semantics and semantics for that
so thank you i will see you in the next week