so welcome everyone to the seventh week of
the course so where that we are now moving
into the second half so in the first six weeks
we had talked about basic tasks on in any
language how do we pre process the language
how do we deal about its morphology and syntax
now we will be going to some advance topics
so in the next three weeks starting this this
week we will talking about semantics how do
we capture semantics so again semantics is
very huge topic we will focus only on very
very basic and interesting notions that can
you help you build some important applications
and also read some research papers in this
field later in the in the in the last three
weeks of the course we will going to various
applications so today we are starting our
discussion on semantics so and we will be
taking about two notions distribution semantics
and then semantics before going into that
let us see what do i mean by semantics so
in this lecture today we will we will give
the introduction to the topic of distributional
semantics so as such when i say semantics
what comes to your mind in general syntax
talks about arrangement ok how are that different
words are arrange in the language in when
while talk about semantics it immediately
we move from arrangement to some sort of meaning
domain so i want to find out what is the meaning
of different words how do they combine together
to form the meaning of the of the larger unit
that can be the sentence that is in general
the the main the main field
so if i have to give a definition i can say
that semantics is the study of meaning that
is what is the relation between symbols and
what do they denote so here suppose i have
the sentence john told mary that the train
moved out of the station at three o clock
ok it's a sentence in the national language
contains multiple words we know how to tokenize
them and how to find the morphological tax
and may be also the syntax and different representations
now what do i mean by saying that now i want
to go to semantics a semantics i will like
to know what all these words themselves mean
separately so what do i mean by john told
mary etc so these are all symbols now what
do they denote and when they combine together
in a sentence what meaning are they putting
so this is as i said very very ah vast field
lot of different research has happened and
is happening we will focus on mainly the word
meaning so how do we say what is the meaning
of a word what are different notions so in
general so when i talk about distribution
semantics or any other model that we will
cover in this course we we are trying to find
out how in general computers can produce such
semantic representations so machines can interpret
some sort of semantics and thats why the i
idea of computational comes in here
so so computational semantics in general is
the study of how we can automate this process
of building these ah semantic representation
and also reasoning with them ok so when we
talk about the methods ah in general there
are two different methods one are based on
formal semantics that is how do i construct
various mathematical models that can tell
me what is the relation between various expressions
in the language and also relate them to whatever
there is is there in the word for example
so if you have heard about read predicate
logic thats what is done in formal semantics
so if i have a sentence like this john chases
a bat and you want to produce a mathematical
structure that denotes the meaning of the
sentence so i will put them in very very very
very logical form like i will say so [vocalized
noise] so for startup i i will say there is
an x where x is a bat and john chases the
bat so john chase becomes a predicate and
i will say john ah chases x an x i have already
defined as a bat and like that i will define
how do i convert my natural language expression
to some sort of this logical form and then
i will also have rules on how do i infer from
this ah logical expressions how do i reduce
one expression into another one and then so
on
and this is again a field of formal semantics
and that is something we will not cover in
this course what is something apart from formal
semantics that we can see and there where
the data a lot of data that we have can help
us and this is where the field of distribution
semantics comes in that is can i study the
statistical patterns of human word usage to
extract semantics so can i see how humans
are using different words in their language
to find out what is their semantics and this
is what will be the topic of this week what
is the type of distributional semantics how
they capture that and how can i use that for
certain meaningful applications so so this
field of distributional semantics is mainly
built upon this hypothesis of this hypothesis
of distribution distributional hypothesis
that is prevent from many many years what
is the distributional hypothesis let us see
some famous quotes about this so as earlier
as in ninety fifty three wittgenstein said
that the meaning of a word is its usage in
language so that is you can know what is the
meaning of a word if you see how it is being
used in the language
ok along similar lines in ninety fifty seven
firth said you know the word by the company
it keeps now what do i mean by the company
of a word what are the other words it occurs
with in my corpus on my language and that
tell me that tells me about the word now going
one step further so so here so what these
different quotes are mentioning that the word
meaning whatever it might be i do not care
about what exactly is the meaning but whatever
it is it should be reflected in the linguistic
distributions that is the way the word has
been used in the language that will tell me
the word meaning so now zellig harris in nineteen
sixty eight that gave this famous code that
took this idea to one step ahead that is words
that occur in the same context tend to have
similar meanings
so now i can talk about two words having similar
or different meanings if i can somehow measure
their context and capture that and i will
say two words are having similar meanings
if the context in which they occur are very
very similar so so the idea here is two words
if they are semantically similar they tend
to have similar distribution patterns so now
thats what we will be doing in this week how
do we capture distribution patterns of words
and use that to find out similarity across
words let see some other quotes from zellig
harris so he also said that if linguist have
to deal with meaning it can only do so through
distributional analysis and that we said in
very early ah seventies and eighties and and
if you see the the field right now so whatever
the main methods or semantics are there they
are built upon distributions so with the idea
of so with the recent idea of and all and
this is what we will also capture in our ah
in this week of this course
another very similar sort of code from zellig
harris from his distributional structures
so if we consider what are morphemes a and
b to be more different in meaning than a and
c then we will often find that the distributions
of a and b are more different than the distributions
of a and complaint in other words difference
in meaning correlates with difference of distribution
so what he saying suppose i take three different
words or morphemes a b and c and suppose there
is some where i can capture the distribution
so that is how they are occurring in the languages
so i have distribution for a b and c now what
he is saying if a and b the distributions
are more different then that of a and c then
what you will find so what we are saying a
and b are more different than a and c if the
distributions are more different in the meaning
also you will find they are more different
ok so you can think of these as so i take
some examples like car as a and b c can be
automobile they are quite close and b can
be something like a book ok so here a car
and automobile are quite similar and car and
book are more different so they are very very
different so if this this is what i see in
meaning i will also see something similar
in distributions so what i will find these
two distributions are quite similar and these
two would be quite different
ok we will see in this week that how do we
capture these distributions and how do we
compare that but this is the basic idea now
what is another important thing here so distributions
that we are capturing whatever semantics it
is allowing me to to handle its all differential
not referential now what is the difference
between that two terms differential and referential
so again if i would look at the same example
of these three words car book and automobile
so what do i mean by saying so the semantic
sign capturing is only differential but referential
so i cannot say what is the meaning of car
i am not defining the meaning of car at sort
of this concept representation ok there is
there is something i am not doing so what
i am doing what how similar or how different
the two meanings are so i am saying a and
c how similar their meanings are or how different
their meanings are thats why this is differential
sort of understanding of semantics so how
different or how similar two different meanings
are i am not talk talking about some referential
meaning in distributional semantics
so now ah if we look at so this was the linguistic
prospective is there some cognitive prospective
also with distributional semantics so so there
we have this idea that what is the representation
of the word and it is said to be some sort
of abstract cognible structure that i am storing
in my in my brain or somewhere we do not know
but that is something i gather as i keep on
hearing this word or looking or finding this
word in more and more context as i find this
word in more and more context i tend to build
some sort of representation about this word
this is the cognitive prospective and what
is some sort of evidence so so for example
how when you encounter a new word that you
have never heard before even if we do not
know its meaning you may guess something about
this word what it might be ok so lets take
an example ah like i am saying this word wampimuk
ok i have never heard this word before now
i am seeing this word or hearing this word
in this context he filled the wampimuk with
the substance passed it around and we all
drunk some ok so just by looking at the word
that are occurring around this word and seeing
what are the words might occur in place of
wampimuk i can say that this might be some
sort of a container some sort of a glass or
something so which can be used for filling
up the substances and and passing around
so so as i keep on hearing a word or seeing
a word in more and more context i tend to
build some sort of meaning structure about
about that word now suppose i have i have
heard this word in a very different context
like this we find a little wampimuk sleeping
behind the tree immediately i will have a
different ah interpretation i will say ok
may be wampimuk some is some sort of a small
animal ok so this is some sort of ah intuition
behind the cognitive prospective and why we
might think the meaning in terms of the distributions
in the language now to capture these distribution
and then and and find semantics from there
the models that are used are called distributional
semantic models and also there is some term
called dsm for them and what are these so
these are various computational models that
build contextual semantic representations
from my corpus data so now what is important
here is that i am already given some sort
of and if more data generally the better so
i am given some corpus data on how different
words are used in language and from there
i am trying to come up with some ah some semantic
models distribution semantic model and this
will capture the differential aspects of meaning
among words so so dsms are models for semantic
representation and where i capture a semantic
content by using a vector so for each word
we will try to build a different vector that
will capture the semantics and these vectors
are obtained via the statistics analysis of
the linguistic linguistic contexts of the
word now this word occurs in various context
will will help to find out its vector representation
and there are some alter alternative names
for this semantics like corpus based semantics
statistical semantics geometrical models of
meaning vector semantics and word space models
and and there might be some other prevalent
names also but we capture the same idea that
can i use the distribution of the words to
find out the meaning or at least capture which
words are similar than other which pair of
words are similar than other pair of words
so now so again so this distribution semantics
when i talk about what do you mean by the
two terms distribution semantics so when i
say distribution they are the vectors denoting
different different words and their vectors
in some multi [vocalized noise] high dimensional
or in low dimensional space and this space
is the semantic space so i have distributions
that are vectors denoting the words in that
multidimensional semantic space and semantics
space has dimensions which correspond to various
possible context and this context can be gathered
from a corpus so what i am doing every word
i am denoting in this semantics space and
this is my distribution semantics and this
semantics space composed of various dimensions
that are my context in which i am trying to
represent a given word so let us let let us
take this an example so when i talk about
symbol vector space model so that all of you
would already be aware of so this is my two
dimensional plane and its x y plane and i
can denote different objects so here there
are two points that i am denoting a and b
by their coordinates so what are ah so their
projection in on x axis and y axis that tells
me the coordinates and i can now capture how
similar how near to words two objects are
in this space analogous to that now let us
think of a semantics space where dimensions
are not x and y axis but they are various
context and can i denote all my words in those
dimensions so here suppose that my dimensions
are two words eat and drive ok
two different words and i am trying to denote
three words car dog and cat in these dimensions
and what you are seen here so this might denote
how often a word occurs with this word on
and this word the projection will denote that
so you see cat comes quite often with the
word eat similarly dog car comes a lot often
with drive but not so much with eat so you
see immediately when you try to put these
word in this semantic space will capture some
similarity that cat and dog are probably similar
much more similar than cat and car and dog
and car and this is the this is the idea can
i use different context as my dimensions and
represents all my words in those dimensions
to give a meaning representation in general
here i have shown you only for the dimension
that corresponds to two words but in general
you all have to use any number of dimensions
so you can use any number of words that you
want so so you might have a representation
like that so i can say cat is a is a any other
object or a word that has a weight of point
eight in the dimension of dog point seven
dimension of eat point zero one dimension
of joke so depending on how often the word
cat occurs with all these words ok and and
this i can do for different different words
and then i can capture how similar they are
and this is a very very powerful technique
although its looks very simple it it works
quite well in many many applications that
that we will see
so now lets take an example and how do we
start constructing this a vector space or
word space model and try to see can we compute
the similarity across words so here i am given
a small data set that has six different sentences
in so like an automobile is a wheeled motor
vehicle used for transporting passengers and
so on there are six different sentences are
given and i have to build a vector space model
or a distributional semantic model now to
build the model i need to start with what
are the words i want to represent and these
are my target words so here i want to represent
four word automobile car soccer and football
so now once i know what are the words i want
to represent the next question i need to ask
is i need to represent in in what dimensions
so this becomes my context here also denoted
by term vocabulary what are the dimensions
in which i will be denoting all these four
words so here i have one two three four five
six seven dimensions now so what will be the
alg informal algorithm for constructing the
deman the distributional semantic space or
the word space you start by picking up the
words that you are interested in that means
the words for which you want to find the distributions
and these are called your target words so
here i start with four target words then you
define what are the context words also so
here you found seven context words next question
would be ok when do i say that this word occurs
with another word should i say that when it
occurs in the same sentence same paragraph
same document or within plus minus two words
ok when do i say that so so that is called
the context window so i can define a context
window to be ah may be five words around the
word or it can be a sentence paragraph and
whatever word so so i need to define a context
window that is how many words should i consider
surrounding a target word and it can be defined
in terms of a document paragraph sentences
and so on
now a simple method would be once you defined
the context window you know what are your
target words what are your context words so
when you are defining a distributions of the
target words find out how often they occur
with the various context words within the
context window and just write down the number
this occurs with this word in this context
window two times three times zero times and
and so on and you define the vectors for different
target words and this is this can also be
called your as your co occurrence matrix between
the target words and the context words now
once you have built the co occurrence matrix
you can think of each row of this matrix as
your vector for that denotes this individual
word so if we try to apply this algorithm
on the previous example that we have seen
so what we will have we will have four words
as the target words seven word as my context
words and i will have a matrix of dimension
four cross seven and each element will denote
how often this target word occurred with this
context word within my context window
let us see the whole sentence here in the
context window so you can try doing that with
the example that that we had seen and try
to find out what are the different number
of times each individual word occurs with
another word and you will find something like
that so this you can call as your co occurrence
matrix or distribution matrix composed of
targets and contexts so what do we see here
automobile occurs with wheel transport passenger
football occurs with passenger tournament
london goal and match and [vocalized noise]
similarly for car and soccer so now this is
my ah representation of target words in this
semantic space now suppose i take only two
dimensions of this semantic space so here
i had one two three four five six seven dimensions
suppose i see only two dimensions so here
i am seeing goal and transport and i am projecting
all the four words in this dimensions so what
representation i will see so i will see that
soccer occurs with goal and goal not be transport
football occurs with goal not be transport
automobile occurs with transport not with
goal and car occurs with transport not with
goal immediately you can see some separation
that is soccer and football are coming out
with more similar automobile and car are coming
out with [vocalized noise] excuse me are being
more similar by just looking at these two
dimensions ok and that is some very interesting
aspect that the distributional semantic models
try to capture
now suppose i go back to my vector representation
so where i have all the seven dimensions and
i want to find out which two words are similar
and to what degree so one simple thing i can
do is to take the dot products ok so that
will tell me if they are having weights in
similar dimensions if they having weights
in different dimensions the dot products will
be zero or close to zero but if they are having
weights in same dimensions their dot product
will be high suppose we are not doing any
normalization i can just take simple dot products
and find out which two objects or which two
words are more similar than other words so
if you try to do that in this example so what
did you would you find automobile and car
so dot product would be one plus two three
plus one four and everything else is zero
similarly automobile soccer you will find
zero automobile football one car soccer one
car football two and soccer football five
ok so from these simple dot products computations
so what what is something that you see so
you see that immediately you can capture the
idea that here automobile and car are very
similar they are having a very high dot product
four similarly soccer and football are also
very similar they are having a dot product
of five on the other hand automobile soccer
are not very not much similar car and soccer
are hm not much similar and so on so you can
find out some sort of differential aspect
of my meaning that is which two words have
similar meanings and which two words are different
meanings just by looking at the simple distribution
and as you keep on getting more and more data
you will you will be able to capture more
and more information about how similar and
how different two meanings of words are this
is a very very basic ah basic idea that that
i had tried to give in this lecture now we
will see what are the different formal ways
in which we can construct these models how
do we count what are different ways in which
we can denote the entries of this matrix and
how do we use that to compute ah similarity
across two different words ok so this we will
cover in more detail in the next lecture but
i hope that the main idea of using these distribution
models is clear
thank you