welcome back for the second lecture of this
week so in the last lecture we started our
discussions on distribution semantics and
we took a very simple example in the very
naive method we constructed that distribution
matrix and try to compute the similarity across
words now you will be see this this concept
much more formally that how do we construct
such models and what are the different applications
that that we can use them all we will see
some some examples so firstly let me just
go back a step and and see why do we need
to talk about the distributional semantics
so if i talk about a vector space model without
distributional semantics what would happen
so there words would we treated as various
atomic symbols so what do i mean by that
suppose think of your semantic space as corresponding
to various various different words that you
see in your vocabulary so if your vocabulary
is of size v so contains word with index one
two up to v and i want to give a representation
to this these words in the vocabulary some
representation so what is the representation
that i can give without any ah looking at
any distributions so i will see that say that
ok each one is a different dimension dimension
one dimension two up to dimension v ok and
how do i denote a word in these dimensions
so suppose i have the i th word so i will
say so let me denote it the i th word this
will be a vector in v dimensions where only
the i th element is one everything else is
zero ok so like that i can give a different
representation to each of the v words right
where only one element corresponding to the
index will be one everything else will be
zero and this is also called the one hot encoding
only one of the entry is one everything else
is zero
now so there is also my semantic space where
all the v dimensions correspond to different
v different words now what is the difference
here i am not capturing distribution i am
just saying this word is the i th dimension
nothing else now can i do semantics with that
or can i capture the meaning of the words
with that each word has a different vector
now suppose i want to find out if wi and wj
are more similar than wi and wk so what is
the similarity between wiwj and wiwk so what
will happen if i use this encoding so i will
find out because here the i th element will
be one everything else will be zero here j
th element will be one everything else will
be zero so if i try to take a dot product
i will get a zero in both the cases even if
you find that these two words are looking
similar than these two words and that is one
problem with using on the one hot encoding
so suppose i take two words here like motel
and hotel and suppose motel occur at this
index it will has one everything as zero hotel
occurs this syntax this is one everything
as zero so if i take to take try to take the
dot product of these two i will get a zero
and if i if i take hotel and book that also
will give me (Refer Time: 04 :00) a dot product
of zero so this will not capture that hotels
and motels are much more similar than hotels
and book now what do we do in distribution
semantics so we use this idea that you know
a word by the company it keeps so instead
of putting only one one and everything else
zero try to model the distributions so suppose
i take a word like banking i will not denote
it by a simply one at its syntax but i will
see what are the other words that come its
context
so if we talk it is occurring in in the corpus
with government dept problems turning crises
europe regulations replace etcetera then these
words will be use to represent banking so
now what will happen so instead of my one
hot encoding i will now go to a distribution
representation where i will say for the word
like banking how many times suppose this is
my dimensions corresponding to government
so how many times it occurs with government
say two times similarly here it is my ah dimension
corresponding to say regulation how many times
it is [vocalized noise] occurring with regulation
so this is i am doing for bank now i can do
similar thing for something else like economy
and so on what they will find probably the
word banking economy have quite similar distributions
than the word like banking and something like
play yes so instead of having a on hot encoding
i am having a distributed representation and
thats what is being done by these distribution
semantic models
so now how would i build a distribution semantic
models step by step so you will take a corpus
that is the ah that is something that you
have require that contains a lot of data the
the various usage of different words in the
sentences now you will do some pre processes
to define what are your target words and what
are your context words context can be context
word or something else we will see some examples
now once you select what are your targets
and context from your data and what is the
next task next you will count how many times
the target co occurs with various contextand
you will give some weights to these contexts
it can be the simply number of times they
co occur or some function applied over this
this number and we will see again see some
examples for that now once you have given
the weights you build the matrix distribution
matrix now some optional step is if you want
to reduce the dimensions of this matrix because
the dimensions in general can be very very
high if you are taking talking about a large
corpus you might have millions of words as
your context so do you want to further reduce
the dimensions then once you have the representation
in that reduce dimension you can also try
to capture the similarity across words so
you compute the vector distances on the reduced
matrix and this is the overall pipeline for
constructing a distribution semantic model
now here there are many design choices that
you might have to make for example we said
that we will define what are my target words
what are my context words now it can be i
there can be many many variations so symbol
is could be my targets are words and contexts
are documents and i am saying how many names
this word occurs in this documents and further
i can give various weights so this is one
matrix type another could be word cross word
how many times this word occurs with another
word ok then again keep on going so how many
times this word occurs with that word in certain
such proximity or this adjective occurs with
this modified noun and word with dependency
relation noun and verb with its argument and
so on so i can have various different sort
of matrix types initially we will only focus
on the ah first and second that is my word
is the target and document is the context
or word is a target and word is the context
now once i have this matrix what are the other
design choices then how do i weight the elements
should i use the probabilities to weight them
should i use length normalization tfidf pmi
positive pmi or positive pmi bit discounting
what is the method that i should use for for
weighting the the entries in my ah matrix
ok then if i am doing [vocalized noise] dimensionality
reduction there are the many methods lsa plsa
lda is also one sort of dimension reduction
method pca so on then once even i have done
that how do i compare two different vectors
once i have built the all the vectors in this
manner should i use the euclidean distance
cosine similarity or dice coefficient jaccard
coefficient etcetera so they are lot of design
choices that you might have to make and each
individual on might make a different sort
oF distribution semantics model but the underlining
idea is the same that you want to capture
a distributions from a large corpus
so now and then there might be different questions
that you might be going to answer that once
you have built the distribution matrix how
do different rows in the matrix let to each
other and how do different columns in the
matrix let to each other so so what we have
seen a number of parameters that we need to
fix like what type of context should i use
what weighting schemes are use [vocalized
noise] yes and what similarity measures should
i use ok and different models might be a different
settings of these parameters n now lets starts
with the simplest case where words are the
targets and documents are the context now
here is a simple example so you areseeing
some words as a as a rows and documents as
columns and what do the entries denote that
against occurs in the document d four one
times in d seven three times d eight two times
d nine three times document it occurs it does
not occurs ok and thats how you are represent
giving a representation to the word against
these doing without any weighting just simply
the row counts and this you can be very easily
find for any different any word so in information
table also this is done for each word how
many times it occurs in various talkings
on the other hand suppose your context are
the word then you are trying to show how many
times a word occurs with another word so in
this particular case so the word against occurs
with age ninety times age agent thirty nine
times and so on and this diagnoses tells how
many times the word agent occurs ok so it
is being computed ah by ah as if co occurring
with itself so so here so again you will you
will define a context window it can be a sentence
or something and you will find out how many
times the word air occurs with against and
age occurs with age and so on this you can
do for all the words or a specific set of
word that you have already chosen for your
analysis this is simply the count now ah if
i am using my words as contexts document contexts
are easy because i know what is the context
window size this is the whole document so
i will say whether this words occurs in the
document or not or how many times it occurs
now suppose i am using words at constant now
now the question comes in what should be the
size of my context window should i choose
only the co occurrence within two words occurring
or within a paragraph within the whole document
and this is the [vocalized noise] design choice
that you can make depending on are you trying
to measure ah similarity on based on some
very close co occurrences or you are alloying
even a some very very distant ah co occurrences
in the same document so so what wsa the parameters
here what is a size of my widow ok so how
far am i looking it and what is the shape
of my window is a rectangular triangular or
something else let me just briefly let what
do i mean by the shape of the window
so that is suppose i am having a word w ok
and it has some context so i am trying to
see how many times this word occurs with these
words around the context so suppose this is
the previous word previous to previous word
next word next to next word ok so my size
is am i looking at only two words around it
or more than that three four and so on this
is my size so this is the size and what do
i mean by shape so we said it can be triangular
ok so triangular will be something like this
was is rectangular what is the difference
in triangular what i will do as i keep on
moving away from my target word i reduce the
ah the count i will say ok this count i will
treat as one this i will treat as point five
so this is the strength is decrease as you
go away from the target word similarly this
can be one this can be point five and you
can as such were give it any shape like exponential
or whatever ok in that that way you can capture
even much far the co occurrences in that you
know what you will what you will do you will
say ok i will count each co occurrence size
same same way so each has a weight of one
or whatever you give
so this is the idea of window size and window
shape now what the so so so let us take one
example ah from some these article so this
is my passage the suspected communist rebels
on fourth july nineteen eighty nine killed
and so on ok this is my passage and i want
to capture the co occurrence over there are
so so what i will do i will first define what
is my window size suppose i have a window
of size five i want to use window of size
five where i am taking two words either side
of my target word so what will the window
look like take the word like rebels here i
will find out its co occurrence only with
two words on the left and two words on the
right so here suspected and communist come
here on and four come here similarly when
rebels occur here says and communist come
here have and killed come here so these are
my context words in the window so i will only
define rebel rebels coming with these words
everything else i will not i will count as
zero so this is my unfiltered window ok i
am not filtering any words i can also use
a filtered window where i can filter the words
so something like that so i will take two
words either side of the target word but now
these are filtered so that they do not contain
the stop words so here on the left i have
the two words suspect and communist but on
the right i remove the words on four and a
number like nineteen eighty nine and i am
taking the words july and killed ok similarly
here i have says and communist in my window
but not have have is like a stop word so i
have remove that and then killed is there
up to sixty five is not there and soldiers
so you can take either the filtered window
or an unfiltered window
now how do i weight the context so again let
us take the two cases when my documents are
context was is when my words are context so
when my documents are [vocalized noise] context
how should i weight the occurrence of a word
in my document so so what it should depend
on so in how many times a word is occurring
in the document what it should depend on or
what the weight should depend on so i am denoting
a word in documents and i am going to give
a weight suppose it occurs five times in this
documents ok and another word occurs seven
times and now i am convert that into some
weight so what should thethis weight depend
on so what can be the the the different ah
parameters on which it can depend firstly
if a wordoccurs more number of times it should
get a high weight ok so this weight should
the proportional to number of times it occurs
and we call it the term frequency how many
times a word occurs in a document
what else if the document is very very long
so you might have take that window count so
suppose i have a document d one of size hundred
and i have a document d two of size thousand
ok and i know that word one occurs in d one
with five times and it occurs in d two ten
times i cannot simply say that in document
two word one has a high weight because document
two itself is very very long so the weight
should be inversely proportion to the length
of the document ok as the length of the document
increases the weight should also reduce and
what can be the other measure another measure
is very very important also you can you can
ah even know that if you have ah heard about
ah some information debate topics so this
is called the inverse document frequency so
that is idf inverse document frequency and
what is the idea so idea is if a word occurs
in many many documents through my corpus was
such if a words occurs in only selective documents
whom should i give a more weight ok so that
is suppose my word w one occurs in this document
five times and w two occurs seven times that
is ok but suppose i also find that w one occurs
only in three documents overall and w two
occurs in fifty documents
what can i say about the nature of the these
two words so one thing i can say is that w
two is probably a very generic term and w
one is a very very specific term ok this becomes
a generic term and this is a specific term
so idea is that specific term might have more
information about the document than a generic
term because generic term might be occurring
in many many different documents so i want
to give a high weight to w one because it
occurs in very few documents and it has occurred
here so that means i will give a weight proportional
to one divide by number of documents that
it occurs in ok so i can call it a document
frequency if the document frequency is high
i give it a small weight so these are three
different parameters or factors on which my
function bit will ah depend on how many times
a word appears in the document then what is
the different number of words that occur in
a document and how many different documents
a word occurs in and as we saw its weight
should be proportion to the number of times
that occur in the documents should be inversely
proportion to the other two factors and there
are various different induction functions
that that have been proposed that take into
account all these ideas and one very common
measure that is used a tfidf that is i give
a weight of proportional to the frequency
fij times log of n by nj ok so nj is the document
frequency so if it is higher i give it a smaller
weight and where tis the document coming in
to picture document length so because once
i compute the tf idf for each individual term
the document i take the l two norm so if there
are lot of terms the document the individual
weights will be reduced ok
so this is one very ah commonly used ah induction
function called tf idf i see what are the
number of times that word occurs in the document
and how many different documents that occurs
in so one thing they have many variations
that have been proposed for this function
this is the simplest function that has been
know for tf idf and finally we have to take
the l two norm this is something that we should
not forget that i have to [vocalized noise]
finally normalize all the different values
in a single document so that some of the squares
adds up to one so now suppose i take words
as my context instead of documents then what
is the interesting weighting function i can
use lets take an example so here my target
words is word is dog in both the cases context
word is small and domesticated two different
words as my context and what you been shown
here so target word has the same frequency
yes but the context words in one case is small
as if it sorry small has a frequency of four
ninety thousand five eighty and domesticated
has a frequency of nine hundred and eighty
so you can clearly see here see here that
the word small is very very common and domesticated
is very specific term
now suppose i find out the co occurrence the
dog are occurs with small eight fifty five
times and dog occurs with domesticated twenty
nine times now my question is what number
i should used denote how much dog co occurs
with the word like ah small and domesticated
so if i do not give any weights what will
happen here i will say dog occurs a lot with
the small eight fifty five times and dog occurs
very rarely with domesticated twenty nine
times ok but that is not capture the whole
picture so what is the whole picture domesticate
is the very very rare word it occurs only
in nine hundred documents out of which in
thirty documents occurs with dog a small occurs
in four ninety thousand documents out of which
only in eight fifty five documents it occurs
with dog so can i use the idea that if a word
is rare word its co occurrence with the target
word should have a higher weights than if
the word is very very common word ok so that
is can i use the frequency of the individual
words also when i give the weights to their
co occurrence and thats what we do why using
various association measures that i used to
give various weights to the context and the
idea is that the less frequent target and
context elements are the higher the weight
you give to their co occurrence count ok so
in this case what will happen so because my
context element is less frequent here in domesticated
their ah occurrence with dog should be given
a high weights so co occurrence with the frequent
context element small will be less informative
here than the co occurrence with the rarer
word domesticated and there are various measures
that captures that like mutual information
is very very popular measure and also log
likelihood ratio etcetera they try to capture
this so how common and rare or rare the words
that among which i am finding co occurrence
are and how many times they co occurred together
so they try to use both of these into a single
function so what is my what is the function
for point wise mutual information for two
different words w one w two i will find out
in mutual information
what is the probability that they co occurred
together in the corpus i will divide it by
what is the probability that they would have
co occurred together had they been they been
occurring independently ok so this mutual
information tells me how much information
do i gain by seeing how many times they are
co occurring that i that i wouldnt have obtain
by their random co occurrences so so thats
the formula thats the formula so what is their
probability of of they co occurrence in the
corpus divided by what is the probability
of a co occurrence in the corpus if they were
independent now how do we capture the probability
of their occurring of they occurring independently
in the corpus so that would be i will say
ok the probability with which w one occurs
and among those times w two could have occurred
again with this probability so it will be
the probability of occurrence of w one times
probability of occurrence of w two so so this
is a function that i can use probability with
which w one w two co occur divide by probability
with which w one occurs times probability
with which w two occurs and i will take a
log of for that and how do i capture probability
of occurrence in a in the corpus for two words
number of times they co occurred together
is a simple co occurrence count divided by
n so n here would denote the different ah
number of context that you can see or in in
or it can be also the number of different
tokens that you have in your data similarly
probability corpus of the word w is very simple
this is the unigram model number of times
this word occurs divided by a num all total
different ah number of token that you have
seen
so
so in pmi what would happen in in sudden cases
the value might also go to ah negative values
so what we what is some variations there so
you can use up only the positive values and
this is called positive pmi ppmi so where
only those ah values that are greater than
zero are taking into consideration everything
else is converted to zero now there is one
problem in this mutual information approach
that there is a biased words some in frequent
evens so remember why why we came this idea
of mutual information we wanted to give high
weight to the evens that are in frequent ok
if two words are rare we do wanted to give
their association a high high weights but
what happens if two evens two words are very
very rare they get they might get some high
weight ok so some one particular cases suppose
think about the scenario with wi and wj have
the same occurrence in the corpus as w i wjwj
together ok now what to do the probability
or the mutual information in this case so
pmi between wi wj is log of probability wi
wj divided by probability w i times probability
wj and suppose all three are equal so what
would happen this would cancel so this will
be log one by p wi so what it is saying if
these three are equal pmi will be high if
pwi is low and immediately that that gives
a bias in in the favor of events that are
smaller though or words that occur very very
rarely ok so you can think of two scenarios
where all this three probabilities are one
by hundred or versus all these three probabilities
are one by ten thousands so either we i would
like the association to be the same in both
the cases but what would happen in this formula
the association become high when the probability
is low and this is not desired ok so this
will create a problem when their ah individual
probabilities are very very low this this
immediately will become pmi will become very
very high
and there are another ah another case where
you can see that if the word wj occurs only
once in the corpus and it also occurs that
time in with wi so what would happen so pwiwj
and pwj will become similar here also because
what i am i saying wj occurs once also with
wi ok so pwj will be one by n and pwiwj will
also be one by n so if i put that here it
will again come out to be this formula and
that means it will the pmi will depend on
wi if wi is frequent pmi will be low if it
is rare it will become high i mean this is
not desire so to evaluate this problem so
they are two different things that you can
do one is you can ah probably start by the
moving all the words that are having very
very low occurrences so all the words that
are occurring less than two or three times
you can remove from your data all together
and huh the words that are occurring more
than that this problem will be not ah not
that bad but if you want took also take into
considerations the very very infrequent words
so what you might have to do you might have
to ah takes into consideration some sort of
ah bias
so what is the idea so there is this very
important discounting factors that are proposed
by pantel and lin so what it says that you
multiply the pmi value with this discounting
factor that is fij divided by the fij plus
one times minimum of fi fj divided by minimum
of fi fj plus one so what would happen now
so you will multiply this with pmi so is a
frequency of the individual events are very
very small this factor will become smaller
so like thats take two cases here one where
fi is equal to fj is equal to fij is one where
they are even second fi is equal to fj is
equal to fij is equal to ten not so rare ok
so in the first case what will be the discounting
factors one divided by one plus one times
one divided by one plus one this will be one
by four in this case it will be one divided
by ten plus one times one divided by ten plus
one this will be sorry ten divided by that
so this will hundred divided by hundred twenty
one so discounting will be much more higher
here so you will divide the pmi by point two
five here you will or multiply by point two
five here you multiply by roughly point eight
and this takes care of the problems that we
had talked about in with infrequent events
so whenever there are infrequent pmi will
become very high so if you use this discounting
it will again come back to a reasonable value
and this will not create a problem when the
evens are not so rare so here is one example
of what kind of vector do you get by taking
this pmi ok so on the left hand side you have
so so what is done here you taking a large
corpus and finding out for individual words
what are the other other vectors that i having
high pmi values and then you are doing some
normalization so that all the pmi value is
on this course for a given word add up to
one so what do you see here if i take a word
like petroleum you find words like oil gas
crude barrels exploration that are coming
out to be having very high pmi values with
drug you find words like trafficking cocaine
narcotics insurance you find a words like
insurers premiums lloyds with forest you find
the words like timber trees land and robots
robotics you find word like robots automation
and so on and all this is coming out just
by putting this pmi function over this corpus
where different words and sentences are ah
are put together ok i am computing this function
and finding out for a word what are similar
words and you can see that it is capturing
very nicely what are the other very similar
words to that ah to s starting word like robotics
you find words like robots and automation
but the word like forest you find immediately
words like trees etcetera and this can give
you nice intuition that you can use that very
nicely to capture which two words are similar
which two words are very very different and
in in some of application you can make use
of that so i will start from here in the ah
so for the for the next lecture and we will
see how we can use that for some very interesting
application like ah term information i will
define the problem and see how do you use
that
thank you