so hello everyone welcome to the third lecture
of this week so we are talking about distribution
semantics and we had already discussed what
is a generic framework of distribution semantics
how do you build models by taking different
sorts of targets and context and how do you
fill up all the antigen of matrix now in this
lecture we'll talk about some of the some
applications for distribution semantic models
also how do i compare similarity across two
words and then we'll move towards some a structured
model of distribution semantics
so starting with some application so so let's
talk about this problem of term mismatch that
we see in the case of information retrieval
so what is the problem so so information retrieval
the user is giving a query that is in terms
of certain words that he feels are describing
his information in it and so he is trying
to ma so the system is trying to match this
this set of keywords to all the documents
that are there in the depositary and by by
doing this matching they are trying to find
out what are the potential document that can
be returned to the user
now what is one problem here so it might happen
that the particular concept that the user
has in mind the user expressing by using certain
words but the documents has have the same
concept using a very very different word so
so they are the the words are similar on the
semantic label but on the surface label they
are two different keywords or two different
words so this is called a term mismatch problem
and one of the key issues in information retrieval
is how do we solve this term mismatch problem
how do i find out that the user typed this
particular term but he might also be interested
in the other term that is semantically similar
but on the surface form it is different
so let's see an example so suppose ah there
is a user query insurance insurance cover
which pays for long term care and it might
happen that the rol relevant document that
contains the answer to the user query may
have words like medicare premiums insurers
etcetera that are not directly provided in
the user query
now one question is how do i find out that
these documents that contain some similar
words are also relevant to this user query
so for this task one can use issue semantic
models for query expansion so query expansion
is one of the techniques that is used for
this term mismatch problem so idea is that
i the user has given a query with certain
words can i try to find out some other words
that are semantically similar to the user
query words if i find out some words then
i append those words to the user query and
this is called the expended query query expansion
process and now i give this expended query
to to my search engine and then retrieve the
documents so now what we will see in in brief
can we use our distribution semantic models
for this problem of query expansion so so
what is the idea so once user gives a query
we reformulate it using the terms is a relevant
or that are related to the terms that are
already there in the ah in the query find
out some related terms and try to use that
to improve the retrieval performance so so
how do we find out the related terms so firstly
i have the query terms that the user is giving
find out what are the distributional vectors
and take a function combination of all the
distributional vectors and obtained the expanded
query
so suppose that the query has three terms
find out what are the related terms to all
this three terms in the distributional sense
and make a linear combination of all such
ah possibilities and give the expanded query
to the user so how will it look like so suppose
the user gives a query like catastrophic health
insurance so what you are doing so in your
distribution vector suppose you are finding
out what are the terms that are related to
each of the three terms catastrophic health
and insurance
ok so what will happen so user has given these
three terms
and suppose you are using words at con as
context so the different words were there
w i w n and for each word so you are computing
what is the co occurrence so it can be say
p m i value what is the p m i between catastrophic
and w one so like that you are computing for
all the words so now what you might do you
might say ok what are the words that are associate
with all the three words so that are having
high p m i values so one way is you just add
all the p m i values p m i q w i for all words
q in my query
ok so for each word w why i i complete a score
like that what is the p m i of that query
one of the query word with this word w i and
add your all the query words and then i can
sort it and maybe i can normalize it with
respect to the highest term so what will happen
at the end of that if i can i can sort these
course and find out what are the words w i
w i prime etcetera that are very much related
to the query terms and all these we have already
covered how do a compute this course once
we this course i can compute this symbol formula
and find out what are the terms in a decreasing
order
so this one part way but you can have any
other sort of functional combination so this
is a simple addition but you can have multiplication
and other sort of function combinations also
so suppose we we do that so what happens to
the actual query so this is my ac actual query
catastrophic health insurance and if i try
to use this technique to find out some other
related terms i get terms like this so i have
terms like surtax h c f a medicare and h m
o s medicaid h m o beneficiaries premiums
and so on now so these terms are taken by
ah from a news corpus that is u s news corpus
so they are certain terms that are relevant
to the u s ah medical ah system so what are
the so what you are seeing in this in the
expected terms so some terms are like broad
explanation terms so that means if you look
at may be some ah ah or some other thesaurus
you can find out such kind of ah similar terms
so you will say ok medicare beneficiaries
premiums or some broad explanation terms so
they are ready to the query in addition you
also get some very very specific domains domain
term like here h c f a that is u s domain
term for health care financing administration
similarly h m o for health maintenance organization
h h s so these are very very domain specific
terms so if you know that you query in in
a cert is coming from a certain domain this
approach can be very very helpful to also
find out terms that can ex used that can be
used to explain the query and not also a domain
specific
ok so let's take another example so these
are so i'm showing here some trec topics so
trec is a text t o conference so they organize
various competitions for information retrieval
so they are actual queries from the trec ah
data so you have a query like ocean remote
sensing and when you use this method you can
find some other terms like radiometer landstat
ionosphere c n e s altimeter nasda meteorology
and so on and ah again as we seen saw in the
earlier query there are some broad explanation
terms like radiometer lanstat and ionosphere
that are connected to the query and they are
some domain specific terms like c n e s and
nasda here
so this is one very nice ah application of
distribution sem semantic models you have
some ex existing query you want to match it
to some document why don't you expand this
query by using some related terms and this
is the idea and this we can use in general
for any rid matching task you are having do
different text data and you are trying to
match these so try to find out if there are
somehow related on the semantic label using
distribution semantic models and use this
idea to find out if they are similar or not
now so ah so once we have computed the distributional
semantic model so i have the vectors for different
words ok so different target words i have
the vectors now how do i compute the similarity
between different words so it depends on what
is your representation that you are using
for computing the ah semantics or the what
is the vector representation if it is the
binary vector you will use different sort
of similarity methods than if it is a ah real
valued vectors or if it is a probability distribution
you will use a different sort of similarity
matrix
so as is the framework allows you to use any
of these ah vector representations so let
us see if you use if you are using any of
these what kind of similarity methods you
can use to compute similarity between two
words so let us say my ah so have words x
and y and they are denoted using some binary
vectors so as such any sort of distribution
you can also convert into binary vectors
so how do i com ah compare ah how do i find
similarity between two word two words where
the representation is binary vectors so for
binary vectors we have some standard methods
like using dice coefficient ok so what is
that ah two times intersection of x and y
divide by length of x plus length of y and
what do i mean by this so x and y are binary
vectors suppose x and y are binary vectors
and let us say ah the size of the my vector
the dimension are say since it is a nineteen
dimensions ok and my x is one one one one
in the first ten dimension and zero zero in
the rest nine dimensions on the y is zero
in the first nine dimension and one in the
last ten dimensions
ok so now i have two vectors x and y and i
want to compute the similarity between these
two vec vectors suppose i'm using dice coefficient
so the formula is two times x intersection
y divided by length x plus length y so this
is the length of x intersection y now what
is a x intersection y so that is only one
element ok so x intersection y has one element
that is one so this will be simply one two
times one length of x how many ones are there
ok so we'll not take the length of the vector
because otherwise it will be the same for
everything everything will have the same size
so length of x means how many entries are
one so here it will be ten for y also it is
ten ten plus ten so this will a point one
ok so now this is ok if you have the binary
ah values suppose you do not have the binary
values so suppose my values are like my x
could be point three point five point seven
point zero one and so on so if you want to
use these measures so one simple way could
be convert them to binary and now converting
would mean you would put a threshold that
if the value is below this threshold then
you put it to zero above this threshold you'll
put it to one so suppose here threshold is
point zero five so what you'll do this will
go to zero this will go to one this will go
to one this will go to one and here you'll
check whether less than zero point zero five
then go to zero if greater than then go to
one like that so you can convert any such
vector into binary representation and then
use this dice coefficient now are there some
other methods of computing similarity also
so we have jaccard coefficient and overlap
coefficient so jaccard coefficient is x intersection
y divided by x union y now what is the difference
between jaccard and dice in what scenario
jaccard will gave give a different value than
dice coefficient so let's try out the same
example so i'm using the jaccard as x intersection
y divided by x union y ok so in this case
what is x intersection y this will remain
as one only one entry is one and what is x
union y now x union y will contain all the
elements this will be nineteen so what you
are seeing for the same two vectors dice give
the value of point one and jaccard gives one
by nineteen that is closely point zero five
so this give much smaller value
ok so why is that so you are seeing here if
there are very small number of shared entries
jaccard further penalizes ok so that's what
you are seeing here there are very only one
entry common among twenty so jaccard is giving
further penalty
now what will overlap do so overlap is x intersection
y divided by minimum of x y so can you think
of a scenario where overlap it can becomes
one but say jaccard will not become one so
this will happen when ah one of x and y is
completely incoud included in the ah other
so so let us say let us take a different case
ah suppose my x is one one one one one zero
zero zero zero zero and y is one one one one
one one one one zero zero ok so in this case
what would be the jaccard it will be x intersection
y divided by x union y so this will be five
divided by eight and what will be overlap
this will be x intersection y divided by minimum
of x and y ok so this is again five and what
you mean of a x and y again five this will
become one so that is if if one of the vector
is completely subsumed by another vector overlap
is one ok and that will not happen in jaccard
dice coefficient and similarly if there are
a small number of shared entries jaccard will
give us smaller value so that means depending
on what kind of ah ah what kind of similarity
want to use you you can have either dice jaccard
overlap suppose in your task you want to find
out if one of the words is completely subsumed
by another you will use overlap and not jaccard
ok but if you want to see some other criteria
you can choose one of the three methods
so here so what you have seen jaccard coefficient
penalizes small number of shared entries while
overlap coefficient uses the concept of inclusion
where the one of the entries completely included
in the other one now this is a vectors of
binary vectors suppose they are ah real number
values so like x and y so the say the sa n
number of real number values so then you can
use simple cosine similarity or euclidean
distance
ok so you can use cosine similarity and euclidean
distance now what is the difference between
the two if the my vectors are not normalized
cosine similarity euclidean distance are different
ok but if they are normalized they will be
the same and they will give the same sort
of ranking and that you can do a very simple
exercise if they are normalized they will
give me the same sort of ranking between the
ah similarity of vectors now on the other
hand suppose my distributions are probability
distributions so i am devot denoting different
vector size probability distribution my space
of the context vectors
so then how do i compute the similarity i'll
use different measures that are used for computing
similarity or distance in the case of probability
distribution so what are the common measures
so you can use k l k l divergence is so that
is sigma i p i log p i by q i so this so k
l divergence is asymmetric ok so if you use
divergence between p and q and q and q and
p they will come out they may come out to
be different so that's why there is a symmetric
divergence also that is information radius
so p and p plus q by two and q and q plus
p p by two fo find the k l divergence between
these and add this that is information radius
and also you can use is a very simple formula
like l one norm so you have p i q i find out
the l l one norm
so what is the difference between p i minus
q i sum over all i so that is you have different
sort of representation and you can u use different
similarity value similarity matrix now so
let us talk about what are the ah different
what are some other sort of distribution semantic
models that all that also try to use some
specific instructions in the sentences and
we try to motivate them using this example
so that is what is the difference between
an attributional similarity task and a relational
similarity task so what is ash attributional
similarity so that is i'm given two words
like do dog and wolf and i want to find out
how similar they are so similarity between
dog and wolf will depend on how much their
attributes are similar that that's why it
is called attributional similarity and by
using distributional semantics how do you
capture that what are the other words they
are co occurring with are they co occurring
with similar sort of words if they are co
occurring with similar sort of words they
will have a high attribution similarity and
what is relation similarity so that is slightly
different
that is now i'm talking about pairs so that
is i have two pairs a b and c d are they relationally
similar that is how many co similar relations
that they have so example would be like one
pair is dog and bark second is cat and meow
so now dog and bark do they share similar
sort of relation as cat and meow so this is
simple different type of task ok and so this
that's why first one is called attribution
similarity how much the attribution similar
among the two words second is called relation
similarity i have the pair the relation between
this pair does that hold also for the other
pair ok and this also gives tries to many
analogy testing task so a is to b as c is
to what so we'll see how do we extend our
distributional seman similarity or semantics
models to also capture all these cases
now for that we will talk about a different
sort of matrix and this will be called pair
pattern matrix so till now you are talking
about target context matrix so let us see
if you can use a similar idea for building
a pair pattern matrix so what do i mean by
this
so here the row vectors will correspond to
various pairs of words like mason stone and
carpenter wood and the column would be various
patterns in that in the sentences these words
occur with so like here x cuts y x works with
y etcetera and then you compute the similarity
of rows to find similar pairs of words so
now so what what do i mean by this so till
now what we were doing we had words like dog
cat and i was finding out these representation
in various contexts so i'm finding out vectors
for dog vector for cat and trying to match
these ok and this was my simple attributional
similarity so now what am i doing i'm trying
to compute a similarity between pairs so now
my rows are different pairs so like the pairs
can be say dog bark cat meow or it can be
like here mason stone carpenter wood so like
that they can be various pairs now these are
my rows now what do the columns denote now
columns would be various patterns so pattern
could be like x cuts y x works with y and
so on these are various patterns now what
are x and y you can think of this as my patterns
x y sorry pairs x y
now what ha how will i fill this matrix simple
way would be i have x and y x can take value
like mason and y can take stone for a given
pair now i will go through my coppers and
see what are the various patterns in which
these words co occur with so suppose there
is a sentence mason works with or ah mason
works with stone or carpenter works with wood
let's take a sentence carpenter works with
wood so here so i have pattern x works with
wood x fits for carpenter y fits for wood
so i'll say ok there is a plus one here similarly
there will be all sorts of pattern here in
which x and y can occur and i'll fill which
pair occurs with what patterns so now this
is my pair pattern matrix pair pattern matrix
and then i can once i have this matrix i can
compute which pairs occur in similar patterns
and then they are called ah relationally similar
they have similar relation at the other pair
so so then so we can talk about the extended
distributional hypothesis this that much given
by lin and pantel so what is the idea patterns
that co occur with similar pairs tend to have
similar meanings so here we are talking about
in terms of our columns so here suppose what
they are saying if a pattern p one and pattern
p two if they co occur with similar sort of
pairs then they are giving similar sort of
meanings
ok and and therefore i can use this matrix
to compute semantic similarity of patterns
also so i can find out the semantic similarity
of the pairs also the patterns so suppose
i'm given a pattern like x solves y and i
want to find out what are other similar ah
patterns as x solves y how will i do that
i will first enumerate all the possible patterns
that can occur with with x and y then i find
out all the possible pairs how many times
they co occur with various patterns so i'll
fill this matrix and then i'll find out for
this pattern like x solves y what are some
other patterns that us that are having similar
pairs as x solves y
ok and what are patterns like x is solved
by y sorry y is solved by x ok suppose it
occurs with similar pairs as x solves y i'll
say that this and this are same and that will
be the idea its like here y is solved by x
y is resolved in x and x resolves y so what
do you find all these patterns occur with
similar pairs so they can be also called similar
now so now what is one thing so for dealing
with this pair pattern matrix words will not
be my basic context units so how do i capture
and represent this sort of information like
x solves y and y resolved by y x how do i
capture this information so for that i'll
need a formalism that can capture semantic
relations and also ah various syntactic information
can be captured and for that we will go back
to our dependency based formalism to capture
this kind of information what is the idea
so let us say ah i have a sentence like the
teacher eats a red apple so i can first formulate
a dependency graph for this sentence now i
can use this dependency relations to say that
only some sort of dependency relations are
interesting and others are not interesting
ok so for example i can say that eat is not
a legitimate context for red ok although eats
and red co occur with the very small distance
context window i can say that ok the relation
det object an and a modifier together do not
form a very nice context so i'will not use
this co occurrence so i can be selective in
choosing what kind of co occurrence information
i will use and what kind of co occurrence
information i will not use and i may also
give them different sort of weights so for
example i can say that the object relation
connecting eat an apple will be different
than the modified relation connecting red
and apple ok so this relation det object and
a modifier at can be different relations so
till now what was happening i was only seeing
if this word co occurrence with this word
or not
so now we have started talking about in different
terms this word co occurs with another word
in this context ok so with using a det object
relation with using an adjective modifier
relation and so on now so so from the parser
i can get all these relations so how do i
further use those so ah so we'll say that
to qualify as a context a word must be linked
by some interesting lexicon syntactic relation
so wha what do i mean by lexicon syntactic
relation a good dependency path should adjust
between the two words so in in simple terms
i can only use of use a single edge between
two words ok but in general you can also talk
about ah larger path larger len length of
edge between the two words so let's take it
simply for the simple paths of length one
between two words
so what will i do so let us see i have a sentence
the virus affects the body's defense system
and you get the dependency parse now from
the dependency parse i can extract the various
triplets like system det object affects body
possessive system so these are the various
ah topples i can extract from a dependency
graph so i will have things like this system
det object effects and so on now how do i
use those for my ah structured model so let
us try to ah have a look so we will have words
like system d o b j and affects yes and i
have many such pairs many such topples now
how do i use those for my distributional semantics
so there are actually many ways you can do
this so one simple way would be just forget
dependency information so that means you will
have system affects and so on so that is you
going back to your earlier relation where
you are not using the instruction so this
you can again convert into that kind of model
the word system is here and what is the co
occurrence with the word affects and you will
have one and so on there is one way so where
you forget the dependency information but
that's not what you wanted right you wanted
this information for some reason so another
option could be i combine dependency information
with the context so my context is now structured
so that is i'll have system and my context
is det object of the verbs affects ok so these
are my context now
so then i can represent system
in this context det object of affects det
object of other verbs and subject of these
verbs and so on ok so now you see immediately
my dimensions are different from here here
i had only words here i had verbs and some
relation together but i'm going back to the
same sort of matrix format and still i cannot
use this dog is to bark and cat is to meow
i cannot do it here now what is some other
sort of representation from here that you
can gather
so other could be i combine these two in my
rows this become my target and this come become
my context so that would be third would be
so like system and affects coming my target
and det object is my context so now we can
talk about my pair matrix so i have systems
and affects these are my pairs and pattern
right now only dependency relation det dependency
relation det object and subject and so on
ok and this is the general framework pair
pattern now here we are talking about only
very simple paths of length one what is the
det relation between these two words you are
free to choose a higher order path it can
be ok there is a path of length det object
n subject and so on and use that at your patterns
here
ok so so that can help you to capture all
these things like x solves y so you can also
use what are the different words that occur
in between these two words if there are some
other words occurring that can be your one
of the pattern so here you have complete freedom
of choosing what are your pattern so these
are simple dependency graph for for simplicity
but you can choose any other patterns that
you would like these patterns come from may
be dependency graph come from the word co
occurrence how what are the words that are
occurring between these words and so on and
then you can compute similarity between various
pairs
ok so now quickly so we have this data and
i can use that to get this information or
this the other sort of information or the
third sort sort of the information that we
saw now let us see one simple application
like how do we use that to find out selection
preferences of the verbs now what do i mean
by this selection preferences now different
verbs for their different argument like object
subject they prefer a particular type of noun
and this information is useful in many task
like dependency parsing so for eat i want
to know that eat will prefer only certain
ah sort of nouns as objects ok you can eat
only verys very ah specific things so like
so how do we compute this selection preferences
for verbs so we have seen that that from a
parsed corpus i can ah compute these vectors
like virus and system i can put them in this
space how many times car occurs as object
of carry so you are carrying car you are buying
car you are driving car you are eating car
and you are storing car and flying car and
so on
ok so what are the number of times and this
is some normalized values vegetables how many
times are they carried bought eaten stored
and so on ok so this you can compute from
the corpus once you have the parse so this
gives you some sort of representation that
what kind of objects come into that can be
used ah ah what kind of words that can come
as object of the verb buy what kind of words
will come as object of the word verb drive
and so on ok but suppose you want to build
a prototype that is in general what kind of
words can come as object of the verb eat from
the corpus here one simple thing i can do
i can find out which words has have a high
value so you know vegetables can be eaten
biscuits can be eaten so they have a high
value but suppose i want two hundred prototype
for a new wor the words that is not occur
in the corpus how likely it is to come as
a object of the verb eat so what will i do
so what is the simple method so i would say
ok let me find out what are the words that
are having a high weight in this dimension
so you know vegetables biscuits fruits etcetera
will ga will have a high weight in this dimension
now my hypothesis will be words that are similar
to these words like vegetable biscuits can
also be eat now how do i find out words that
are similar to vegetables biscuits and so
on so for that i'll build a prototype that
is ok what are these words so these are words
that can be carried bought stored right so
that means any other words set can also be
carried bought stored might also be ah eaten
ok so then i will find out all the other words
that have high weights in these dimensions
other than eat because whatever is having
high dimension eat i can easily capture here
but what are the other words that are having
high dimension in all these high weights in
all these other dimensions that also can become
my prototype
so what will we do suppose i want to compute
the selection preferences of the nouns as
object of the verb eat i'll take some top
n words like vegetables biscuit that have
high weight in this dimension of object eat
then i take the complete vectors so that is
of all these top nouns so this will words
like that can be consumed bought carried stored
etcetera now this becomes my object prototype
now given any noun try to match it with this
with this object prototype and you will see
that how likely it is to come as a object
of the verb eat and that is the generic method
of finding selection preferences of an word
noun for any ah word noun to come as a object
ah or subject for verb so we talked about
ah how do you extend your distribution semantic
method for using a structured models ok a
lot of work again a lot of research has gone
to this si this domain so you have already
touched the basic and i hope if you if you
need this idea you on your own you can you
can think about how do you use different sort
of interestings context interesting targets
and and solve various problems so in the next
lecture we will talk about another very import
important interesting idea that is what are
word vectors so and word embedding and how
do we obtain them from the corpus and and
what are different tasks they can be used
on ok so i'll see you in the next lecture
thank you