welcome back so so we talking about distributions
semantics so in in this fourth lecture in
the fifth lecture of this week we will talk
about another very interesting idea that is
word embeddings that come from distribution
semantics ok so what are word embeddings ok
so when i am talking about word embeddings
so they are like word vectors so ah so the
word vectors are nothing but simple vectors
of vectors of weight ok so you are so we talked
about these factors so its so you are having
some dimensions and they are representation
words in this set of dimensions on their various
weights
so now we also talked about this one hot encoding
that is among the n dimensions only one dimension
is one everything as a zero and these dimension
might correspond to the index of the particular
word that i wanted to be set
now and we saw that if i if we are using one
hot encoding i cannot ca ca compute the similarity
among words so if i motel and hotel there
will have one at different places and if I
compute similarity if i do and it will be
zero
so this is not ah conducive to for ah semantic
similarity between words so no let's take
a simple example so have a vocabulary that
contains only five words king queen man woman
and child so the so i have a I have vectors
in five dimension so i can encode queen like
this so queen has a weight of one in the second
dimension that correspond to the index of
queen and it has weight zero and other dimensions
and i cannot compute the how similar king
and queen are how similar queen and child
are by using this method
so we cannot make any ah meaningful comparison
we can only find if these two words are same
so that is not very interesting so what happens
in the distributional representation or so
we also called it word embeddings that any
word w i in the corpus is given a distributed
representation ok by in embeddings so i have
a fix dimension like d dimensional vector
and I represent each word in these d dimensions
and i have give them various weights and these
weights are to be learnt by some method and
we will talk about what will be the method
by which i will learn this weights so idea
is that each word in my vocabulary i will
try to represent them in some fix dimensions
d
so now so so this is one idea so like i have
the word linguistics and i can denote this
word in some fix dimension here d is eight
so there are eight dimension so they it has
different weights in different dimensions
and similarly all the words will be represented
similarly they have so different weights in
these a dimensions
so so what is my distributional representation
so take a vector with several hundred dimensions
so it can be hundred fifty three hundred thousand
now each word is represented by a distribution
of weights across these elements so each vector
is nothing but a distribution of weights across
these dimensions so what will happen so instead
of a one to one mapping between an element
in the vector and a word you have a ah distributed
representation of each words and by using
that you can cap capture similarity so whether
two words are ah similar or not if they have
similar weights in ah many dimensions then
they will be similar and that's how i can
capture similarity between words ok
and yeah so we we can say that each elements
in my vector or each dimension might contributes
to the definition of multiple words so what
the dimensions might indicate ok this is just
in illustration ah this is not ah a literal
meaning ok so thats what you can ah thats
what can you can help you to understand what
are these dimensions so suppose all the dimensions
in my distributional representation i can
label by some hypothetical ah labels ok so
my algorithm may not have some labels some
very ah good labels like that it may not be
possible to do that even manually but this
is simply for understanding that assume that
so there are d dimensions assumed that you
can assign a label to these some topic some
concept ok like here my dimensions can be
like royalty masculering famining age so on
these are my dimensions and assume that the
weights that each for is have in this dimensions
correspond to how much that word is closer
to that concept so for example the word king
word how much it is closer concept of royalty
so this king is very close to concept of royalty
it has a high weight in this dimension point
nine nine it is very close to masculering
so it is has a high weight point nine nine
but very small weight in famining age suppose
that a high weight means a ah it's elder so
it's point seven
similarly for queen what will happen royalty
will get a high weight yes but masculering
and famining will be just opposite and age
can be again ah three point six now take women
and princes women will have very low weight
in the in the case of royalty high weight
in the case so famining and princes will have
a high weight in the case of royalty and high
weight in the case of famining and very low
weight in the case of age and this is simple
simply for illustration so idea is that i
am trying to represent all my words instead
of fixed dimensions and these dimensions are
latent they met correspond to certain concepts
a combination of concepts and so on that may
not no that the algorithm also does not assign
but we would assume that that these dimensions
correspond to some concepts and now each word
can be return as a distribution among these
concepts ok and then i can measure to words
based on how much similar they are on various
concepts this is the idea ah main question
is how do i capture this representation that
how do i represent different words in this
fixed dimensions
so now we can see that so such a vector is
representing the meaning in some abstract
manor so now what is my ah dimension size
so my dimension d can be if we starting from
fifty up to thousand ok and the by ah focus
is that the word that are similar in meaning
they should have similar embeddings or similar
representation
now if you know about ah s v d singularly
de decomposition that is also some sort of
embedding method that converts the vectors
in some low dimensions so i will i will i
will encourage that you read about singular
that valid decompression also another another
name for that is latest symmetry indexing
but i will just give you very briefly what
is the idea of s v d so we talked about ah
this co occurrence matrices ok so this is
my matrix a so these are the target words
these are contest words ok and this matrix
has certain entries now what is one problem
is matrix this might be very high dimensional
so each word might have a say five hundred
k dimensional representation so so what did
what this is co occurrence with different
words and this words can be age number of
words can be age age five hundred k and even
more in some cases so now i want to give a
low dimension representation a distribution
representation so what will the idea so i
will use the theorem that any matrix say can
be written as u sigma v transport ok and there
are certain properties of these u sigma and
v but this sigma is a diagonal matrix and
the n this are singular values ok second here
about it what is this matrix particular decomposition
for singular values now once you have this
matrix in this format this is same matrix
so idea is that you take a k rank approximation
so that means you have singular values they
are is in the decreasing order and you take
only the top case singular values and you
do that for all this u sigma and v so we have
taking only top k and t so only the first
k entries of you corresponding to top k singular
values that is u k sigma k v k transports
ok and this is my k rank approximation of
my matrix a ok
so now this u will denote my low dimensional
representation so earlier you might be in
the same ah dimensions you can be again in
ah five hundred k dimension ok five hundred
thousand but suppose you you you are trying
to pick only hundred you will take only ah
first hundred dimensions from here ok and
this will be a low dimensional representation
for u v and so on so s v d is also one sort
of ah embedding so each word you can embedding
some ah k dimensions by taking the top case
singular values only so but we are not talking
about s v d here we will talk about the word
vector method for computing this representation
so now before i discuses what are the different
task sequence do with these word vectors oh
ah sorry how do you compute these word vectors
let us see what why they are found to a very
interested in in in this domain and what are
the different task they have been used in
so what is we found that these representations
are capturing some meaningful syntactic and
semantic regularities in a very very simple
manor so what is that so that is we can use
the vector offsets to talk about ah relation
between words and how how much two words ah
are similar compare to the other pair of words
so for example i want to capture the singular
plural relationship between word like car
and cars boy and boys bag and bags and so
on and suppose i do not know what are singular
and plural words so can i capture that using
word representation
so what does we will found suppose that for
each vector x i u ah for each word i you are
vector x i so we can take the vector offsets
and they will be coming out to be similar
for ah singular to plural pair so that is
if i try to compute x apple minus x apples
that is coming out to be very close to x car
minus x cars similarly to x family minus x
families and so on that is i compute the vectors
of these and if i take the vector offset apple
minus apples has similar offsets as car minus
cars as family minus families and this is
very very interesting this is not something
for which this vectors for trained for but
they are capturing this ah regularity very
ah nicely so this would be like and and and
because they capturing such regularities they
can be used for various reasoning task like
enology task a is to b as c is to what so
like man is to woman as uncle is to and you
will answer aunt but can my model answer that
man i have given man woman pair and for the
next pair the first word is uncle what be
the next word can you find out aunt and that
is what the word vectors have you found to
be very useful in they can predict these ah
enology sort of task and how do we do that
this just use the simple vector offset method
so let us see one example so here so this
is the idea so i have my vectors denoted in
a two dimensional plane so how do you come
convert any say hundred dimensional vectors
to it two dimension representation you can
use principle component analysis p c a or
some other methods to project them into some
lower dimension so that is been done here
so two dimension representation so what you
are seeing here so that outside would be woman
and man that is similar to what has been observed
in uncle and aunt and king and queen and this
is a very nice regularity
similarly here for singular plural king to
kings and queen to queens they having similar
offsets so we can use that for enology testing
so what is the enology testing task you are
given a pair with a with a certain relation
like france and paris what is the relation
so paris is the capital of france now we are
given various examples and we have to find
out which of this examples attribute the same
relation so that is whether itally rome has
its relation of capital and country japan
tokiyo and florida tallai tallahassee which
of these has the same relation so can my vectol
vector representation ah capture this so a
given one example can you find out the other
example and so so similarly for big bigger
can you find out this small ah smaller cold
colder quick quicker and miami florida can
you find out other examples so on
and how do they do that so i have this task
a is to b as c to what so example is man is
to woman x king is to sorry ah man is to woman
as king is to what and how will they do that
so simple idea is take the vector offsets
between woman and man and add it to king ok
so find out woman minus man add it to king
but how do you find out the word queen in
generate may not be then exact match so how
do you find out what words are coming closer
so this the idea so i have a is to b as c
to what ok so so what will happen in my vector
representation a b and c i want to find out
what is the word d so what will i do i have
the vectors of each of the words so find out
the offsets w b minus w a added to see now
i am trying to find out which vectors or similar
to this ok i write it this and were what are
the vectors are similar to this one and so
i will just find out ah similarity of that
to all the words w i in my corpus and i can
also normalize it w b minus w a plus w c ok
so that is a normalize all this is not very
important and we take the argmax over all
w i in my corpus so all words are vectors
so i find out which words are coming closer
in this is space so what is the closer words
to by when i add this offsets to this word
and that is my answer ok so so for example
if you do this here so will find that the
word queen comes up
and this has we shown in many different cases
like country and capital vectors china beijing
russia moscow japan tokyo and the what you
are seeing here the offsets between the vectors
are very very regular in all this cases and
this is just coming out from the word vectors
and more questions like news papers so new
york new york times baltimore and balitmore
sun san jose san joshe mercur mercury news
and so on various n b a teams detroit detroit
pistons an and so on airlines austria austrian
airlines belgium brussels airlines and company
executives what do you seeing it is capturing
a generic relation also in journal any relation
that that that can hold between two words
so if if you are finding out two words with
one relation you can find out some many other
words that i having the same relation by simple
this vector offsets method so find out vector
offset between pairs is it similar to the
vecs vector offsets of my initial example
so this is the problem we also tackled in
the case of ah instruction models of distribution
semantics that is we have making the pier
pattern matrix and then capturing the co occurrences
in the in the case of word vectors even you
even though you did not is start by piers
and battles even the though you you found
out only with the word embeddings word vectors
this helped further in doing this task also
and this was very ah one of the very interesting
aspects
similarly here we can do element element wise
addition so suppose you have the embedding
for a german you have embedding for airlines
and if you add these two embeddings and find
out words that are coming closer to to the
new vector now and you find out some very
interesting words coming up like here check
plus currency and you find out word that very
close vietnam plus capital again words setup
very close german plus airlines you find lufthansa
airline and lufthansa a carrier so on russian
plus river you find words like moscow french
plus actress and you find some transact message
and this was again some interesting accept
so you can have embedding of two words and
you add these gather if find something that
is some sort of composition of these term
so not a generic method so this was coming
out in some cases may not be true for all
the cases but even coming out in some cases
for what in interesting observation
so now how do we capture these word vectors
how do we compute this word vectors now basic
idea is we will again go back to the co occurrences
we will trying to use co occurrences but instead
of counting the co occurrences from a coppers
what we will say i am given a sentence a word
is there and the contest is there try to predict
the contest from the word or the word from
the contest and if you not able to predict
try to update your weights and this will be
the idea ok it start with some initial vectors
using those vectors try to predict from the
contest what to do the targets of on the target
what will be the contest if it is not machines
update your vectors
and so all the codes ah as well as the learned
vectors are available here so we can actually
download these and and and try to use them
for many of your task also but you will discuss
how what are this word vectors in how to they
so in general there are two different variation
of this models so that tried to capture these
word embeddings and they are called c b o
w for continues back of words model and ah
skip gram models and let me just quickly explain
what are these and we will discuss in little
in the next lecture so in continuous back
of words model what you are doing so you're
taking the contest so you are focusing on
the current word w t we taking the previous
words so it can be actually any number of
previous words and to next words and your
trying to use those to predict the center
word so using the contest pred predict the
target word or the center word
in the skip gram model what you are doing
you are using the center word and trying to
the context words so there are two different
ways of learning is embeddings so idea would
be i will start with some initial vectors
now trying using the context vectors i will
try to predict what is my center vector if
i am not finding the match i will update my
r different vectors send for send the as well
as the context and I will keep on doing that
until i am able to predict this some high
confident or i am i am converging at certain
point my vectors are not changing and these
vectors that I am learning by this method
will be my word vectors ok and i do that slightly
different in both continuous back of words
model and scripts come model
so in the next lecture what we will do we
will discuss in detail how do we learn this
vectors ok
thank you