so hello everyone welcome to the fifth lecture
of this week so we are talking about word
embeddings so in the last lecture we discussed
the what is the different ideas behind using
word embeddings what what can be some interpretation
given to the different dimensions here and
what are different tasks where you can use
these word embeddings but we do not go through
the learning part how do we actually obtained
these word embeddings for different words
so today in this lecture we will try to discuss
in detail how do we obtain these embeddings
so so in the last lecture we discussed that
there are two different models for word embeddings
so for their main to main models one is continuous
back away words model and another is skip
gram model what is the idea there in continuous
back of words model using the map neighbor
neighboring words i am trying to predict the
center word in a skip gram model using the
center word i am trying to break the neighboring
words
so let us see what we do will c b o w model
so here let us say we have a prose like this
the recently introduced continuous skip gram
model is an efficient method for learning
high quality distributed vector representation
and so on so that i data that i have so much
and i am i am trying to learn representation
for various words embeddings so at a time
i will go through one particular window here
so i will focus on a word so let us say i
am focusing on one ah word like learning ok
so what i will do i will take a window around
that word now window size can vary and this
can be a hyper parameter that you will choose
so you can chose a i will take forward before
there and forward after that so using these
eight words around this word learning i will
try to predict this word learning so how do
we do that so yes so imagine is sliding window
over the text that includes the central word
and with four words that precede and the four
words that follow it like here learning is
my focus word and there are four words before
it and for words after that and you can also
call that as the context words and usually
the context words you are trying to break
the focus word so so this is some sort of
network representation and how this learning
will take place
so you are seeing here in the input you have
a so input you have various column vectors
so what do i mean y this so here so what you
are doing here you are putting in one hot
encoding as the input so i have this column
vector of size v
so the column of size v now so v is the size
of my vocabulary i have that many words my
vocabulary so i may not use this only v ok
v is the size of my vocabulary now in your
context your heading having certain word that
will be there in the vocabulary so let us
say this is the index of that word so this
input would be everything else a zero and
this will be one ok so one hot encoding of
that word so column vector so like that in
you are context suppose you have here eight
words so we will feed all these eight one
hot forms so here it might be one here zero
here it might be one somewhere and everything
else zero ok that is your input that you are
feeding now using this input then you are
having a hidden layer this is n dimension
ok i remember this n will be important we
will see what is this n
so now the size v now i want to map these
two this n dimensions so i will have a weight
matrix let us set up do one of dimension so
this is ah v cross one sorry so this you can
take it as one cross v so you will have it
h v cross n ok so that the final representation
is n dimensional now so you will have the
same weight matrix at each input so you will
get and then you can take the average of all
these now from these n dimension you again
go to your v dimension this is you are output
layer so what will be the second weight here
this will be n cross v ok see i starting with
a v dimension going to n dimension and hidden
and then going to the v dimension in the output
now so what you are doing here so before going
into what are the connections a network you
are putting some input there are your context
words so suppose you are having eight different
one hot vectors and whatever happens here
finally you are trying to create your ah center
word this should be your center word ok so
what will happen here you will have various
weights w one w n some numbers you will w
v some v different numbers you will get
and you want to ensure that the actual center
word suppose this is my center word this is
the highest probability and if it is not having
the highest probability you will try to modify
the weights in your network so that it it
it gets a higher probability then what is
getting right now
so now let us see what do we mean by all these
connections ok so what would happen from here
so let us go back to the slides so each word
is encoded in one hot form that is here we
have a single hidden layer and an output layer
so you are having two different weight matrixes
one is v cross n another n cross v ok so so
from input you go to hidden from hidden you
go to output output you are trying to predict
the ah the center word so what is my training
object is here so you see i am getting some
word some numbers for different all my v words
at the output layer and this you can think
of as the probability value and you might
have a question that how do i convert these
numbers to probability we will see that so
assume that you having v different probability
values now you want to maximize the conditional
probability of observing the actual output
word given the input context word with regard
to weights
so you say that i want to maximize the probability
that i will obtain the actual what that i
saw in my input and not any other word so
whatever probability i am getting that becomes
my objective function so i want to maximize
this condition probability of output word
given all my input words and this probability
will be express in terms of all these weights
that i am having in my network so in our example
what would happen i am giving this input all
these eight words an efficient method for
high quality distributed vector and i want
to maximize the probability of getting learning
as the output this my centre word
now so what happens from input to the hidden
layer so input we are saying you are feeding
one hot vectors so if there are eight different
input words i am having eight different one
hot vectors now what do i mean by multi bank
this one hot vector with my first weight matrix
the dimension we cross n so you can think
of it like that so you put using an input
so this is one word and having a corresponding
ah element is one that that is my input word
and you are multiplying it with v cross n
weight matrix so this operation is nothing
like this nothing but you are taking the corresponding
row of this matrix this matrix has v different
rows so these v rows you can think of as if
corresponding to v different words in my vocabulary
so whenever you are feeding a one hot form
of one word you are picking up that row ok
and so you are doing it for a different words
so you are picking a different rows in my
ah initial weight word weight for matrix and
then so you are having given c input words
so activation function for the hidden layer
will be simply summing the corresponding hot
rows so i will pick up the hot rows here that
correspond to the input words and divide by
c so that i have an average representation
so now you understand what is going from input
to hidden layer you are taking ah c different
one hot c different rows from your weight
matrix and averaging those thats what goes
in your ah hidden layer now what happendes
from hidden to output layer so remember we
have a ah second weight matrix w two that
goes from hidden to output layer and its dimension
is n cross v so now a hidden layer dimension
each one cross m so if i multiply this one
cross a matrix with this n cross v matrix
i will get a one cross v matrix ok and that
is my output layer so these one cross v matrix
even think of as having weights for different
words in my vocabulary and i want to maximize
weight for my center word ok so from the hidden
layer to output layer the second word matrix
w two can be used to compute a score for each
word in my vocabulary and now so you can obtain
the weights how do we convert them to probability
values and for that you use soft max what
is the idea of soft max
so here you will you get the weights w one
to w v they can be any real numbers ok now
how do you convert that to probability distribution
so this is a simple idea that is in soft max
so in soft max what you do is you are given
w one to w v and you want to convert that
to a probability distribution so you will
see that i simply multiply all these by so
i will put an exponent over these so e to
the power w one e to the power w v now they
are all positive numbers and then to convert
them to probability i will just divided by
summation over e w i for all i ok
so now this is this will some off to one because
this is normalize and these are my probability
distribution so i have these weights i use
a soft max to convert them to probability
values and then i will try to maximize the
probability of my actual center word this
will become my training objective and based
on that i will learn my weights ok so i will
i will talk a bit about this learning problem
in the when i go to the next model of escape
ground but suppose we have some way of learning
these weights and finally i have the optimal
set of weights w one and w two now where are
the word vectors what are your word vectors
here i am feeding one hot vector this is not
being learned this is the same so where are
my word vectors being learned now if you think
about it so what i am learning are the weight
matter research ok this is off v cross n this
is n cross v so i can take a transfer this
also will become v cross n so you can think
of it as if for each word you are learning
a n dimension representation ok so after you
learn this matrix these weight one and wait
two will correspond to your ah word embeddings
ok
so w one will be of size so w one will be
of size v cross n so you can take any vector
i and get a n dimensional representation and
the sign you can also think of as your d d
dimensional representation ok so for each
word you are getting a d dimensional vector
similarly for w two you will get similarly
if you take a transpose you will get a v cross
n representation and in general what you what
you do you can take a ah so you are getting
two vectors one for from w one one from w
two so we can finally combine these two vectors
you can either concatenate these vectors or
the same word or some these over or taken
average and that works fine so this is the
addition about what is the kind of network
that you use for learning these embeddings
ok so these weights are nothing but my embeddings
that i am learning ok so this is about continuous
back of words model now what will happen skip
gram in a skip gram model the network will
slightly change so now i will feed only the
center word here only one input vector but
i will predict multiple contexts words ok
so now from input to hidden there are only
one so the only one input vector but output
there are multiple vector so let us look at
the skip gram model skip gram model is the
opposite of c b o w model so so you have the
center word as the sing single input vector
and the target context words are at the output
layer this is my output layer and you can
now very easily correlate with what we did
in c b o w so the the weights correspond to
roughly the same idea
so now let us formally define so we see how
in the using the network we can think about
the learning how the learning will take place
and how the weight updates will take place
but suppose you want to write it mathematically
and how do we do that so so yeah this is very
analogues to what we find the case of c b
o w so here from input to hidden layer i am
simply copying the row from the weight matrix
w one so i am having only one input so i will
copy only one row and that will go to my hidden
layer now at the output layer we will have
see different distributions and i will try
to predict the see different context words
using my hidden layer and objective is to
maximize the some prediction errors across
all the context version my output layer so
you want to predict although so i want to
maximize the probability for observing my
actual context words so let us say we have
a window where i am having ah small c words
in the left small c words in the right so
what can be my training objective it can be
i am trying to maximize suppose i take a log
probability w t plus a given w t w t is the
center word and i am going from minus c less
than equal to j that is equal to c window
of size c around j and j is not equal to zero
and this i can do for all possibility all
possible center words and this becomes my
training objective ok so we will see that
so i am predicting surrounding words in the
window of length c of each word my objective
function is i want to maximize the log probability
of any context word given the current center
word so i am trying to maximize this probability
probability of w t plus j given w t and sum
over all the possible context words and then
i can sum it over all the possible words in
my input and this becomes my overall objective
so j theta and theta of all the parameters
all the weight matrix w one and w two that
i am trying to learn
so now this is my objective function and i
want to maximize that ah and by doing that
i want to learn my parameter theta and how
do we do that so firstly let us see how will
be compute these probability probability w
t plus j given w t now this will be actually
you have already seen that in the case of
ah using the network but using which ah some
mathematics can be show that so idea is that
let us say i am having a probability for p
w o given w i w i is my context world and
w is the output word that is the i am sorry
so i i should say as the center word and this
is my output word these are all the context
words ok let us say for a given context words
how do we write it and i am saying we can
write it in this form that is exponent v prime
w o transpose v w i divide by sum over w is
equal to one to capital w v prime w transpose
v w i ok and these are formulation of this
probability and let us try to understand that
so whatever different is we have written here
so one thing you are seeing there is a v and
there is a v prime so for each word you have
two vectors one is v another is v prime so
v is for the so v is use only for the input
center word and v prime is use for output
so when i am trying to use the input word
to pre the output word i will simply take
a dot product of these now both both is vector
like column vectors so v w i will be of this
form
and v prime w will also be as a column vector
so how do i get a number by multiplying these
two i will take a transpose of this ok and
multiplied with this and thats what i am doing
here v prime w transpose times v w i that
gives me single number now this number i want
to convert to a probability value so then
i am using a softmax over that exponent over
this number divide by i will do it for all
the words in output ok so hey thats why i
have a summation over all the words w is the
total number of words in my vocabulary this
is nothing about a probability distribution
and you can see that summation p w o given
w i for all words w o will add to one because
because of this normalization factor so this
is added to word this is giving me a condition
probability of w o given w i now as a simple
exercise you can also try to see how this
number comes from the network that we talked
about ok so so we had a networking interpretation
now we have a simple matrix short of interpretation
so how they correspond to each other and they
use the idea that word one sorry weights one
and weights two what are these weights weight
one correspond to the input and way to correspond
to output use this idea and see that by using
the network also are you getting the same
form of this probability by putting x softness
over the output layer and you will you will
see that you are actually getting the same
form so now i have this formulation w o given
w i this particular formulation and i put
it here for all the words in my context and
this becomes my j theta
this is my objective function now what is
my objective i want to learn my v an v prime
so i will try to learn my v v and v prime
such that this is optimized and for that there
is a simple ah way that is you can use getting
descent algorithm so you can try to take partial
derivative of j theta with respect to each
of these parameters and update your weights
accordingly so so this is the ah probability
condition probability distribution function
that we have found and v n v prime are input
and output vector representation of the same
of the same word w so every word has now two
vectors
so suppose i have d dimensional vectors so
d is my ah so so d is the dimensional of my
hidden layers in network terms or for each
word what is the representation that we using
we using dimension representation so i have
the many words so what is the size of my parameter
theta so i have ah capital v words for each
word i have been input vector and output vector
so there are two v vector and each vector
of dimension d so i have two d times capital
v that many parameter slower this should my
whole set theta and what is the ah simple
gradient descent formula so this is like you
take the derivative with respect to the ah
that particular parameter so so theta j new
is theta j old minus alpha is my learning
date and you take a partial derivative of
j theta with respect to the parameter when
putting the old values
now i i i am supposing that you know the idea
ah gradient descent that is used to optimize
your minimize a particular function ah so
if i want to give this idea very briefly so
this is like suppose you have a simple function
like this and i want to find out for what
parameter theta of what parameter x will suppose
this is a function over x and this my y for
what value of x this is minimized so what
i will do i will start with n e x ok so suppose
i am starting with this x zero i will find
out the value of function so i i go to the
function so why is suppose f x zero now i
want to know what is the value of x where
there is minimized so what i will do i will
take the derivative of the function at this
point f prime at x zero and so now if i have
to minimize if this direction of my gradient
i have to go in the opposite direction of
my gradient so my new value should be x naught
minus f prime x naught so i will go into opposite
direction and i will use some learning rate
with what rate you will go in this direction
and this is simply the idea of you keep on
doing that so you go somewhere again you find
our suppose you are going at this point ok
so now your gradient will point you to this
direction so will try to go in this direction
again gradient will point you some direction
and finally you will converge so this is a
very simple idea of gradient descent but i
will suggest that you have a look at it that
what is actually the gradient descent
so this is simple function but your function
can be over multiple parameters so like here
i have my theta two d v dimension so i have
two d times capital v many parameters my theta
is a function my j theta is a function of
all these parameters so what i will do i take
a partial derivative with respect to each
of these parameters and accordingly update
those parameters and this is how it will look
like so we are not going in in doing the derivation
because that wont be in the scope of this
course but if you are interested you can try
to find out if i derive this form what update
values do i get for different what vectors
how do i update these vectors and now once
i have done that i have two different vectors
v and v prime and i can simply some these
over and that will give me the final embedding
for each word and if you want to understand
more about how do we learn these parameters
so you might have a look at this paper and
this gives the nice tutorial for parameter
learning and also if you want to try out an
interactive demo so you can try out here
now so so what to work is one famous model
and the such two variation c v w and skip
gram and both are used so in some tasks skip
gram has shown to be better in some c b o
w has shown to be better and there are many
other tricks that i used for learning these
parameters that we have not covered i have
only tried to give you the intuition so i
hope you will at least have an idea that how
these word vectors are learned from my data
by just predicting neighboring words from
the context or context from the neighboring
word and what is the embedding so how these
weight vectors for my embeddings
so now there are some other models so one
other popular model is glove model ok and
so so what is a basic cognition of glove model
when so in this skip gram so i am trying to
learn my ah all my embedding from scratch
ok so in glove model what they are saying
so from a coppers you can kind of count the
co occurrence see know with so thats what
we did in the distribution semantics we would
counting co occurrence now what they are saying
so this gives a very good idea about the words
so which words are similar to what are the
words and suppose you find out what is the
co occurrence probability for any towards
now try to make word vectors such that when
you do a dot product between towards you get
close to the actual co occurrence that you
are seeing in the corpus
and by doing that you will get a low dimensional
representation and also it will take care
of the words that are coming very sparsely
where you do not have enough data in the corpus
to predict the co occurrence and this is the
simple objective function so that is if you
look at the objective function so forget word
f f is a few simple function that that make
sure that if certain words are certain co
occurrence we are very very popular you do
not bayes your learning towards those see
you just clip those at certain point so everything
above that will be converted to this one
now what so this is the main idea here of
this glove vectors so you are having in word
definition for i and j that you want to learn
an idea is try to learn them that are that
such that they are resembling their whatever
you get from the co occurrence probability
so p i j is from the co occurrence you can
use either p m i condition probability or
many other things so find out w i w j such
that they are close to this co occurrence
probability and then we have these objective
function and you optimize this objective function
and try to learn your different weights so
so you are trying to combine the best of both
words using the count based methods and the
direct prediction methods and using both of
these you are trying to come up with your
word vectors and these vectors have also become
very very popular because the training is
much more faster then then my skip gram model
because now you are not going to the each
individual word in your and all the windows
you have already computer the counts now you
are only looking at the pairs word pairs and
one maximizing that and so even with the small
corpus and small vectors they have shown very
good performance
so so one good thing is that suppose you want
to use this vector finding of your task so
either word vectors or glove vectors are freely
available on different websites so what do
we already told the website in the previous
lecture for glove you can go to this stanford
website and there you can download code as
well as the vectors and these vectors you
can use for many of your tasks where you are
trying to find out whether two words are similar
or you are trying to find out some analogy
task a is to b then c is to what and many
other application they have been used in so
i think this is what i had to say for this
tropical distribution semantics this is a
very ah very well growing research field and
lot of new thinks happening so i hope whatever
we have discussed will help you to to also
understand the papers in this field if you
want to going in further depth and also you
can try out these ideas for many of your applications
so in the next week what we will do so we
will start with a separate notion of semantics
that is leska semantics so how to use lexicon
to find semantics between words
thank you