so hello every one welcome to the week eight
of this course in the last week we had started
a discussions on semantics and we discussed
a particular method for caption semantics
that ware distribution semantics so how we
can use the distribution patterns of words
in a corpus to extract meanings out of that
and we said that how we can compare two words
to find out if they are more similar than
an an another pair of words
so so in this week what we will be doing we
will be taking another approach of semantics
that is by using the connections that we see
among items in an lexicon and that's where
we will also see how to use a very ah important
resource that is word net for extracting meaning
some ah between words so so topic for this
week is lexical semantics
so how can we define lexical semantics so
as a as i am saying what we are doing in this
topic we will see some entries in a lexicon
and we will try to identify what is the relation
between these generatives so we will have
some particular set of relations and we will
try to defined these relation among these
entities so so in that way we can define this
this field so lexical semantics is concerned
with the systematic meaning related connections
among lexical items so i will have a certain
lexical items in my lexicon and i will try
to find out what are the connections between
any two items and we will be also see what
are the internal meaning related is structure
of individual lexical items
so what you are seeing here we are not focusing
our attention to something called a lexical
item so what what is the lexical items so
so lexical item i there is another term for
that this called lexeme so this is this is
nothing but an individual entry in my lexicon
so here i am talking about connections among
different lexical items and what is the single
entity it will call a lexeme and we will mostly
we talking about in terms of lexemes now so
if we try to understand intuitively what would
be there in an entry in in an lexeme entry
what what are the things that i need to keep
in an entry so because i am also talking about
the meaning if a word as multiple meanings
it should not be called like a single lexeme
it should be called as two different lexemes
so when i talk about lexeme what all things
i need to have i need to have what is the
form so how do i spell that how do i pronounce
that and also some something that says what
is the meaning of this particular entry so
these are the two important components that
make like a lexeme so i will have so i can
think of lexeme as a pairing of some orthographic
and phonological form that is how do you write
the lexeme how do you pronounce that and with
some sort of symbolic meaning representation
ok something that might be definition of the
lexeme or something that explains what this
it's stands for
so when i talk about orthographic form and
phonological form they are the the form part
of the lexeme and then i have a science part
of the lexeme that talks about the meaning
of the lexeme so if we have seen in various
dictionaries that's all the entries are also
defined so let me take one example so this
is example from the dictionary that comes
with mac so you are having a a suggest single
word like verge but it appear size three different
lexemes so we are having verge one verge two
and verge three ok and do you do i see the
pair the form part in the meaning part so
form part is giving on top for each entry
so i have the spelling so that is the same
for all three then i have the pronunciation
also ok then there is there are certain descriptions
about this entry that that correspond to what
is the meaning of this entry
for example you might have the lexical creditory
of that so it's a noun it's a noun it's a
verb and then there is some meaning like an
edge or border they they come they come down
to the verge of the lake so also given an
example how it is used and some history of
the words also provide it so when i talk about
lexeme that's what i need i need a form part
that can be the spelling of the lexeme plus
the pronunciation and the meaning part once
i have done that now we can try to establish
relations between various lexemes in my lexicon
or each lexical items in my lexicon
so now what are the various meaning related
facts you can extract from the with the lexemes
and defined in my dictionary so let's take
some examples from this heritage american
heritage dictionary so is nineteen eighty
five version and what we are seeing here we
are seeing four different entities here right
left red and blood they are four different
lexemes in my in this dictionary and some
meaning of these entities are also provided
so so for example right is defined as located
near the right hand especially being on the
right when facing the same direction as the
observer and left is defined as located near
to this side of the body then the right so
this is some definitions provided to these
lexemes
now what is something that you can immediately
ah some point that you can immediately see
from the these definitions so one thing that
you see is that the word right has been defined
terms of right this is some sort of circular
definitions if you say if you say in that
way and also lexemes are defined in in terms
of other lexemes ok so like here red the color
of blood or a ruby and blood is defined the
red liquid ok so blood is defined in terms
of red and red is defined in terms of blood
so we see that there is some sort of circularity
involved here in the in the way we have defined
in the lexicon
but even even if that is the case you can
still extract some sort of meanings for example
if you see the definitions of right and left
you can easily find out that they are somewhat
related they mean their meanings are very
much related and you might also say that they
might be in some sort of ultra[vation]- with
respect to each other ok
so so what do we see here so the entries are
description of lexemes in terms of other lexemes
and from the definitions i can see that right
and left are some similar sort of lexemes
and they are in some sort of alternation or
opposition also from these definitions we
can see that red is some sort of color and
and it can be apply to blood as well as ruby
and blood is some liquid so you might extract
some other facts about the lexemes also from
these from these entries
now in general so when i am talking about
identifying what is the connections of different
between different entries what are the various
formal connections that have been defined
and what are the relations that we can study
so let us have a look at some of the relations
so so these are some very important relations
that are established between word meanings
and forms so like homonymys polysemy synonymy
antonymy hypernymy hyponymy and meronymy and
you might have heard of some of the list terms
like polysemy which very very popular and
similarly synonymy and and antonymy so these
we might already have heard so let us try
to formally define what are these relations
and and when do i say that to and it is my
lexicon are connected by a particulation from
one of these
so how do i define homonymy so homonymy is
defined as a relation that holds between words
that have the same form but unrelated meanings
so what is that mean so we have defined an
individual entre entries in my lexicon as
having if form part and a meaning part so
now if two entities have the same form part
but the meaning part is different then they
will called the homonymys ok you think of
an example of ah two such or a single word
that as the that as ah same form but two different
meanings so simple example might be like the
word bank bank and before the financial institution
bank or it can be some river bank similarly
bat it can be for the cricket bat or it can
be the bat as a mammal so what you are seeing
here they are having the same form but different
meanings
so these are two examples that that we talked
about now so there is one important thing
that you should remember here so we are seeing
that they have the same form but different
meanings but we have defined form to be both
orthography form and phonological form so
it might happen that it in certain cases the
orthography form is same and meaning is different
and in some cases the phonological form is
same and meaning is different they are called
homonymys but there are specific terms for
both of these and these are called homographs
if there is the same orthography and homophones
if there is the same phonological form let
us see some example so homophones are the
words that have the same pronunciation but
different spellings ok and different meanings
also so example here are write and right there
is the same homological form they are written
differently and their meanings are different
same with piece and peace and homographs would
be the lexemes and that the same orthographic
form then they would have may be the different
pronunciation and different ah meaning all
to gather so for example the two different
usage of bass one in the sense of in the sense
of a guitar or music
now now why do we need to worry about this
ah homonymys so we will see what are the different
n l p application where they create a problem
so ah let's take this example of text to speech
so do you think these homon homophones or
homographs would create a problem for ah text
to speech so what do we do in text to speech
in text to speech you would have a text contain
written it can be a sentence where there are
multiple words together and you need to speck
that out so why the homophones or homographs
can create a problem for that now think of
the same ah same word that as the that as
the particular spelling but it is pronounce
into different ways into different meanings
so unless you know what is the particular
sense it's being implied you cannot pronounce
it properly ok
so if the of orthographic form is same but
the phonological forms are different that
creates a problem for text to speech now it
can also create the problem for information
retrieval so so why the problem for information
retrieval so suppose you are looking for the
term bat ok and by bat you implied the the
mammal but sup the suppose the systems gives
you ah cricket bat as as the ah desired or
as the ah page edge that that you will look
for and immediately it will not match your
information need
so what would happen if the same word as multiple
meanings if you are searching for that word
because your only a specifying the the orthographic
form it is not it may not be clear to the
search engine what is the meaning that you
are looking for so this also create a problem
for the search engines
and it might be problem for the speech in
also for example the perfect ah homonymys
ho homophones where you have the same phonological
form but different way of writing that so
suppose you are writing to ah suppose you
are speaking to so it may not be clear which
of the three words should be ah the correct
interpretation whether it is to or to or two
t w o t w o ok so these are also problematic
for i speech reorganization so these are some
problems where they they create problem ah
now so suppose the the systems have to deal
with that so how do they find out when i am
talking about to is it t o or is it t w o
t t double o and for that they have to use
various information from the context in which
that is spoken or something about the speaking
and so on and some of the problems of this
kind we will also deal in this week in the
topic of word sense disambiguation that if
a word as multiple meanings how do i use the
context to identify what is the particular
meaning is beings used here
so now coming to the second relation that
is polysemy so polysemy and homonymy might
be confused with a certain times so polysemy
is also the same sort of relation that is
a word as multiple meanings but the same form
but the difference here is these meanings
are very related and not unrelated tight we
had in the case of homonymys so in case of
homonymys two words have same form but very
different meanings for polysemy they have
the same form and slightly related meanings
ok not not very very similar and not very
very different also
so what is the example let us see ah let us
focus on the word bank here in the two sentences
in the first sentence we see the bank was
constructed in eighteen seventy five out of
local red brick and second one is the the
sentence i withdrew the money from the bank
so as such if you if you look at this sentences
you may feel that so there the same word bank
is being used in the for the same sense but
if you look closely you find there is some
slightly def some slight difference between
the meanings of the word bank so what is the
difference here in the first sentence the
bank is used as some sort of building that
belongs to a financial institution ok on the
other end second sentence it belongs to the
financial institution itself and that sort
of ah slight gradation in meaning is is there
in many many such words for example let us
look at these two sentences heavy snow caused
the roof of the school to collapse and the
school hired more teachers this year than
ever before so again the same word school
is being used an as they look the same sense
but again if you look closely this refers
to the building of a school and this refer
to the institution a school as such or their
administration
so and and these relations are called systematic
ok so for example if you look at these words
school university hospital church supermarket
all of these can be seen as the building as
such or the institution and that's why the
two meanings would be ah slightly related
they are not very very different and not exactly
the same there are some other examples like
you can have the men the ah connection between
the author and the works of author so if i
say jane austen wrote emma some talking about
the author on the other hand i if i say i
really love jane austen so what do your meaning
is that i really love the works of the author
so author in works of author again appearing
some sort of slightly different meaning side
that is that is ah observed by ah this term
polysemy
similarly animal versus meat so when you chicken
it can be animal or meat similarly sometimes
it can be tree versus fruit and this kind
of relation like if i say plums so if i in
this sentence plums have beautiful blossoms
plums mainly refer to the tree but here i
ate a preserved plum would be a fruit so again
there are very very slight distinction between
the meanings here
now ah ah in in linguistics so suppose i want
to distinguish ah identify if the if the same
word is being is into different sentences
it is been used in slightly different ah meanings
ok all is it is the word polysemys somehow
so what is one particular linguistic test
that we can do and this test is called zeugma
test and what is the idea suppose the same
word has been used in two different sentences
now try to compose a single sentence where
the word has been used only once and the two
different ah usages have been captured by
some sort of consumption and see if this sentence
is making sense already is looking weird if
the sentence is making sense ok so probably
this word as the same sense in both the sentences
but if the sentences looks weird then you
ok there are polysemys
so here is an example so i have the same words
serve being used in two different sentences
so which of these flights serve breakfast
and does midwest express serve philadelphia
now i want to find out if there is some polysemy
involved in the usage of the word self here
so what i would do i would combine these to
ah usages together in a single sentence so
what can be one sentence we can compose out
of this so you can compose like does midwest
express serve breakfast in philadilphia ok
and immediately we are serving breakfast in
philadelphia putting them together in the
same sentence looks weird ok you can put them
in to a different sentences ok but putting
them in same sentence looks weird then we
can say that so these two usage of the words
are are polysemys so here does midwest mist
west express serve breakfast and san jose
if you put them together it ah sounds weird
so we say that they are two different senses
of the word serve
so so that's what we have covered homonymy
polysemy remember they are very very ah it
may not be easy to distribution among the
two in polysemy they are quite related in
homonymy they are very very different in general
if you might also you might in in general
you might say that word is you note that the
word has multiples senses now the next relation
that we will see is synonymy what is synonymy
two words that have very very similar meanings
but different orthographic and phonological
form so examples are like couch and sofa they
have same meaning different words big and
large automobile car water h two o ok so now
what is a important here is these two words
are similar meanings but probably they are
not substitutable in all the contexts ok for
example in scientific context you might want
to write h two o but not water but when you
are all talking in general terms you would
use the term water crossing you to give give
you water you will not ask give you h two
o ok so so all though the meanings might be
very very singular depending on the context
you use one word or the other
so as such we can call two lexemes are synonyms
if they can be successfully substituted for
each other in all situations but this not
actually the case we cannot in general you
cannot substituted them in all the places
you can probably do them most to the places
but not so now let's take an example so i
take two words big and large and let's see
these sentences how big is that plane i can
also write how large is that plane so would
i be flying on a large or small plane so with
word plane i can use the word either big or
large and both are substitutable here so in
that sense they look like perfect synonymys
but can i always replace big for large of
large for big in all the contexts let's see
this example suppose i have the sentence miss
nelson for instance became a kind of big sister
to benjamin ok and suppose i replace big by
large here and the sentence comes out to be
miss nelson for instance became a kind of
large sister to benjamin and immediately you
can see that this this usage of word large
immediately it starts looking weird ok and
why is that the case so that means we cannot
substitute large for big big here ok and and
why is is that
so because you would you would see that big
has a very very specific sense that is being
grown up or elder and that sense never applies
to the word large ok so big has a sense of
being older or grown up but large as such
lacks this sense it does not have this sense
sometimes they are very shades of meaning
in an some sort some words of being preferred
to use them other words like when you are
talking about what is the cheapest first class
fare we will talk about you will prefer to
say fare then price ok sometimes there are
collocational constraints so with some particular
words only one word goes not the other one
even if they have very very similar meanings
for example before mistake would you ah like
big mistake or large mistake generally big
mistake is preferred so here this is the sentence
so we frustrate e m and frustate e m and pretty
soon they make a big mistake ok and we would
not substitute large here so large mistake
is not collocational but big mistake is collocational
ok so because of language usage also some
words are preferred to be used then others
so they cannot be substituted at all places
probably in some places
now coming to the next relation that is antonyms
so here i say that so what is the general
ah notational the general ah definition of
antonyms two words if they are entirely opposite
to each other they are opposite to each other
but this is something interesting about antonyms
so two words antonyms if they are completely
ah so we we said that they are they are having
very very opposite meanings but in general
if you look closely they will have very very
related meanings but they are opposites only
in word particular aspects so let's take one
example see like hot and cold ok so so do
you call them are they related or are they
very very diff very different so as such they
are related they both talk about temperature
yes but they are at the ah opposite ends of
the history extreme so we will say ok it's
cold one extreme and hot is the other extreme
but as such both talk about temperature
and ah suppose you you try to use the distribution
semantic method that we tried in the last
week to capture if two words are antonyms
it might become very very difficult because
we would occur in very very similar contexts
yes so hot and cold occur with words like
weather yes temperature and so on so so what
we are saying in antonyms they are having
very very ah similar meaning but they are
opposite only in one aspect of the meaning
so like dark and light short and long ok hot
and cold up and down in and out they are opposite
only in one aspect otherwise they are similar
so more formally we can say that and antonyms
can define some sort of binary opposition
or at opposite ends of a scale so like long
and short hot and cold fast and slow and be
reversives it's like rise and fall now coming
to another important relation that is hyponymys
and hypernymys now what are hyponymys and
hypernymys so they are relations between a
subclass and a super class ok so so formally
we say one sense is a hyponym of another if
the [fir/first] first senses more specific
and a denotes a subclass of the other so example
here is like car car is a subclass of vehicle
so we can say that car is a hyponym of vehicle
similarly dog is a class of animal so we say
dog is a hyponymy of animal and mango is a
hyponymy of fruit because mango is a type
of fruit
now just the other other way round the relation
would be called hyponymy so i say mango is
a type of fruit so fruit is a so so fruit
is a super class so mango is a hyponymy of
fruit and fruit is a hyponymy of mango ok
so conversely we can define the hypernymy
relation also so vehicle is a hypernym of
car and animal is a hypernymy of dog and fruit
is a hypernymy of mango and these are of some
of the relations that we will ah see very
very closely what is so how do we use hypernymy
relation for extracting various meaning related
facts among entities
so with hyponymys we can also defined some
formal ah criteria so for example entailment
if i say that sense is a hyponymy of sense
b that means being an a entails being a and
b for example as a dog is a hyponymy of animal
dog is subclass animal is super class so being
a dog entails being an animal as it's some
some entities dog it is an animal so it will
have all the characteristics of animal also
impose on that and but you cannot say the
other way round that is some ah if someone
something is a dog animal it is also called
dog this is not valid so if a is a hyponymy
of b i will say being an ah a entails being
an b you can also define the transitivity
relation that is if a is hyponymy of b b is
a hyponymy of c then a is also hyponymy of
c that is also very very trivial condition
on hyponymys so entailment in transitivity
now we can also define other relations like
meronymys and holonyms so meronymy is some
sort of asymmetric but transitive relation
between senses what is that so i will say
x is a meronym of y if x denotes a part of
y so it's not symmetric so example is so here
porch is a part of house or wheel is a part
of car so to define the part of relation i
say wheel is a meronym of car leg is a meronym
of chair nose is a meronym of face and the
other where round relation is called holonym
that is face is a holonym of nose car is a
holonym of wheel and so on
so now so so we saw what is the different
relations that we can defined among lexical
entities so now ah what are what are the different
lexical sources where these relations are
nicely captured so where you can you can find
out what entries are related by the relation
of hyponymy hypernymy and meronymy and use
for different ah tasks or application that
you want to bit and that's what we will see
in the next lecture then we will ah have a
discussions on what is the structure of word
net and how are all these relations defined
in word net and how can you can use that to
capture various semantics like ah whether
these two words are related or not and to
word degree that will be the ah topic for
the next lecture
thank you