yes welcome back to the second lecture of
this weak so in the last lecture we started
with lexical semantics and we defined the
relation between lexical entities and we talked
about ah polysemy hyponym hyponymy meronymy
and and so on and and in this lecture we'll
see resource wordnet and how it captures all
these relations
so wordnet you can you can get a lot of information
of wordnet on this website so its an its an
effort started at princeton and there are
lot of versions that that have come up and
you can you can find out the latest version
of wordnet and also download that and you
can use that also in once you download you
can use that in your command term[inal]- terminal
also so what is wordnet wordnet as such is
a hierarchically organized lexical database
ok and its completely machine readable
so you can you can use that in in different
applications you can call wordnet get get
the recent information from there so as such
on this website you will find the wordnet
for english but there are other so there are
many many other versions for other languages
also also built so there are lot of wordnets
available for european languages and a lot
of effort has happened in the last decade
for building wordnets for indian languages
and that you can also ah download many any
many of those versions are also available
for download for free so for that you can
look at indo wordnet ah website so ah so there
you will also find out what sort of synsets
or concepts in one language are relate to
some other concepts in other language
so this information would be available in
this ah in this indo wordnet and and euro
wordnet websites so now div now we will focus
only on the the english wordnet part in this
in this ah lecture but the methods would be
easily applicable to other wor[d]- wordnets
that are having shared by single structure
so if we talk about english wordnet so there
are mai[nly]- mainly four different part of
speech words that are ah and there and what
we are seeing here how many different synsets
are there for each part of speech so there
are roughly eighteen thousand ss synsets for
nouns thirteen thousand plus synsets for verb
and eighteen thoudsand plus synsets for adjective
and three thousand plus for adverbs now so
so one important thing is that we when we
talk about wordnet we talk in terms of synset
now what is the idea of a synset in wordnet
so in synset what will happen so there is
different words that have similar meanings
will be stored but a single word might have
multiple meanings also so how are how are
both of these things taken care together so
so lets take an example
so ah so example is particular synset corresponding
to chump that is a noun and that is a person
who is a believable and easy to take advantage
of and suppose chump the first synset this
programme meaning so word has have might have
multiple synsets so chump first synsets is
this meaning but there might be other words
also that have the sense and so this word
its nine sense denotes this particular meaning
so i have to say that the word mark its nineth
sense is this meaning the word fool its second
sense is this meaning the word goal the first
sense is this meaning and similarly fall guy
and so on so what i will do here each word
might be represented by multiple synsets so
a word might have sense one sense two sense
three and so on and what i will do if suppose
the third sense of word one and second sense
of word two shared the same meaning i will
put them in a single synset and that is the
idea of synset different words that share
a same meaning and by words here i will mean
the lexim ok or a particular sense and for
wordnet this list might denote what is the
meaning of the word chump or you will also
find some gross information of the wordnet
so now this also this figures some so[rt]-
some sort of explains what is the relation
between the word form or the lemma and the
synsets so what you are seeing here so there
is many to many relation so that is for example
the word note it can go to note and to end
bullenthri so denotes two different synsets
in one sense it goes to note synsets another
sense it goes to bill synset but this bill
synset will contain note and also contains
bill and some other words ok so what you are
seeing here many different lemmas that share
the same sense can come together in a single
synset and the same semma same lemma for different
meanings can go to different synsets and that
is captured by giving some unique identifies
to different two different synsets of the
same lemma
so i will start talking about now lime one
lime two lime three instead of just saying
lime ok and each of these three will be ah
in different synsets so what are all the possible
relations that ah that you see in wordnet
here is some example so in wordnet you have
relations like antonyms hypernyms hyponyms
entavment relations synonyms and so on ok
many of these we have already seen in the
previous lecture lets see some example types
of these relations so like what are the relations
between ah various ve[rb]- nouns so the relation
hyponym that we discussed so hyponym is relation
between a concept and its super concept ok
so like breakfast is a kind of meal so i was
a meal is a hyponym of breakfast so this relation
will be there in the wordnet where the breakfast
one synset or the corresponding sense its
connected to meal one by the relation of breakfast
is a hyponym of meal and meal is a hyponym
of breakfast similarly the converse relation
of hyponym meal and lunch member so faculties
in so professor is a member of faculty harinstins
is composer in instins s bash austin is a
instins of author member maronym like capital
is a member of crew part maronym from whole
two parts
so table to leg part holonym the other way
round from parts to whole coarse to meal yes
and antonym that is a opposite diden follower
so what would happen all these relations are
defined in wordnet you know what what the
relation means and then you can find out for
a word collision what are the different pairs
or given pair in the wordnet is there any
realtion ah that is defined similarly there
are relations between verb elements also like
hyponym fly and travel so fly is a kind of
travel so travel would be the ah hyponym for
fly tropoynym from a verb to a specific manner
for that verb like walk and stool so stool
is a typical manner of or a particular manner
of walking they can be eh entanment relation
also from verbs to the words that they end
till like snoring and sleeping so i'll say
snore and tell sleeping so this is also relation
that is captured in wordnet and then there
can be antonyms for the opposites so increase
and decrease they are antonyms for each other
further in wordnet we can also capture ah
what is the complete hierarchy of a given
concept and what do you mean by hierarchy
that is starting from the root word and wordnet
how do you go down to that particular word
ok what are the different concepts that you
need to pass through and that you can find
for all the different synsets for the for
a given word and so thats why we said that
ah wordnet is very very hierarchically organized
database so you can find out or you can locate
each concept or a subset ah each synset in
that complete hierarchical tree so for example
if i see the word mouse so i'll find it has
four synsets so for sense one mouse you can
find out the complete hierarchy so mouse is
a kind of rodent kind of placental kind of
mammal vertebrate and so on up to animal living
thing object physical entity and entity ok
you can go to the root of the wordnet entity
starting from this particular sense of mouse
here is another sense of mouse that is a computer
mouse again you can keep on going up the hierarchy
electronic device device artifact object physical
object physical entity entity and you can
see where do they depart so mouse comes under
whole then an artifact and this mouse comes
under living thing thats where they depart
in that ah in that wordnet hierarchical tree
and this we can do for any any sense any word
word in the wordnet you can find out the complete
hierarchy now so so as such wordnet will always
store which two concepts are related by wap
relations and ah suppose car an automobile
occur in the same synset if you query in a
wordnet there is a very easy way you can query
in wordnet ah and you can find out if they
are part of the same synsets then you can
say ok they are similar but suppose two words
are not part of any sense any particular synset
in wordnet and i want to give it a number
like to what degree are they similar similar
to what we ga[ve]- did in the case of distribution
semantics we found out how much two words
are similar to each other by seeing how much
their patterns are similar so can i do sim
something in the ca[se]- case of wordnet that
is given two concepts or two words how similar
they are even if they are not part of the
same synsets so so by using synonymy i can
only see that the two words are synonymous
or not but suppose you want to do the matrix
for word similarity or word distance so what
are the different things in wordnet i can
use
so in wordnet there are many other relations
also defined so i can also use the fact that
whether there is any other kind of relation
between these two words or do the words do
these words share a common hypernym hyponym
and so on also you might have a have a look
at the gloss of these two ah entit entries
whether their glosses are very similar so
so i i'll say two words are similar if they
share many different features of meaning and
if features can be captured in terms of ah
how many relations are common how many words
are common in their gloss and so on now one
thing that then that we must keep in mind
when we are talking about establishing relation
between different en[tities]- entities in
in wordnet we are talking about relation between
different synsets and not the words ok because
a word might have mutiple synsets and the
relation that is there in in one sense of
word one ad one sense of another another word
may not be there in the ah other other synsets
so so for example here so ah for example is
a word bank this is sense one this is in the
sense of you can say in the economics and
sense two is like river bank ok and then they
have i have another word like fund ok and
there is s one that is for economy so as you
see that this sense one of bank is connected
to this particular sense of fund but i cannot
say that this is connected to fund this is
not true so i cannot say that bank is connected
to fund saying that will not be correct what
i will say sense one of bank is connected
to sense one of fund so we'll talk about relations
between synset of words and not word directly
all though we'll try to extend it later to
the words ok so instead of saying bank is
like fund i will say something like bank one
is similar to fund three suppose that is the
third sense of fund and bank two is similar
to slope five the fifth sense of slope and
so on
now we will also compute similarity over words
and synsets both so let us see how do we do
that by using the wordnet hierarchy and any
other information that we have so now this
is something that that we have talked about
earlier that if i want to find out similarity
between words there are two two ver[ry]- very
popular methods one is by using distribution
algorithms and that we discussed in in detail
in the last week there i can find out the
distribution patterns of two words and compare
those but if you wa[nt]- if i want to use
a lexar resource like wordnet so here can
i use the idea that some words are more near
in the wordnet hierarchy than others so if
two words are near in the hierarchy i might
say they are similar if they are very far
apart in the hierarchy they might be different
so can i use this idea to establish if two
words are similar by using the ah wordnet
resource and we'll we'll so we'll now see
lot of such methods of doing that so so as
such i can use any relations like maronym
hyponym troponym glosses examples yes but
in particular with this sort of based methods
that that we have they mainly use the e j
hierarchy tree the hyponym hyponym relation
tree sometimes we will also use the glosses
of the of the words so we'll start by seeing
some examples or some particular ah ah methods
that ca[n]- that try to use the the hierarchy
wordnet hierarchy to capture the similarity
between between the words and then we'll also
see a particular method that uses the glosses
of the of the different synsets to capture
their similarity now so one thing that that
you might ah have seen or have understood
by know that by using all these methods we
are not capturing the synonymy as synonymy
as such we are not seeing that that we are
finding two words that are very very similar
what you finding is that two words that are
related or are used in similar sort of context
and topic so like if i take car and bicycle
they are quite similar but car and gasoline
they might be related but not similar
so by these methods car and gasoline might
come come closer but all that means is that
they are related they may not be exacty similar
so now now coming to the methods to capturing
similarity across words so what is the first
idea first idea is to use the path between
two words in the hypernymn graph and what
can be a simple measure i will say that two
words are similar if the path that connects
the two words in the in that hierarchy is
small ok so two words are similar if they
are nearby in the hypernymn graph and to give
a formal measure or quantity to that i can
define the path length between two concepts
so path length between two concepts what will
be that that is the number of h h in the shortest
path in my graph between synsets c one and
c two so what is the length of the shortest
path that connects c one and c two in my whole
graph now once have have found this path length
how do i use that to compare the similarity
between these two concepts so that is path
length is large they are less similar if path
length is small they are ah very very similar
so my similarity should be inversely proportion
to the path length so one measure can be one
divided by one plus path length and this is
one simple measure that is in which the path
similarity between two concept is one divided
by one plus path length of c one and c two
so thats how we can find out the relation
between two synsets so now suppose i want
to extend that to find the similarity between
two words
so one way is to i find out similarity between
all the synsets and take an average but a
more ah commonly extended measure is find
out similarity between all the possible ah
payers of synsets between the two words and
take the maximum ok so what you mean by that
suppose i have word one word two that is sense
s one one s one two s one three and this a
synsets s two one s two two ok so by using
this measure i can find similarity between
any two pair s one one s two two what is the
similarity similarly i can do for all these
pairs now how do i establish similarity between
w one and w two so that is similarity is the
maximum value of similarity between s one
i and s two j you take any sense for the the
firs[t] first word any sense for the second
word whatever the maximum similarity between
between a pair this gets me the simi[larity]-
maximum similarity or the similarity between
these two words that is a very simple way
in which i can extend all these ideas to word
similarity so in whatever we will see ah in
the ne[xt]- for the next methods we will also
alway[s]- all always talk about similarity
between synsets and extended for similarity
between words so i will say similarity between
words w and w two is nothing but the maximum
similarity between any of the synset of the
word one and word two so lets take an example
that how what will this ah path way similarity
look like so this is my wordnet ah hyponym
graph so not all the notes are shown only
if if very few notes are shown so we are starting
with entity abstraction measure standard although
with entity there will other concepts here
then you are you are coming to a particular
branch with where you have medium of exchange
currency coinage coin nickel and so on
now i want to find out similarity across two
different concepts so what is similarity between
nickel and coin so i will say what is the
path length path that connects nickel and
coin what is the length of this path so here
the length is only one so similarity between
these two concepts will be one divided by
one plus one to point five and what is the
similarity between nickel and dayne it will
be one divided by one plus path length and
path length is two so it will be point three
three and if you see nickel in a very different
concepts like richard scale so here you will
find similarities point one to five because
the path length is seven so like that i can
capture the similarity between two concepts
by using the path length
now there is ah another similarity measure
along the same lines so this is called l c
similarity so what it says the similarity
between two concepts is minus log of path
length divided by two d so this is just a
sim different function over path length so
earlier we had a function one divided by one
plus x now they have function minus log x
divided by two d ok and what is d here d is
the maximum depth in my my hierarchy ok wha[t]-
so starting from the root note what is the
maximum depth of a ah hierarchy for any any
of the leaf note and and this helps in that
this ah this path length will always be less
than or equal to two d and this will give
me a similarity between these two concepts
so ah so what is the problem with this l c
similarity or the previous similarity that
we have seen so what they are saying for any
two concepts find out the path length and
and one and the similarity is nothing but
a function of path length if path length increases
the similarity decreases but when problem
with with these approaches is that any two
pairs of concepts if the path length is same
the similarity will be the same irrespective
of wherever they occur in the tree
so let us just go back to the previous tree
so what these approaches will say so what
is similarity between coin and nickel the
path length is one similarity is one divided
by one plus one that is point five but what
would be the similarity between entity and
abstraction their path length is also one
so their similarity will also become one divided
by one plus one so that is point five but
ideally what would we want do we want the
similarity of entity of entity abstraction
to be the same as between coin and nickel
so if we think about it as we are going down
in the hierarchy we are moving to very very
specific concepts so while we are moving this
specific concepts the same path length should
amount should amount to a higher similarity
noun that it was doing earlier so entity and
abstraction this similarity should be much
lower than the similarity this similarity
should be very very high but these methods
as of now as of now do not capture this idea
so they will have this path length to contribute
same way as this path length so now can we
do something different so that here the similarity
becomes high but here similarity becomes low
so so you want a matrix that lets us assign
different lengths to different average so
so the ah so what is the idea that we will
be using and for that we use the idea of concept
probability model now what is this so ah so
in the wordnet whatever concepts we are seeing
we will assign them into probability so what
is the probability with which i see this concept
in a corpus now idea would be whatever i am
seeing in my corpus is an entity because its
part of the tree where entity is the root
so whatever word is in the tree is an entity
so in the other word whatever word i am saying
in the corpus is an entity but it may not
be an abstraction so there will be some words
that are abstraction and some words that are
not so what i will do whenever i encounter
a word i will find out what are all the concepts
to which it contributes and i will add a count
to all these concepts and finally i'll give
i will convert them to probability values
so what would happen the root note will get
a probability of one because every everything
i see is a is an entity but as you go down
these values will keep on decreasing i'll
use this idea ok to convert them into log
log values and then taking the difference
between the two values as the path length
ok and that can converted to finding the similarity
between two synsets so so let us say p c is
the probability that are randomly selected
word in the corpus is an instance of c so
what would happen probability of root is one
and a lower a note in the hierarchy the lower
is its probability and how it can be estimated
these probabilities we count something called
concept activations in the corpus so what
would happen whenever encounter a nine i'll
also increment a call for coin currency standard
etcetera
so what is the idea so i have a wordnet hierarchy
tree is starting from root that is my entity
and going down so what would happen suppose
this is my word x whenever i encounter this
word x x in my corpus i increment its count
by one and all its parents because whenever
i am encounting encounting i am also encounting
this concept and so on so what would happen
whatever i encounter i always add one to the
root ok but only to its parents so when i
do that root will have so all the counts will
be added to root and i can find the probability
by dividing everything by the count of root
so so suppose i do that on my corpus so this
is one example so so here you can see there
are one point nine million roughly instances
overall because entity has been ah always
ah appended with one but their num[bers]-
the numbers are different so diamond and nickel
has only eight and ten coin has thousand hundred
and eight ok so you see the we are not showing
the whole tree thats why there will some other
branches of coin also that are not here now
once i have got these counts i know opt in
the probability values by dividing everything
by this number
so this will be my concept probability now
how do i use this concept probability to define
or define my so what i will do i will convert
them in some in some information value what
is the information content of each concept
and the information contemp content can be
directly obtained by the probability values
by using minus log probability ok idea is
that if the probability of something is very
high it does nt have much information but
the probability is low it contains a lot of
information so i use the information content
of a concept as a minus logarithm of the probability
of that con[cepts]- concept so i can do that
for all the concepts and i can also define
what is my lowest common subsumer that is
if i take two notes or two concepts c one
and c two the lowest common subsumer is the
lowest note in the hierarchy that subsumes
both the notes or what is the is the lowest
note in the in the tree where these two concepts
meet
and now you can see how you can use that ah
computing similarity between concepts so these
by using from the probability if i take minus
log probability the other different numbers
i will get so minus log one becomes the different
numbers i will get so minus log one becomes
zero then point five minus six and so on now
what is something that you are seeing here
so as you are going down these numbers are
increasing so one simple way of capturing
ah similarity between two words is by seeing
what is the lower common subsumer and what
is the information content of that so nickel
and dime what is the similarity path length
is two but the lowest common subsumer that
is coin has a information content of seven
point four five five on the other hand if
i take these two concepts medium of exchange
and scale their common lowest subsumer standard
has an information content of six point one
one
so immediately you can see this this can be
said to have a higher similarity than this
pair ok so what are the formal method by which
we can capture this so one is resting similarity
so that says how similar two words are depends
on how much they have in common so that is
find out their lowest common subsumer and
find out their information content of that
and that will denote the info the similarity
between these two concepts so it measures
the commonalty by the information content
of the lowest common subsumer ok so like here
nickel and dime the similarity would be the
information content of the l c s that is coin
so similarity between them is seven point
four five five now nickel and money similarity
would be the information content of their
l c s that is medium of exchange so that would
be six point two five five and so on ok so
now immediately you can see that as you keep
on going up in the hierarchy the similarity
will be decreasing so to be highest when you
have took single leaf notes but if you keep
on going up the similarity will ah decrease
so this capturing what you wanted to do but
still there is one problem here so can you
find out what is the problem so one problem
here is if i find the similarity between coinage
and money this would be same as similarity
between coinage and budget yes because their
l c s is the same so here what is being captured
is that how much information they share but
what is not being captured is how much information
they do not share or how much they are different
so we have a different measure for capturing
how much information they do not share and
this is called lin similarity so it says that
ah the similarity this measure is not about
just commonalities we also have to capture
the differences so the more information they
share the more similar they are but the more
information they do not share the less similar
they should be ok
so accordingly the lin similarity between
two concepts is defined as two times logarithm
of or two time information content of th l
c s divide by information content of the concept
plus information content of the concep concepts
so while doing that what would happen now
if i take the similarity between coinage and
money this would be six point two five five
times to divide by seven point four one nine
plus eight point zero four two and if i take
the similarity between the coinage and budget
it will have a term of ten point four two
three in the denominator instead of eight
point zero two four two so immediately this
similarity will become lower than this similarity
so lin similarity is a much more well accepted
measure than the ah the previous measure that
we have seen the resting similarity there
are some variations here so for example the
jc similarity
so what they say in jc similarity find out
or give a value to each h that is a distance
between two concepts and this would be the
information content of the concept minus the
information content of the hyponym and i can
define the distance between two concepts as
their distance so how do i go from one concepts
concept to its ah l c s and second concept
to it its l c s and i just add the distances
and i compute similarity by taking the inverse
of this distance so what am i doing here i
am having different notes in my hierarchy
yes and suppose that you have already found
what is their information content ok so what
do you do in in the case of resting similarity
in resting similarity the c one c two c three
and this is c zero in resting similarity the
similarity of c one and c three is nothing
but the information content of c zero so as
per resnic similarity of c one c three is
i c c g one ok as per lin similarity this
would be two times information content of
c zero divide by information content of c
one plus information content of c three now
in jc similarity what you would do you would
count you would find out the distance this
is distance is nothing but c one minus c zero
and this distance is c three minus c zero
so for gsc similarity it will be c one minus
c zero plus c three minus c zero is the distance
between these two concepts and the similarity
between the one divided by that ok and thats
what is written here information content of
c one plus information content of c two minus
two times information content of the l c f
of the two and the thats what you can say
here i c f c one i c f c three minus two times
i c f of a i c s so i hope by this example
you understood what is the difference between
resting similarity lin similarity and jc similarity
and among these lin similarity is very very
popular ok
so i hope it is clear that how do you apply
these three different similarity measures
so here you have example that a if we use
the jc similarity what is the different values
you will obtain among different concepts so
i'll ena increase that you will you try and
find out that say suppose between nickel and
richard scale or between nickel and coin can
you obtain the same values by by applying
the formulas so now i will ah ah also talk
about briefly the other approach for computing
similarity between two concepts in in wordnet
so till now we have only used the the hierarchy
tree in wordnet and i am saying two words
are similar if they are nearby in the in the
hierarchy tree or some other formulation and
that that we have seen some examples now suppose
i want to use their glosses the way their
the different concepts are defined in wordnet
for comparing similarity so these are very
simple algorithm called lesk algorithm also
have a extended lesk version that is used
for that and what is the idea two concepts
are similar if their glosses contain similar
word and the word drawing paper defined as
paper that is especially prepared for using
drafting and decal the art of transferring
designs from specially prepared paper to a
wood or glass or metal surface i want to find
out how similar they are
so what i will do i will see how many words
are common there so as such you are seeing
that three words that are common paper especially
and prepared ok that a kind both the glosses
so what algorithm does is that it counts how
many n grams are common so n gram in the sense
of one unigram bigrams and trigrams and so
on see you will see that this bigram is specially
prepared is common to both the glosses glosses
and the unigram page is common and whenever
an n gram is common it adds a score of n square
so that you have is given for a commonality
of bigram trigram and so on so in this case
what would be the similarity one bigram is
common so two square and one unigram is common
and one square so similarity would be two
square plus one square five ok one plus four
five that is the similarity of using lesk
algorithm now so so we have talked about what
are the different ah relations we can capture
using wordnet and we have also seen how we
can find out similarity of across two words
and that looks like very simple method once
the wordnet is given and you might ah also
wonder this might this might be a better method
of capturing similarity than ah distribution
similarity ok because i i have a manually
created this orders i know which of the words
occur where in the tree i can simply use the
distance or measure to find out how similar
they are but there is one ah inherent problem
in using wordnet for any of the task
so can you think of what is the problem so
so let me give you the hint if you know if
you want to capture similarity across synsets
wordnet is very good it can capture the similarity
between the synsets very nicely but if you
want to catch similarity between words that
is very difficult now when we encounter natural
language we will only encounter the words
and when we see the words we do not know what
are the synsets that are being used so i cannot
directly apply wordnet there because i do
not know the sense i can only do an approximation
where i can find out ok i am assuming this
word corresponds to or i am i am applying
the methods i used for synsets for the words
ok this would be an approximation and it works
sometimes but does not work some other times
so to be able to apply wordnet to be able
to use wordnet one important problem that
we have to deal with is i need to find out
if a word is used in in a particular sentence
what is the what is the wordnet sense that
has been used for that ok and that is is difficult
problem that we will try to address but this
problem is very very common and we will just
take a very simple example for that so we
see very sim[ple]- very very easy sentence
i saw a man who is ninety eight years old
and can still walk and tell jokes yes this
is a very simple sentence now for the simple
sentence what do you think are there many
different synsets of this word or this whole
sentence or there is one interpretation so
when we when we hear this term this sentence
we have only one interpretation in mind but
in wordnet what are different synsets of individual
words so let us see so if i go to wordnet
the word saw has twenty five senses man has
eleven senses age has four jokes has four
tell has eight and so on so now if you combine
if you combine all these together they are
as a sixty seven million plus senses that
are possible sentence this might look like
a very extreme case but you might have examples
where they are multiple divisions for the
same sentence and different words can have
can occur in multiple synsets so my problem
is if there are so many synsets how do i find
out what exact synset wordnet is being used
and thats where we'll talk about the problem
of word sense among the many possibilities
dissimilate the particular sense of the word
and that we will start in the next lecture
thank you