so welcome to the third lecture of this week
so so we are talking about lexis semantics
and there we delt with what are the various
relations we can establish between the word
form so we were talking specific ah in traditional
now that are lexemes different items in my
lexicon and we also talked about word net
that what are the different relations we can
establish between various lexemes word net
and what are the different standard forms
like using sins at and what is the hierarchical
award net how do you use the define word similarity
and so on and finally we ended up the saying
that there is one in head problem engaging
word net that is when you get a new sentence
you do not know what is the particular sense
of the word that is being use in the sentence
so you cannot apply the methods vary directly
so so thats fair so we deal with this problem
that given a sentence for each word find out
what is the sense in the word net that is
being used here and this problem is called
versions disambiguation so very classical
problem in n l p and let lot of research has
happened in over last few decades so we will
ah talk about what are the most important
methods for dealing with this problem and
we will talk about both simple approaches
and machine learning based approaches and
also some unsupervised approaches so we will
cover that in the next two lectures starting
today so this is our topic that is word sense
disambiguation
so let me just define the problem again so
we have seen in this week that there are many
words that are having several meanings and
then we can call them different senses of
the same word so now example can be of the
word bass so you can use bass or base depending
on that they you want to use that in the context
of fish or music now the problem is whenever
you are given this word i will be talking
about music or fish you know ok so lets see
these two sentences here the first sentence
is an electric guitar and best bass players
stand off to one side not really part of the
scene just as a sort of nod to gringo expectation
perhaps this is one sentence and the second
sentence is talking about some trip bass in
in lake mead were too skinny so now the same
word is being used in both the sentences and
i have to find out whether the word is being
used the sense of fish or music now once you
see the sentences how do you find out that
what is the meaning of of the of this word
in the sentence you will try to look around
the context in what context this word is being
talked about accordingly you will chose one
sense over and another one now this whole
the field of words has disambiguation
so this deals with this problem that so i
have to find out the sense of the word depending
the context know how can i do that computational
so so so we can define the task of the disambiguation
that is to determine which of the senses of
an ambiguous word is invoked in a particular
use of a word so we say we are doing this
problem only for the ambiguous words whenever
it has more than one senses in a particular
use of that word what is the sense that has
been used
now and and as you can see we will deal with
this problem by looking at the context of
the words use so now how exactly we do that
there are many different algorithms that handle
this problem so there are approaches based
on their knowledge base approaches that use
different overlap based methods for handling
that then there are some machine learning
based approaches they use supervised approaches
unsupervised approaches and semi supervised
approaches and also there are some hybrid
approaches and in the literature there are
a lot of different methods for solving this
problem
now what we will do we will talk about some
very basic methods so that you have the intuition
with you that what are the different ah features
what are different methods you can apply for
word sense disambiguation so now starting
with the knowledge base approaches so there
are some sort of overlap based approaches
they try to use some sort of overlap now how
do they find is overlap they would require
a machine readable dictionary ok so like word
net is my machine readable dictionary you
can have some other sort of the torus also
that are in a machine readable form so by
machine readable i mean so all the entries
and all the information is such that you can
easily access that and you can make use of
that
now so what approaches will do they will try
to find the overlap between the features of
different senses of an ambiguous word that
is they will call it sense bag and the features
of the word in its context and call it as
the context bag and they will try to measure
the overlap so now just to explain this idea
let us see i am having a sentence s that contains
some words w one to w n and the word w i can
be used in two senses w i prime and w i double
prime its sense one sense two ok now in the
sentence this word w i would be used only
for one sense and that is what we are assuming
this will be true in most of the cases unless
the speaker himself wants to imply two different
meanings of the same words so we will say
in general for this word w i you would have
only one sense
so now i want to find out depending this context
whether sense one should be taken off sense
to should be taken so idea would be for each
sense i will construct the sense bag ok and
we will see how do we construct sense bag
so i will have a so this i will convert that
to a sense bag sense bag one and this i will
convert to sense bag two now looking at the
context that is you can think of all the words
that are coming in the sentence other than
this word i will construct a context bag now
i will try to find out what is the overlap
between context bag in sense bag one and what
is the overlap here ok and i will take the
answer as the as the one sense that is having
the highest overlap and this is to explain
that simply i have various senses lets context
the sense bag context that the context bag
take the overlap take the sense with the maximum
overlap
now to construct this sense bags and context
bag you will use various features that are
provided in the dictionary that you have so
features could be like what are the sense
definitions that i am having what are the
example sentences that are provided different
hyponyms hyponyms and so on and any other
criteria that you can use from the dictionary
and you will use that to construct both the
sense bags and the context bag take the one
with does maximum overlap
now lets take a simple example or in actual
algorithm that that does that so we have lesks
algorithm so we talked about this algorithm
in the previous lecture also for a different
case when you wanted to find out what is some
ready between two different senses now suppose
i want to use this this less algorithm for
the purpose of versus disambiguation so what
it does so it constructs the sense bag context
bag and how are they constructed the sense
bag contains the words in the definition of
the candidate sense of the candidate part
so i have a word that it ambiguous can have
multiple senses for each of the senses which
i will construct one sense bag and the sense
bag is constructed by using the definitions
that i have in my dictionary and how do i
construct the context bag i take all the words
in my context take each of the senses of the
context word and then take their definition
all these together become my context bag so
i have a single context bag and i have multiple
sense bag for different senses of the word
and then i take the overlap and this overlap
is taken by using the leska algorithm similar
to what we saw in the previous lecture that
if there is a match of n a particular n gram
i a d score of n square
so now lets take this case so i have a sentence
on burning coals we get ash now hear the word
ash it ambiguous and i want to find out what
is the correct sense of this word that is
usually sentence and suppose for simplicity
we are using only the word coal as my context
so what am i going to do i will find out i
will make different sense bag for the word
ash whatever senses are recorded in my word
net and i will construct the context bag by
using all the definitions of the word coal
ok and then i will try to measure the overlap
so suppose we do that so here is the case
from by taking the dictionary definitions
from word net so ash has three senses so one
is corresponds to some trees second corresponds
to some solid residue and third is to converting
to convert that into ash and we want to find
out what which of the three senses is used
here
so what we will do we will take the word coal
that is the only context for we are using
here but in general you can use any number
of context words i take all its sense definitions
that are defined combine them together to
make a context bag so this whole thing together
becomes my contacts bag now i measure it similarity
with each of the senses ok and if you do that
we find the sense to three of the words are
matching here and sense to becomes a winner
so here what you using here you are also using
the is stemming so this is optional you might
use stemming you may not use stemming so this
is the generic idea of leska algorithm ok
i hope this is clear if i want to use multiple
words i can repeat the same thing i suppose
i am using burning coal and get all the three
words i will take all their definitions and
combine them together into a single context
bag and then measure the similarity of each
of senses with this whole context bag ok
so now lets take another scenario where we
have a different kind of source so what is
this source now for each word we are told
what are the categories these senses its senses
belong to so i have some finite set of categories
this can be like finance category location
categories sports category and so on and each
word has been recorded as it has a sense in
these this category so now the problem would
be when i am given a sentence a word can can
have senses in multiple categories find out
what is the a probably category in this sentence
so how do we use the this framework here so
what i will do so for each sense of the target
word if find out what is the source category
to which this belongs ok now calculate the
score for each senses by using context words
no idea would be the context words again would
be having the researches all categories so
for each context but i will find out what
is the source category over i will see by
using the context word which thesaurus category
getting the highest count so here so what
we will be doing a context word will add score
of one of the sense if the thesaurus category
of the word matches that of the sense so lets
take this sentence the money in this bank
fetches interest of eight percent per annum
and suppose my ambiguous word here is bank
has two senses one in the case of safe finance
that is for the money bank that is also used
in the sentence another could be river bank
also also can be used as location or something
ok and i take each context words money interest
and annum fetch each again would have their
own dissolves category
so what we will be doing i will take all these
words money interest fetch annum i know bank
have two different senses finance and location
so for each of these context words i will
put a one if the match any of this category
so money message finance so i will put a one
here interest message finance again i will
put a one here fetch does not meet meet any
of these senses so both are zero and a message
finance again plus one and then i will add
the score of both the senses and i in here
i say that a finance the score is three for
locations score is zero so i will take the
sense of bank is finance in this particular
case so these are simple approach it by just
taking the dictionary definition thesaurus
category
now so so there is one problem in both these
approaches that is work for disambiguating
the sense of a particular word we are not
disambiguating the sense of the other context
words we are taking all the possible senses
of them into a single context bag but suppose
you want to solve this problem where in a
sing in the same sentence there are multiple
ambiguous words and you want to disambiguate
each of them together then can we do that
and this can be done by making each of the
fact that although each word might have multiple
senses but the particular senses that are
being used in this [sen/sentence] this sentence
there will be somehow connected to each other
so we want to exploit this and for this we
can use some sort of grab based method similar
to what we do in the case of ah pagerank algorithm
so let me just quickly explain this idea and
we will actually deal with this pagerank algorithm
in detail when we talk about summation application
but i will try to give you the intuition so
this is the problem that suppose i have the
sentence the church bells no longer ring on
sundays ok and i can say there are four words
bell rings church in sunday and i want to
disambiguate the senses of these words and
also suppose that from the dictionary i know
what are there sense definitions so here the
word church has three senses bell has three
senses ring has three senses and sunday has
one senses and i want to disambiguate the
first three words together so how do i do
that so idea would be so that is treated as
a graph based problem where for each word
i first write down water [diff/different]
different senses of this word so i have made
a vortex for each of the sense of these words
so there are three three words is for a bell
three for ring three for church and one for
sunday so i have now ten words in this graph
now what will be the idea i will now try to
connect the different words together by seeing
what is the overlap among different sense
definition so i will now try to correct connect
some weighted edges between different sense
definitions by using [las/laska] lesks method
so the [lask/laska] is by similar by simple
for finding similarity between two sentences
i use that find out what is the similarity
between any two sense definitions and add
a weight between these two and this will give
me some sort of matrix like that so i have
all the sense definitions connected now one
thing one important thing is that for the
same word i will not have to connect its own
sense definition so there will not be any
edge between s three and s two for the same
word bell but they will be edges between different
words so as three of bell an s two of ring
would be connected by what is the similarity
between these two sense definition so idea
is that now we want to somehow find out that
particular combination here so one sense for
each of the three words such that their overall
similarity is the highest so they are having
the highest similarity and one particular
method that can use for that is using it a
pagerank kind of algorithm so idea would be
if there are multiple if there are appropriate
sense definitions that are similar to each
other if i use the pagrank algorithm they
would have very high ranking school because
they will all contribute to each other
so what do we do so for this graph once we
have all the word decease we have all the
edge bit also we treated as a problematic
fear finding the page rank for each vertex
of this graph and to give you simple intuition
so now what would we have so we have ah ten
nodes the graph and i try to connect them
by different numbers these numbers depend
on there lesks similarity now once i have
this if i want to compute the pagerank scores
for each node ok and now what is the algorithm
for computing paging is score if you take
it the simple idea that is ah i suppose so
this pagerank it completed in a creative manner
so we start with some initial random is course
this will be some sort of probable distribution
and i use this equation v equal to v a to
find out what will be the pagerank score ok
and we denotes the pagerank scores and and
how do we actually come up with this score
start with some initial v zero and then keep
on multiplying a a square a cube until it
converge and that becomes your pagerank score
ok
so we will talk about this algorithm in detail
later and for now you can just quickly have
a look at what what is the pagerank algorithm
but the idea would be once we we do all that
you will find one pagerank score for each
node and the nodes that are having a lot of
connections with other nodes and with high
in degree connection will be given a higher
pagerank score so if suppose this node is
connected to multiple sense definitions it
is connected to this sense definition this
sense definition and this sense definition
that means this might be one of the important
senses in this for this particular word and
idea would be to find out for each word one
sense that is having the highest connection
and this would be so someone that will get
a high pagerank a score
so i will give pagerank the score to each
of the ten node and then for each word i will
pick the one that is having the highest among
this set so i will take one from each of the
set and here i anyway choose this one and
this becomes my final disambiguated sense
so once i have added all these weighted adages
i will apply the graph based ranking algorithm
so this can be pagerank algorithm and now
once we get all this course i will for each
word i will choose the one with the highest
score an idea here is the sign the purpose
sense that is connected to multiple other
sense which for multiple words would get a
higher score and that is the intuition that
i want to choose the particular sense that
is having a similar definition has many other
senses and this i do for each of the word
so here suppose s one in for bell one s three
for ring and s two for church are selected
and they are my final disambiguated senses
for these three words ok and this is my overall
algorithm
now we can also use some machine learning
based methods and one simple idea would be
to use a naive bayes algorithm so naive bayes
algorithm we were we are using for doing classification
here what is the classification task for a
given word there are multiple senses from
the sentence find out what is the appropriate
sense so this is this method has to be word
specifics and for each word you might have
as many classes as the number of sense of
this word so so problem here is find out the
sense of the word that gives the maximum probability
as given f and set of features that i will
extract from the context around this word
so this for a multiple senses i want to find
out the sense that is having this score at
maximum now because naīve bayes genetic model
that means the sense comes on the off first
and then the features are are generated from
their different features so how do we compute
this particular probability this would be
nothing but orgmax s probability f given s
probability s divided probabilities f and
because this common for all the sense this
is orgmax over s p s p f given s is now p
s nothing but the prior probability of the
sense that is if a particular sense of the
word is more commonly used that get a high
prior and p f given s h what is the probability
of different features being observed or generated
by this sense so naīve bays model what we
do we make this assumption that each of these
features are conditional independent of each
other given s given the sense s so suppose
there are features f one two f n so i was
write it as orgmax s p s i is equal to one
to n probability f i given s ok and this i
will do for each sense and i will i will take
the one that is giving you the maximum score
now what is important here is what are different
features that you will be choosing for an
naīve bayes method and these features have
to come from the context around the word so
what what are different things i can use in
the context i can use water different part
of speech that are being used what are different
words and so on let us see for this task what
are the important features so this we have
already seen some for this task i can use
the part of speech of surrounding words and
what are different semantic and syntactic
features i can use co occurrence vector that
is what are the different other words this
sense is used with and then i can use this
collocation vector vector that is water in
general the next word next next word previous
word previous to previous word and their part
of speech tags when the word is used in this
particular sense so i will construct this
this side of feature vector by by using this
all these examples and the two parameters
of a model that is the prior probability of
the sense and the probability of features
given the sense can be computed from my corpus
by using simply maximum likelihood estimate
so how do we compute probability of the sense
s i number of times the sensitive divide by
number of times this word is used improbability
of a particular feature to the senses sense
number of times this feature is observe with
the sense divide by number of times all other
features are or number of times senses used
so these are simple formula for mle and you
use that and plug into the algorithm and you
have your naive bayes models thirty for for
use and you can use some other approaches
like decision list algorithm so what is the
idea so here so you will use so this hypothesis
of one sense per collocation now what is this
one sense for collocation hypothesis for a
given word idea is that with the particular
collocation it is use only in one sense for
example take the word like bat we saw there
are two two different sense one is like it
creates cricket bat and what another it like
a flying mammal now suppose you take this
collocation cricket bat ok so the word cricket
covering before bat with this collocation
the word bat will always used in one sense
only not the other sense this is the idea
can i collocations to find out with this collocation
this word to be with all in this sense and
with the other collocations it will be used
in another other senses and this is called
the one collocation percents property sorry
one sense per collocation property and so
how do i start about getting these set of
collocations for a for a ambiguous word so
initially i can try out all the possible set
of nearby words that that occurs with this
word more more often and once i have done
that for each such collocation i can compute
what is the probability of a particular sense
being used for this collocation with respect
to the other sense now take the simple case
where the word has only two sense sense a
and sense b so for a given collocation i will
find out what is the probability of sense
a given the collocation and what is the probability
of sense b given this collocation
now question is once i found both these numbers
what will be a function that will tell me
how good this collocation is now this collocation
would be good if one of these probabilities
is high another probabilities quite low so
collocation indicates sense a if this probability
divide by this probability is high sense b
if the inverse of that is high and this simple
measure we used to come find out what collocations
for a word are more important than others
so so i come so this and i take a log of this
and this is called a log likelihood ratio
log of probability of sense a given the collocation
i divide by probability of sense b k given
collocation i and then hire log likelihood
means more evidence so what i will do for
different collocations that i have extend
for the word these can be some simple words
that occurs a lot with this word in different
context i will compute this log likelihood
this course and then i am i will arrange them
in their decreasing order ok and this will
give me the decision list so now so here is
an example suppose you have some training
data and here the ambiguous word is plant
ok near trying to extra various collocations
that can help me to find out whether the sense
used is a a is in the sense of plant life
and with the sense is b in the sense of manufacturing
so suppose i i i run my algorithm and i find
out that the collocation plant growth its
having a very high likelihood that is ten
point one two and this this is for the sense
a what does that mean log of probability sense
a given plant growth divide by probability
sense be given plant growth will become ten
point one two and this is the highest among
all the collocations this comes out on top
n a c sense is a suppose similarly the second
collocation is if the word car occurs in plus
minus k words around this ambiguous word plant
then the sense would be b and this as a log
likelihood of nine point six eight and so
on ok and with each likelihood i have a sense
now once i have that i can use it directly
as my decision list classifier so what i will
do at runtime whenever i am given the sentence
i find out if this collocation is present
plant growth if this is present senses a if
not whether the word car occurs in plus minus
k words around plant if so senses being if
not if plant height occurs senses a and so
on so so when i get a sentence at one time
like plucking flowers affects plant growth
i will take this sentence and run it through
this decision list classifier and accordingly
wherever i find a match i immediately provide
the sense and i stop
now one thing you have to be careful here
with these numbers so so remember the formula
we have a probable determine the denominator
and it can also be zero in some cases so you
might have to use some sort of smoothing you
can use add one a smoothing or some other
smoothing method for that so once you do that
you can come up with this decision list classifier
and at runtime given a sentence you can easily
compute what is a sense that should be used
here here is another example of decision list
classifier like you are discriminating with
me bass and base the fish and music sense
so it can be something like that suppose this
is how you are different collocations are
ordered h for a log likelihood so we make
a finishing tree if the word fish occurs in
plus minus k words if yes sense is fish fish
if no if the collocation stripe bass occurs
if yes fish if no if the word guitar occurs
is directly coming from the ordered list of
log likelihood and this you can run through
a new sentence to find out the appropriate
sense of the word bus
so we saw some of the algorithms that that
that by using knowledge based approaches and
machine learning approaches now in the next
lecture we will also talk to talk about some
other approaches that are either semi supervisor
unsupervised but in general there are many
many different algorithms that you can apply
on this task we only providing you very brief
ideas on some of those so
thank you soon so i will see you in the next
lecture