so welcome back for the fourth lecture of
this week so we had already started our discussions
on word sense disambiguation in the last lecture
and we talked about some [app/approaches]
that we use i that are either knowledge based
or use some machine learning algorithm so
ah in this lecture we will talk about some
approaches that are either semi supervised
or unsupervised so ah why do we need to talk
about the ah semi supervised or supervised
approaches so so in all the machine learning
approaches that that that we can use for this
this particular problem or any other problem
what is one particular bottleneck let's take
the naive bayes algorithm ok so for for applying
naive bayes algorithm you want to compute
the features at that is as as such easy some
sort of domain knowledge will be required
but you have to find out all these numbers
like what is the probability of a particular
sense what is the probability of a feature
given a sense yes now how do you got get all
these values for getting all these values
you need to have some sort of label data set
and what do i mean by labeled data set in
this context i will have various sentences
where this my ambiguous for would have occurred
and somebody has labeled it that this is sense
one in this sentence the word w occurs this
is sense two and so on so no in some a good
number of sentences somebody has labeled each
word as belonging to one or the other senses
and from there i can compute all these course
and this has to be done for each an individual
word ok
and this can be really really expensive getting
all this annotations them and that is true
for any generic machine learning task so need
to have all these annotations first and that
is quite expensive that's why if you can find
some sort of semi supervised approach where
starting with very few labels you can generate
lot of different labels and which may be which
may not be hundred percent accurate but you
can assume that they are mostly correct so
that is also quite well appreciated that is
you are trying to use some sort of semi supervised
approach and that will save a lot of efforts
in labeling and also you use a lot of bootstrapping
here
so you see one such approach for word sense
disambiguation that was proposed by yarowsky
so so this is also called minimally supervised
word sense disambiguation and what is the
motivation that for a machine o for using
a supervised learning [alg/algorithm] i have
to use annotations and that that are quite
ah expressive inexpensive so i use bootstrapping
so what is the idea i start with some small
seed set and i am learning the my decision
is classified from the small seed set use
my decision list to label the rest of the
corpus again from there find out what are
the labels that are confident modify your
decision list algorithm again run it on the
corpus find out more labels and so on so you
try to go in some sort of a loop of starting
from some seed set label some sentences ext
extending your seed sets of or patterns or
rules again applying it getting more labels
done and so on until you have somehow conversion
so and you can use some sort of heuristics
for doing this ah semi automatic labeling
and two heuristics are very common in the
case of words disambiguation one is one sense
per discourse and another is one ah sense
for collocation one sense for collocation
we have already seen in the in the ah previous
example of decision list classifier what is
one one sense for discourse so idea is that
suppose you are taking one particular document
or one particular long context if the same
word has been repeated multiple times most
probably it is using the same sense so for
example you are seeing the commentary or some
news article about sports and you find the
word bat has been used at one point and you
know this category is sense one
now if the same word bat occurs in some some
nearby places you can probably assume that
this is also being used the same sense and
this is the idea so in the same discourse
if your word appears multiple times i tag
it with the same sense so these are my two
different heuristics one sense for discourse
that is a word tends to preserve its meaning
across all its occurrences in a given discourse
and one sense for collocation we have already
seen that if it is used with the same collocation
it will have one meaning and generally it
is strong for nearby collocations and if the
distance becomes higher it becomes weaker
and weaker so now how do we use this ideas
to construct a semi supervised approach for
words disambiguation so idea would be let's
take the same example that is i'm having the
word plant it has two senses one is industrial
sense another is living thing sense so i will
starts with some sort of seed labels or some
seed ah collocation so suppose i say that
with the first sense that is industrial if
the word plant occurs with manufacturing it
will have only the first sense similarly if
the word plant occurs with life it will have
the living thing sense ok
so this becomes my decision list classifier
i check simply if the words plant is occurring
with manufacturing all life manufacturing
i say it is sense one if if life sense two
ok so what will i do i'll take my whole corpus
see wherever with the word plant one of these
words either manufacturing or life occurs
wherever the word manufacture occurs i say
ok this is labeled as this is my pseudo label
sentence so now i have some set of pseudo
label sentences both with manufacturing and
using manufacturing in life so what i would
have now from my corpus i would have labeled
some sentences ok with sense one with sense
two so these are all the sentences where the
words plant occurs with manufacturing and
these are all the where the plant occurs with
life ok
so now the idea would be so now i am doing
going in in in iterations so now i will treat
the match my labeled data ok although to be
ah very ah clear we can also call it my pseudo
labeled data it is like i am only making an
assumption that they are labeled with sense
one and sense two now treat it as your label
data and then apply your decision list classical
algorithm to find out what are the good collocations
suppose you find some three four collocations
here so it can be ah different things about
growth and whatever or the word car like what
we saw in the previous case so we find some
collocations here now use this collocations
and your algorithm to build a new decision
list classifier
new classifier again you will use that to
label new sentences and you will have new
data you will get new collocations from there
and you keep on repeating the system so let's
see for this particular example so suppose
i use that and i label some sentences with
sense of ah living thing some with sense of
industrial plant ok
so you see here everywhere life is occurring
here everywhere the word manufacturing is
occurring now from these labeled or by pseudo
labeled data i will try to extract some more
collocations like here suppose i see that
the word like animal and kingdom occur a lot
with this sense but they do not occur with
this sense so this becomes my collocation
now now use your decision list classify algorithms
previously that we have talked about to make
ah so make to make my decision list ok now
again run it over the coppers and then you
can find suppose the word where plant and
animal occurs so here you can again label
it with sense of sense of living thing and
from from once you have done that you can
extract some more collocations from here and
you keep on doing that so idea would be something
like that so you have this whole corpus where
the word plant occurs somewhere by using this
initial seed set of life and manufacturing
you have label sense a and sense b now what
you will do you will treat them as label data
from their capture some more collocations
so something like this so you capture collocation
like cell animal species microscopic for for
the sense of life and equipment employee automated
manufacturing for the sense of ah industrial
ah plant
now use that to label more sentences and it
is a more sentences that you have labeled
ok so all these content this might microscopic
speech anyone and so on now you have a larger
data again extract collocations from where
build build here recently and try to label
the rest of the corpus so you keep on iterating
this and ideally at some point you will have
you whole corpus covered now so ah so when
do you stop when the error on the training
data is less than a threshold so we can have
some small training data to check how could
your ah this bootstrapping approach is performing
or when no more training data is covered by
the algorithm when you see that all the examples
have been covered and when whatever final
decision list you get by this algorithm use
that for word sense disambiguation now what
is the advantage of this approach so ah so
you can see that the advantage here are that
it would have to put the efforts into manual
labeling of the corpus
so you can start with some some very small
seed side set keep on applying this algorithm
retroactively and obtain the final classifier
now so so accuracy also turns out to be quite
good but what are the different ah what maybe
one problem with this approach ah so one problem
of this approach might be that the whole accuracy
that you get by this approach depends on how
good are your initial ah initial seed set
if your initial seed set is not good then
you may not ah go very far in this in this
approach so the the good thing is if you chose
choose very good initial seeds that have lot
of precondition the corpus and are also very
very distinctive you see this gives starts
give giving you very good precision and good
recall from the very beginning
so now this is a semi supervised approach
and i hope the idea is clear now we will see
one unsupervised approach for what watson
disambiguation by unsupervised i would mean
that the senses for the words are not defined
a priori but they are sort of learned from
the data so from the data you try to find
out what are the different senses a word is
used in and this becomes your ah sense definition
for each word and this field is also called
word sense induction as such so you are trying
to induce the sense of the word by its usage
in the corpus now what is the basic idea
so we will talk about the algorithm the hyperlex
so key i idea here is word sense induction
that is instead of taking some sense that
are defined by a dictionary try to extract
the senses from a corpus itself so the way
the world is used in a corpus use that for
extracting senses of the word and these copper
senses or uses will correspond to clusters
of similar context for a word now let's take
one example to get the intuition so here you
are seeing the word space and there are many
other words that are coming along with this
space so the connections show here that two
different words occur together in a arc occur
together above some threshold number of times
in a corpus ok so and as denotes that they
are probably similar in the sense that they
are co occurring a lot so now try to look
at this this simple picture so what do you
seeing the words like retail parking are connected
retail square are connected feet and parking
connected here in the left hand side right
hand side you are seeing words like astronauts
mission and ah n a s a shuttle all these are
connected
now by looking at these connections so what
is one thing that you are seeing is that you
are finding out two different clusters here
ok one in the left hand side one in the right
hand side one is denoting one sense of space
in the sense of parking space retail space
in secondary space as such ah space where
astronauts will be going in and that involves
n a s a and all now from the corpus i can
find out that ah astronauts n a s a and shuttle
n a s a connected retail parking retail square
all these are connected but how will i find
out that the word space has two senses and
these two senses correspond to ah some particular
words so if you look at the figure again you
can see that for a particular sense of the
word space the words will be highly connected
to each other for another sense again these
words are highly connected to each other but
there will not be much connections between
the words in this sense and words in that
sense so that is if i construct this as a
graph and [kin/can] use some sort of clustering
algorithm to find out what are the different
ah portions of partitions of this graph so
one partition will belong to one sense another
partition will correspond to another sense
and this is the idea try to exploit how much
their that the difference for the same sense
the words will co occur a lot together but
it will not happen for the words across to
senses and there are many many different algorithms
that are developed based on this idea for
word sense disambig[uation] induction ok
so now we will talk about a very simple approach
hyperlex that uses this idea now what is this
algorithm hyperlex so what it does is that
for a given word that it ambiguous by using
the data in my corpus it tries to identify
what are the ah main hubs so each hub will
correspond to one sense of this word so it
tries to enter what are the main hubs and
every other word in my ah co occurring graph
will be connected to one or the other hubs
ok
so so you know everything is divided into
these hubs so how do you detect these house
and how do you connect the words to one of
these hubs so so so in hyperlex algorithm
the idea is that the different usage of the
target words from highly interconnected bundles
or high density components and each component
will have one one of the nodes this is hub
that is having a high degree then the other
nodes nodes so how do you start applying this
algorithm so first firstly you have to construct
your co occurrence graph co occur occurrence
graph we have seen already in the previous
week that i find out how many times these
two words occur in the corpus and i use some
function of that to find out how much their
ah association is strong how strong is their
association and i will probably retain only
those words that have a very high association
so i start with connect correct ah building
this graph from the corpus co occurrences
now so what do you do this graph is connected
around this word this ah ambiguous word like
a space in the previous example so first thing
i will do i arrange all the nodes in this
graph in the decreasing order the of their
degree so i will forget about the word space
but every other word will be connecting the
decreasing order of their degree so what i
will ah assume that whatever the hubs are
will have high degree shape
so take the node that is having the highest
degree among all the connections and this
will be the first hub try to find out what
is the neighborhood of this hub take them
to the to it's to this sense cluster remove
this from the graph altogether from the remaining
graph find out what is the node with the highest
degree make it the second hub find out its
neighborhood make it the second sense cluster
remove it keep on doing that so so once i
have arrange the nodes in the graph g in decreasing
order of degree now select the node from g
that has the highest degree and this will
be the hub of the first high density component
now delete this hub and all it's neighbors
from the graph from the remaining graph again
repeat the step three and four to find out
what are the hubs and what are their high
density components so let us try to see this
algorithm on a simple example so here what
do you have you have the word bar that is
the central world and i want to detect what
are it's different senses so what we have
done we have first try to construct the co
occurrence graph so this is this is what you
are seeing is a co occurrence graph that tells
what is the strength of association between
two words ok ah one thing here so so so i
will talk about what is association measure
so according to this association measure you
will take a threshold and choose only those
which is that that are above or below the
threshold depending on how you are defining
your threshold in this particular case so
the number denotes what is the distance between
two words so you are only retaining those
words whose distance is below a threshold
so your threshold is point two five so we
written only those connections that are below
point two five and distance can be captured
by something that is inversely reverse to
the association so in this case it is one
minus liability of max of probability ah so
it is one minus max of probability w i given
w j and probability w j given w i so we take
the max of that to find out what is the association
would be w i w j and this will now capture
the distance because this corresponds to the
similarity how similar they are their condition
probability if i take one minus max of that
that is how much they are different what what
is the distance
so once we have done that for all the words
all the pair of words i'll take only those
that are having distance below a threshold
that means they are quite near and they that
is captured in the left hand side of the figure
now once you have done that now you apply
your algorithm that is finding out what are
different hubs and taking their ah different
neighborhoods so first i'll arrange all the
words in decreasing order of the degree now
what are the no nodes here that are having
the highest degree so you find the word like
iron iron has a degree of one two three and
four coffee has degree of one two three and
four wine also has a degree of one two three
and four ok so now there are multiple words
that are having the highest agree so we'll
choose some preference may be either the lexical
graphical order on some or some ordering on
the or some travels or ordering on the graph
and suppose you say from i will choose the
one from the left and and you choose the word
like iron here as your first hub so what is
the next next step make iron as your first
hub and then take all the neighbors of iron
and put them with this ah with this hub so
we taking the two neighbors gold and steel
and putting them with this hub here ok
and that becomes you first hyperlex components
now how do you find the next hub you remove
this hub and all it's neighbors so i remove
iron gold and steel from the graph again find
out what is the node with the highest degree
you will find the word like coffee here so
take coffee of the second hub take its neighbors
so it will be chocolate cocktail and wine
so these become it's neighbors it's become
my second hope hub and all the component with
that remove that from the graph now find out
the next hub so this can be the word soap
that is having a degree three you take the
words soap and wax as your third hub and it's
component and then finally you will have the
word like pressure and dyne thats your four
hub so this is my hub and these are different
descendants of the hub so from your corpus
you are focusing on one word k bar and you
are trying to construct the co occurrence
matrix finding out the association between
various words building out this graph from
there you are detecting what are your various
hubs and the descendants and this becomes
your instruction on this is your target word
different hubs and their descendants and this
is what you have ah obtained in a completely
unsupervised manner because nobody told you
how many ah senses the word bar put have or
what are the different senses of bar you found
it automatically by using the corpus data
so so for all other words other than hub you
attach them to the root hub that is closest
to them and how do you find what is the closest
hub you can take the distance between that
node and the different route hubs ok
and this distance is simply the summation
over the path length what is the path length
you just keep on adding the path length that
is the distance between any node and the root
hubs attach this node to one of the root hubs
only and this is something that i talked about
that how do we compute the distance between
two nodes in my original co occurrence graph
i take this one minus max probability of w
i given w j and probability of w j given w
i so now so we can see that how do we ah start
from my corpus and construct different senses
of a word so y y hub and ah descendants now
at run time so we we are talking about this
problem whats in the disambiguation so at
run time i am given a ah sentence where this
word is provided and i want to find out what
is it's appropriate sense that is used among
all the possible senses i have fine formed
by this algorithm so what is the approach
so let us say i have this context or the sentence
where this word w i occurs and w i is my target
word that has multiple senses so suppose they
are it has k senses k hubs that is k senses
so what do we do we associate a score vector
as with each word in the context such that
s k denotes what is the contribution of the
ah so what is the contribution it will have
to the k th hub and this is simply taken by
one divide by one plus distance between the
hub and the word if it is if the hub is an
ancestor of the word w otherwise it' is zero
and you do that for all the words in my context
and sum those over so find out a simple vector
that tells me which sense has how much score
which has a have how much score and whichever
has hub has the highest score i will choose
that so to tell that again so what we will
do so we will have a sentence w one to w n
and i have this word w i that has s one to
s k k hubs ok now i want to find out which
of these k senses is used in this particular
particular example particular sentence so
what will i do for each word w one w two up
to w n i will construct this core vector ok
so [sco/score] vector has that many dimension
as the number of hubs so it has k dimension
so i'll construct this vector for each of
the words ok
so now what are the entries in this vector
this entity tells me how much contribution
this words will make to the first hub this
contribution would be if this word is an ancest[or]
if if the particular hub h of the sense one
is an ancestor or this word w one it will
be one divided by one plus distance of h one
and w one ok so that is if the distance is
high this score will be low if the distance
is smaller this will give a high score on
the other hand if this word if the hub is
not ancestor i will put a score of like that
i will put all the different values here and
finally once i have all the values i will
add all these so for each hub i'll add all
the possible scores and i will take a final
vector that is how much contributions all
the words together are making for hub one
hub two and hub k and i take the one that
is having the maximum score among all these
and that becomes my winner sense ok
so ah so this is the overall idea of this
approach so what we have done here we did
did not start with any distance defined sense
we used a corpus and defined our own senses
by seeing what are the different components
that occurred together so so idea is that
for a for a given sense of a word different
words would have a high co occurrence they
will make some sort of cluster so identify
different cluster size different senses
now once you have these senses if you want
to op use them for ward sense disambiguation
at run time whenever the word is used find
out from the context words which of thus ah
different hubs they are closer to so whichever
hub gets the high score becomes your disambiguate
sense so thats ah these are some different
ideas for ah approaching this problem words
and disambiguation although i said earlier
there are many many different ah approaches
that have been proposed so in the next lecture
we will briefly talk about ah an idea of word
sense ah discovery that is how do you find
out if the world has got a new sense in the
corpus this is a relatively new ah new field
and ah we will see how the ideas that we have
developed in this these lectures to you how
do we use them to find out if a word has got
new sense in the corpus ok
thank you