so hello everyone so ah so welcome to this
final lecture of week eight and so in this
week we have talked about our a different
method of semantics that is lexical semantics
and we saw that how we can use connection
between words to find out semantics and last
two lectures we we talked about a very classical
problem of word senses disambiguation that
is even a word if it has multiple senses
how do you find out ah in a given context
what particular sense has been used and this
is a very generic kind of problem and you
can use a lot of different methods for solving
that and we saw that how you can use simple
knowledge base approaches by using the dictionary
definitions and you can use some machine learning
methods you can use some bootstrapping based
methods and also unsupervised methods there
we also talked about a page rank based algorithm
if you want to jointly find out the senses
for each words you did not describe that algorithm
fully so if you want to know in in that algorithm
details so you might have to wait till we
cover the summarization topic in summarization
i will talk about pagerank in detail but i
sense the generic idea you can also get from
the what we discussed and also you can look
it up
so now so this lecture we are taking a new
research problem that is coming from word
sense disambiguation idea itself and also
from whatever we discussed in the towards
the end of in the last lecture so in the towards
the end of the last lecture we were talking
about ah learning the word senses in an unsupervised
manner that is now i am not talking about
senses defined in a dictionary so i am saying
ok i have a corpus i know how the word has
been used multiple times can i use the the
usage of the word to find out what are it's
senses and what was the basic idea
so basic idea was that if i know that i have
a corpus see my corpus and i can find out
which words co occurred other words ok so
like that i can construct some some what model
i know what what's co occur what and all words
so idea was it suppose i am constructing this
network if a word has two senses what will
happen the words that correspond to it's so
there is suppose my center word so words that
i connect corresponding to one sense will
be connected together words that are in second
sense will be connected together this is sense
one this is sense two
so if i am building the whole co occurrence
graph if i center it around the particular
word and try to cluster it i can find out
it's different senses it is a very generic
idea and this i call as word sense induction
also also known as from wsi there are many
ways of doing that because they are many ways
you can do this clustering you can apply any
graph based clustering method
so for example chinese whispers is a very
popular algorithm and you can use any other
methods also so idea would be now when you
do that for each word you will get some senses
s one s two s three and so on and these might
correspond to say the words these are the
words it can be different words we can have
weights and so on now so this is you have
give a corpus you can find out what are the
word senses but in this lecture we will talking
about the problem that can you find out if
a word has got a new sense or not in some
recent time had you got a new sense
now does that happen so over the time we keep
on using the same words new new and senses
ok so and with the social media that is becoming
a lot more common that you are using the same
word in some new senses that is that it was
never used before so let's see one example
so i have the word sick right sick is a very
common and popular word and you will say ok
what is the meaning of sick something to be
related to some disease illness ok so like
so this is the pub dictionary definition so
affected with a disease or illness of or relating
to people who are ill and very annoyed or
bored by something because you have had too
much of it so i am sick of that
so now this is one common sense of sick now
do you think sick has got any new sense in
recent times and and and if you think about
it sick has got a very a new sense and that
is completely opposite of this particular
sense so what is that sense so let us look
at this tweet so listening to paulo nutinis
new record it's sick ok so now what is the
meaning of sick here of the same word sick
it's not boring ok so this thick means something
that is very very cool ok so this sick has
got a very new meaning from whatever we were
seeing earlier something that disease illness
to something that is very cool
now so what's keep on getting these new meanings
in the in the ah in the corpus so the way
people are using that now the problem is suppose
my dictionary or my lexicon like word net
is not getting updated regularly so if this
word sick has got this new sense and it is
being used in this new sense in the corpus
i will never be able to match it to any of
the sense in the word net because word net
has not recorded the sense at all so does
not know probably sick has the sense also
and this is happening for many other words
ok
so now what is done in this field of novel
word sense detection from the corpus and the
way the words are being used can i detect
whether the word has got new sense and if
i can detect it i can populate different lexicons
and different and also my word net version
i can update using this definitions so how
do we find out the word has got new sense
now again so this is a new area but there
have been some different sort of methods and
works i will not go into details of any of
those works
but what i will do i will try to give you
a basic idea that if you understand watson
induction how can you use that to find out
new word sense or novel word sense so let
us so have a basic idea the basic idea is
that i can try to compare the sense so that
is if your word is undergoing sense change
it can be detected by comparing the sense
clusters obtained from two different time
periods ok
so something like this so you take the word
compiler suppose in nineteen not nine nineteen
fifty three so the we take took the data and
we did the watsons induction and from the
induction we found out that the word compiler
has these two senses so one sense is in the
sense of reporter auditor listener etcetera
second is on scientists compositor philosopher
publisher preacher so there are two different
senses this so what it means is that these
words come together to form one sense and
these words come together to form another
senses in nineteen not nine nineteen fifty
three
compiler was merely some sort of person who
wish to compile now if i look at this word
in recent time like two thousand two thousand
five compiler has got the sense in the sense
of ah programming language compilers this
sense was not available not there in nineteen
not nine nineteen fifty three so can i automatically
detect that the word has got a new sense from
the data itself so what i will do again into
v into two thousand five i will do the watsons
induction so suppose i do induction and i
find these two senses
so one is again the same sense translator
editor listener reader commentator that is
similar to what we had earlier but you see
a new sense also coming up preprocessor driver
handler hardware software loader kernel dbms
ok and you can immediately see by looking
at these words in the computer sense this
sense was not available earlier
so now this is interesting observation that
if i simply do watson sense induction over
the new time period i find a sense cluster
that was not available before and this gives
me a generic framework so what i will do i
will take my data that is over several time
so it can be say eighteen hundred to two thousand
ten or whatever so it's starting from some
t one to t two i want to find out what words
have undergone sense change so what i will
do i will try to take some slice of this data
call it time point t one
take another slice later on time point t two
is that ok so now i will do i will compute
my co occurrence ah and whatever i want to
compute my distributional casares then i will
do watsons induction so for each word i will
find out s one in time t one s two in time
t one s three in time t one and so on and
that i will do for all the words similarly
i will do the same thing at time t two so
i am at w and i will say s one at time t two
s two at time t two s three at time t two
and so on ok
now i have got the sense cluster at time t
one and at time t two now i will try to compare
these to find out if the word has got a new
sense cluster that was not available in the
previous time point and the second do for
all the words and by doing that i can find
out which words have got a new sense of the
newer time period so and in general i can
define various ah various different sort of
sense change
for example it might happen that earlier a
word as a sense it has got to split into multiple
senses or it can be a join two different senses
of joined together to form the same sense
they may not be so common but what is common
is something like a birth that the word had
initially two senses s one and s two now in
the new time period it has got a new sense
s n this is very very common and then they
might be death of a sense also that earlier
it had a sense of s zero now in the new time
period i cannot sense find out the sense so
all these you can find out just by comparing
these sense clusters
so here is another example that we observed
from the data so this is from the work that
we did ah in two thousand fourteen so this
was in a c l two thousand fourteen if you
want to have a look so the title was that's
sick dude ok and there was some other subtitle
so this was in year two thousand fourteen
so so we did so we took the data from google
anagrams and we took the whole data from starting
from ah somewhere around sixteen hundred to
two thousand eight divided into eight different
time points then ah so that they were divided
such that in each time point you have roughly
the same amount of data
so as you go over ah recent years even like
three years and four years for making a complete
time duration in earlier it might be hundred
years together because the data was not too
much and then we took different time points
constructed distribution of and then you ah
chinese algorithm to find out sense clusters
and then complain the clusters and so what
are the words that are getting some new sense
so here was an one example so we found that
the word registers earlier had these senses
and you can see these are like dictionaries
directories libraries compilations bulletins
these are registers as you like paper registers
and so on so that you have even now similarly
here notebook diary returns accounts
so in the new time period we form that these
two senses are there directories compilations
manuals summaries schedules ledgers notebook
but a very new senses come up and can you
think of the sense what is the sense peripherals
processor circuits workstations devices so
register has got the sense of if the sense
of computing in a hardware that
so now ah so this new sense we could detect
simply by using the corpus that these all
words are being used with resistance and and
they were having similar ah co occurrence
such as the word to resistance so we found
this is a new sense cluster that is coming
up and like then many other senses so this
is i will say as i was saying this is a new
research field and some works have have come
up in this in this field this is one such
work but i hope the basic ideas care that
if you want to detect new word sense what
you need to do so that ends this week of lexical
semantics
so next week again we will continue with the
topic of semantics so we have started with
distributions of semantics one idea then we
talked about lexical semantics another idea
of semantics now we will see how we can capture
semantics using topics ok can we find out
what are the topics that are there in my data
use that for some semantics and that's why
we will discuss topic models detail ok and
there are again very very popular tools in
n l p so
thank you i will see you in the next week