so everyone welcome back to week nine of this
course so we have been talking about semantics
in the last two weeks and we discussed two
different approaches of semantics one was
using lexical semantics and otherwise using
distribution semantics and we saw how used
the corpus or from a lexicon you can extract
semantics you can capture the meanings of
words in some sense that is whether two words
are similar to each other and and many other
aspects
so in this week we will discuss another very
interesting way of capturing semantics by
using topic models and they have been a very
very popular tools in n l p for whenever you
have to talk about what are the concepts that
are there in a particular document in a particular
corpus and many other ah questions that that's
around ah that are around the semantics so
let us see what are these topic models
so so firstly let us start the brief ah motivation
that why do we actually need topic models
as such ah so so when we talk about the data
so the text data in general on under that
so so there is a huge amount of data available
right in form of whatever form you can think
of there are lot of data in terms of news
articles scientific articles and blog social
media and everywhere
now so you can think of it as some sort of
information overload and you might be interested
to capture only certain aspect of the data
ok so we want capture certain semantics so
so what is an easy way in which you can some
sort of organize this data and then this can
help you to search or browse through the data
more much more effectively so so what other
so right now what about main tools that we
use for doing this search of different information
either we type some query in our search engine
right some human so so free text query we
type and we get some reals ok and we try to
browses the reals and sometimes reals are
not relevant or even if they are relevant
we go to the pages to which the link to and
keep on browsing so that is some sort of generic
behavior of how we we try to explore this
sort of information
but there is no easy ah interface where you
can you can say ok i want to understand these
topics only i want to go too deep into this
topic i want to go related topics and all
that that is not available with this search
and ah link kind of ah behavior so the topic
modeling gives you an ah alternative method
of going through this huge amount of information
by ah some sort of searching based on themes
criteria so you can think of it as if you
are having a set of documents and you know
what are the themes that are running through
this corpus so you know the ok this documentary
about certain themes related to politics this
document is about certain theme related to
ah dramatic and so on different concepts
now you are going to a popular thing and then
you can either zoom in or zoom out ok so that
is you want to go inside the theme to very
very sub themes or you want to go out to a
broader theme so can this be fascinated by
it by some sort of modeling so so we might
also want to look at how the themes in a corpus
are changing over time ok how they are evolving
over time this happens a lot in for example
scientific article a par particular research
in ah in physics might be starting with certain
certain concepts and over that period of time
it starting with ah it is now having new concepts
ok so by by various discoveries so can we
discovered that what are the themes setup
already over time and you can also talk about
this behavior where you have you would select
the theme first and then you try to examine
the documents that talk about that theme
so topic modeling it is a method that gives
you this facility by which you can organize
all these collections by the themes that are
occurring in in those documents and you can
then understand search and do summarization
and many other applications ok without and
this is important that for doing all that
you do not have to give any prior manual efforts
in in labeling the data so you do not have
to tell that this document concerns this topic
or this document concerns that topic you do
not have to do any labeling so the interesting
aspect is that you give it a corpus an in
an uncivilized manner it learns what is the
overall structure of different topics and
these document concerns which topics and so
on
so this is very this is some sort of very
interesting aspect that made topic modeling
very popular that you no need to have any
prior annotation as such although there are
some variations we will also talk about where
you can give an annotation to get some different
sort of ah topic modeling but overall in the
generic picture you do not have to give any
any sort of annotations so it learns on it's
own from the huge amount of data
so so what you do here so you discover what
are the hidden themes that are pervading to
the collection and the topic model itself
annotates the document as for these themes
so it will tell you ok these are the overall
themes this document contains these themes
and so on and [ noise] once you have these
annotations that are given with the topic
model you can use that to for validation task
like organizing the collection summarizing
collection searching when the user query comes
by using the each annotations so many different
applications we will cover some of those in
this week and yes we can there is a there
is a huge huge amount of literature around
topic models so you can also feel free to
read about it
so so let's talk about one of the applications
before we go into the modeling in in detail
so we talk we are we are cons ah consistently
talking about discovering topics from a corpus
ok that is one of the most important ah application
of topic models so something like that so
you have a large corpus and can you discover
that there are many many topics and topic
look like this ok by topic i mean a set of
words that occur a lot in that topic ok so
so let's see one topic human genomic d n a
genetic genes sequence gene molecular sequencing
map information
so so topic model we will try to get you ok
this is one sort of topics it will not give
you a label ok so although you can see this
looks like a genetics topic of genetics it
will not give you a label it will tell you
that this is there is a topic in this in this
corpus there is a theme and in this theme
each words are more having more higher probability
so these are the more important words in this
theme and then it will tell ok there is general
theme that is going through this corpus something
like this evolution evolutionary species organization
life origin biology and then you see a set
of terms ok these are having a high probability
in that theme there is no labels that topic
model is giving but you can see ok it might
be evolutionary biology ok then similarly
another theme disease host bacteria disease
so on and four theme computer models information
data computers and so on
so so the topic models will tell you ok in
this collection you have these four themes
in addition to some other themes ok so that
is your predefined ah number that you will
need need to give to the ah models so you
can say ok i want fifty different themes in
this corpus or twenty different themes in
this corpus yes although there are again variations
where you might not have to specify these
number a priori we will briefly talk about
those also
but for now let us say we we tell the model
we need that money themes so try to discover
ok these are the important themes that i am
seeing with a pervading through this corpus
and these are some examples these are some
examples that we are seeing here that are
coming from a real corpus by doing the l d
s applying the l d a model
now once you have these themes then the topic
model will also tell you ok this document
is about having ah only these two themes out
of these fifty this document is having these
five themes out of these fifty in in what
proportions and so on so like that you can
now ah think about organizing huge your whole
collection and also ah some sort of a summarization
or searching through this
now so why is this intuition interesting so
when you look at a particular document in
general you will see that yes there are actually
ah some particular themes that are that are
pervading this whole document so so that is
you have somehow thought of making a document
that concerns these themes only so here is
an article from sci science magazine nineteen
ninety six seeking lifes bare genetic necessities
and so if you read this article so this is
about using some sort of computational data
analysis to determine the number of genes
and organisms that needs to survive so how
many genes ah genes and organism needs to
survive
so so this topic this article will blend some
of the topics that are important to convey
this message ok and these words are denoted
in various colors here so we are seeing some
words with pink some words with yellow somewhere
to blue and and so on let's read the words
in in pink so there were organism survives
life organisms yellow genes genomes genes
genetic sequenced genome and blue will be
computer productions numbers computational
computer analysis and so on so you you can
clearly see three different themes one is
about genetics another is about the evolution
another is about ah this computational data
analysis
so so this this article is blen blending these
three themes together ok it's can be capture
that in an uncivilized manner without someone
has to manually annotate this ok this is the
themes in this document so if i yes you see
blue is data analysis pink is evolutionary
biology and yellow is genetics so this article
is blending these three topics in different
proportions and that is the motivations that's
what ah that's what is the hypothesis that
we are having about your corpus in the corpus
there will be various documents there will
be a ah there will be some big number of themes
that are going through this corpus but when
you look at a particular document it will
have only a subset of these themes ok in some
proportions can we ah automatically capture
those by using some modeling
so so yeah once you know that this article
blends this topics together you can situate
that in a in a collection of scientific articles
you can say ok where this where this situates
what are the articles it is similar to and
and so on so so what is the basic idea you
are not going to the mathematical details
that we will cover in the next week but let
us see the intuition so so this is the important
idea so topic model is some sort of generative
model and this just as a model that captures
this idea about the collection having topics
and topic document having different proportions
so what it says is that so you are having
a doc having some documents they are nothing
but mixtures of topic and a topic it's nothing
but the probability distribution over words
ok so what are three themes we are talking
about we are talking about a collection that
is having documents d one d two up to d n
here a documents in the collection then you
are having some topics ok so suppose there
are some t one to t k topics and use your
documents in document some words will occur
and you say ok these are my ah vocabulary
these are my words w one to some w m ok
so here three themes in the collection there
are documents documents some words occur suppose
you have a unique words define your vocabulary
and there are some topics now what topic models
say yes topics are nothing but probability
distribution over words so t one would be
something like a distribution ok so here what
one comes the probability of zero point zero
one word two comes with the probability of
zero point one and so on ok similarly t k
will be again a probability distribution what
one comes with a probability distribution
of zero point zero five word two with a zero
point zero one and so on an idea is that ok
probably there will be some part of the themes
now so this is my topics topics are defined
by probability distribution over words now
what are my documents documents are again
some sort of probability distribution over
topics so i say d one what is d one d one
is having a distribution over these k topics
so i will say ok topic one occurs with the
probability of zero point zero five topic
two with probability zero point two topic
three with zero point five and so on ok so
i will say ok something like topic three and
topic two are more turbulent in this document
and not the other topics and same way i can
situate all the documents in some sort of
mixture of topics ok and this is very important
to understand the topic model so what are
my topics probability distribution over the
words and what are my documents again mixture
components or topics or you can offset probability
distribution over the topics ok
so this is all add up to one this will all
add up to one for all the topics for all the
documents ok so so what is that mean so you
have a topic like genetics remember no labeling
but we can see when you see that words so
this is probability word genetics so if we
have topic about genetics this will have words
about genetics with high probability and if
we have a topical of evolutionary biology
it will have a topic about evolutionary biological
of high probability ok so this will be making
two different themes in this connection and
and the model is a generative model and as
we understand generative model so it will
work like ok from we will first generate the
topics yes we first define the topics then
when we have the topics you will now start
building the documents you say ok document
will have some proportion of these topics
and then i will write the words in the in
the documents so topic search in that the
first and then the documents as per the generative
model ok
so so this picture will make themes more clearer
so so what so we are having seen some nice
colors here so on the left you are seeing
some topics right that's all you are talking
about we are having a set of topics any topic
is a probability distribution over the words
in the collection so like here this topic
has the word gene with the probability of
point zero four d n a with point zero two
genetic with point zero one life with point
zero two this is different topic brain neuron
nerve right data computer number different
probabilities you see seen their different
themes
now once we have this corpus wide themes so
so each topic is a distribution over words
do you understand that now what is a document
so you are seeing a collection here and there
are a lot of documents right and we are being
shown one document so each document is a mixture
of corpus wide topics so these are my corpus
wide topics now i will take a particular mixture
of these topics so suppose one of my mixture
is here i take this topic red yellow and blue
i will take these three topics only maybe
others away with a very very small fraction
and this defines the topic distribution of
my doc document
now so i have now seen said that my document
contains these topics with some proportions
now how do i generate the words in the documents
right that is important i need to generate
the words so how are these words generated
that's again interesting so you have this
you think of it as a multinomial distribution
and from this distribution you sample a topic
ok suppose the first sample is this pink that
pink topic that is about a organism life evolve
and so on ok these sample is topic
now from the same topic you have to generate
a word how do you generate a word again this
topic is what a probability distribution over
words think of it as a multinomial distribution
against a sample a word from here and that's
what you will generate in the document and
this we will keep on going for generating
all the words in the document in the in the
document so you will say ok next word i will
again sample a topic i get this yellow topic
about gene d n d n a genetics i use this topic
to generate a word by sampling from a multi
ah multinomial distribution and that's what
are you keep on repeating this is for this
document again for next document i will select
a mixture of topics ok and then once i have
the mixture i will again keep on selecting
the words that will go in the document
so now so so this is a statistical model also
we called it a generative model so what is
this reflect so it reflects to two important
things what are those all the document in
the collection share the same set of topics
right we have an underlying set of topics
all documents are sharing the same set although
the proportions are different ok so each document
exhibits those topics in different proportions
that is one important fact and then what is
the other other fact each word in each document
is drawn from one of the topics where the
selected topic is chosen from the per document
distribution over topics ok
so is that clear so for each document i have
a collection of top i have a distribution
about topics so i say ok this topic is probably
point two point five point one and so on now
each word in the document is sampled from
this ah distribution how you sample a topic
first and then as per the topics probability
distribution you sample a word ok this this
we will covered in the generative model in
more details but that is the intuition that
we showed also from the picture see there
are two important facts about l d f
now so if we think about the example article
from science magazine that we were seeing
so the distribution over topics would place
a probability on genetics data analytics and
evolutionary biology ok and each word will
be drawn from one of these topics so what
will happen when you are doing the influencing
you will say ok these this document contains
these three topics and how do we generate
a word you will sample a topic from here and
as for the topics probability distribution
sample a word and keep on generating the words
so so this is the genetic model but is that
what you also see when we have a real corpus
we apply l d a and do an influencing so that
is what is being shown so for this collection
of science papers so ah in proper model was
trained with hundred topics and this is what
you see so these are the hundred topics and
for this particular document some topics have
a high probability so this topic have probability
point roughly point four point one five point
one two and the next one having point zero
five so if you see the top four topics in
this in this particular document and try to
see the the the most probable words in these
topics so that's what you see so this topic
has human genome d n a genetics and so on
since our topics that we were showing earlier
and you see this was obtained without doing
any manual labeling so you you find out ok
this this document contains these four different
themes important themes and this is you can
also do some labeling later on manually this
is not done by l d a but get this is also
not very very important so what is important
is that i l d a can help you to obtain this
sort of ah distribution this in a very uncivilized
manner so you can find out what are the overall
themes and for a document what are the most
important themes
so now so we talked about ok what is the generative
model of l d a but what is the main problem
of l d a ok so we are saying ok we will generate
the topic first and then we will generate
the documents right by sampling a distribution
of topics each each for each word i will take
a topic it's distribution i will take a word
and so on ok but that's not how we write the
documents right ah so so how will that we
used so so it has to be used in a manner that
i am observing some data i have the generative
model and now i am trying to estimate the
parameters of this genetic model by using
my observations that is what parameters will
maximize the likelihood of seemed observation
so this is like reversing this whole process
of ah l d a that we are talking about ok
so so so we know the documents object in a
collection and if the documents but i do not
do the topic structure so i do not know what
are my topics so whatever distribution of
words within each topic i do not know for
each document what will be the distribution
of topics and i also do not know for each
ah for each word in a document what will be
the topic assignment i do not know any of
this a priori so this is all my hidden structure
so center problem l d a is to reverses in
to process and use the observed documents
to infer the hidden structure so what is the
hidden structure can you infer that by seeing
only the object documents and this may also
called as some sort of reversing the genetic
process and that is a center problem of l
d a so so this is this initial introduction
lecture was about to give to give you the
intuition but now that you have some intuition
of what l d a is what topic model is we will
next going to details about what is the mathematical
model of l d a ok and how do you solve this
problem of ah reversing the generative process
ok so that will be recovering in more details
in the next lecture
thank you