so welcome back for the second lecture of
this week so we had a started a formulation
of topic models in the in the last lecture
so but we mainly focused on ah the basic intuitions
so so today we will do the the so mathematical
formulation of ah latent dirichlet allocation
so that is the main ah sort of topic models
that i used also known as l d a so so we were
here and we were seeing that what is the central
problem problem of l d a so problem we were
saying was that we we have observing only
the documents but we know nothing about all
the parameters of my generative model so i
do not know what are my topic ah what are
my topics what are the topic proportions of
the document and i do not know what is the
per document or per per word topic assignment
i do not know that
so my real problem is from my observation
i want to reverse the gen gen ah generative
model and come up with all these probabilities
so ah so yeah so this figure will ah will
help you in understanding this goal so remember
we saw an earlier figure where we had all
these topics given to us we knew what are
the proportion topic proportion for this document
and then we were drawing topic for each word
in this document but now so in in reality
i will only have the or the documents so i
know all these documents so i know what are
the words but i do not know anything about
what are my topics what are these proportions
and what are these topics assigner for individual
word
so i have to compute the distribution conditioned
on all the documents that i am seeing in my
data so ah another simple example to listen
the addition behind the generative model so
here you have some thirty seven thousand text
passages from some educational material and
suppose you run l d a you found roughly three
hundred topics so here in this slide what
you are seeing you are seeing four different
topics so you are having the topic like two
forty seven which has what like drugs drug
medicine effects body etcetera another topic
having words like red blue green yellow white
another word about mind thought remember memory
thinking and another topic about doctor patient
hospital care and so on
so therefore the topics that that are there
in the corpus by running l d a over these
thirty seven thousand text passages now to
to get intuition about the generative model
so what was in the generative model you have
some topics now how to generate topics we
take some of these topics in a in some proportions
and you start generating words for that now
so so suppose you try that so suppose you
take topic two forty seven and five ok so
so suppose i give an equal probability of
the first two topics so what can a document
you can generate ok this thing we will see
these topics so first topic is about drugs
medicine person marijuana second and another
topic is red blue green colors so suppose
i blind these two topics together so what
kind of document can i generate ok so there
can be some different sort of documents you
can think of so one could be that someone
who was taking a lot of alcohol marijuana
and so on and it affected it's color perception
so suppose you want to document general document
like that we will blend these two topics together
and and write that similarly suppose you want
to blend these two topics together ok so this
topic is about mind thought remember memory
forgotten ok and this is about doctor medical
nurse patients and so on so here if you blend
these two topics together you may generate
the document that says ok someone who had
suffered some sort of memory loss and it's
led to visit of the doctor so ok so like that
you are having different topics you can blend
some of these topics and then generate doc
document so this is the generative view ok
so we can give a equal probability to the
first two topics that gives some sort of documents
and equal probability to the last two topics
that give me another sort of document so now
this single this single picture explains both
the the parts the generative part and the
inference part together so what you are seeing
the left figure so this is the generative
model so you are generating some documents
and how are you doing that so we are having
some topics suppose you are having two topics
probably one topic to each topic is nothing
but a distribution over words so you are having
some words like bank loan bank money loan
ok so these mean this words coming multiple
times here so this words are having high probability
on the other hand second topic is river stream
bank river so on so these are two topics
now using these two topics i am trying to
generate my documents so how can i generate
the documents i will mix these topics so suppose
i only take topic one and i can have a generate
document that contains words like money bank
loan and so on i can just take topic two and
generate words like river bank stream and
so on but i may also take both these topics
instead say equal proportion and generate
document like money bank they were loan stream
bank money so what you seen here in this document
to the words are labeled with topic one as
well as two because the words could have come
from another topic
on the other hand in document one all the
words are labeled with topic one doc three
also all the words are labeled with topic
two because we have the only topics pre possible
in these documents so this is my generative
model idea so here everything here you have
the topics you have per document proper proportions
and you also have per document per word topic
assignment so you know the topics for each
individual word also
now what is the statistical infe statistical
inference part so inference part you only
know your three documents so you know my doc
one contains these words doc two contains
these words doc three contains these words
especially but you do not know what are your
topics and you do not know what are the ah
proportion of various topics that are represent
in each document so all these numbers you
do not know and you also do not know for each
word what is the topic assignment and all
these you have to infer so i i hope with this
figure this clear what do i mean by my generative
model and what is my problem that is to infer
all these probabilities of my generative models
only from my observation
so now important points about l d a so first
of all it uses a bag of words assumption so
i hope by now you understand what is a bag
of words assumption that is i am not looking
at the order in which the words occur so this
is like a bag forming so i am taking all the
words and putting them in in a set it's not
like in list where some order is important
so l d a does not model the word order as
it's so it takes only what are the words present
in any order
second and i guess he would have also noticed
that in the previous ah example l d a s are
also good at capturing polysemy so remember
what is polysemy polysemy is a given word
might have multiple senses so in the case
of topic models what can i translate that
that means the same word might correspond
to multiple topics and this is perfectly allowed
because each topic can have it's own probability
distribution so that means the same word can
come in two different topics also i remember
the previous slide we are having the word
like bank that was coming in both the topics
and that is perfectly allowed so that way
topic models can capture better this word
is coming from topic one and topic two in
it's different senses
so the way the model is defined there is no
notion of the words being mutually exclusive
to the topics ok so for example money and
river can give high probability to the word
so both money and river topics can have high
probability for the word bank you think that
is perfectly defined
now to understand the l d a model so what
is the l d a model so you have to first see
what is a graphical notation ok so if you
are not gone through some of this graphical
notations so this slide tries to explain how
do we interpret the graphical notations so
here what you are seeing i am having some
variables so having a variable y and some
variables x one to x n so ah all these nodes
when that i see my graphical ah model these
are random variables so i have random variable
x one to x n
now what are these edges these edges will
denote the possible dependence so here i know
that x one depends on y x two depends on y
and x n also sub two x and all these depend
on the n y but there is not depend on each
other so that's why there is no edge from
x two to x four and x one to x two so these
depend only on y then there is a difference
that some are shaded some are not so what
is that so observes observed variables are
shaded so that means these are the variables
that i am observing and this is a hidden variable
that is not shaded and to simplify this notations
what we can use we can also group some variables
together so some max instruction that is being
repeated you can put it in the plate notation
so this is you are seen in the in the right
hand side so you are having these and different
variables and you can group them together
by x n and you write here capital and that
means x n is repeated capital n times
so this and these are equivalent and this
further simplify these notation ok so once
we have seen this ah so how do we interpret
graphical notations then we can look at look
at the graphical notation for l d a so what
is the so ok so just one more thing that once
we have this notation we can also compute
the the probability of this ah the whole graphical
structure so i have variables y x one to x
n so probability would be i have the probability
of y and each of these depend only on y so
the probability of this whole structure can
be probability of y times probability of x
one given y x two given y up to x n given
y
so so this graphical ah the the structure
of my graph also defines what are the conditional
dependence between various variables and that
i can use to write my joint probability distribution
ok so this is my joint probability distribution
over all these variables so now let us see
what is the graphical model for l d a so now
so you know ah from the previous slide how
do interpret graphical model so all these
nodes are random variables and observed variables
are shaded ok so the only shaded part is ah
w d n these are my object words everything
else is hidden
now what are everything else so there are
some plates here so let us see this one capital
k and what are these topics so what i am saying
here there are capital k different topics
and each topic is a probability distribution
ok so this is the probability distribution
over top over different words for a given
topic for a topic it's small k ok so beta
k is what is the probability of word one what
is the probability of word two etcetera for
the topic k and this i am doing for all the
capital k topics
then let us look at this part so i have capital
d different documents in my collection so
for a given document small d i have figure
d variable that denotes per document topic
proportions so for this document is small
d what are the proportions in which you are
blending different topics together so this
will be different for different topic different
documents so you are having capital d different
documents and there is again a dirichlet parameter
here and a topic hyper parameter here so we
will discuss what are these ah but right now
you can understand by simply these beta k
is the distribution over words for a given
topic and theta d is a distribution over topics
for a given document
now let us go inside so here now we are going
to one particular document and this can have
capital n words and what are these so you
are having per word topic assignment z n yes
ah each word will have only one topic and
this is the actual word that you are observing
and these are all hidden so i do not know
what my betas i do not know my theta i do
not my z n so this is only the explain what
are my ah what is what are different nodes
here what are the different plates here so
your plates corresponding to topics documents
as well as the words in a single document
and you have all the variables that we were
ah using ah all the the notion that we were
using earlier there are variables for each
of these
now let us see how what is the actual generative
model how we generated the words using this
structure so what is the generative model
so firstly you draw each topic beta i as for
the dirichlet higher higher hyper parameter
eta ok and you do that for all the k topics
so first of all we generate the model you
are drawing drawing your topics ok so fine
i have my capital k topics now now you go
to your documents so for each document that
is small d draw topic proportions so you find
out what are the topics that are involved
in this document as dirichlet distribution
over alpha so we will talk about this dirichlet
distributions what what do i mean this dirichlet
distributions
so you draw a top topic proportion ok and
then for each word in my observation so far
i am go now going to these document for each
word you draw z n as a multiple from a multinomial
distribution over theta d and draw a word
from this ah so draw a topic and then draw
a word from this multinomial distribution
over beta z n
now yeah let's try to understand this a bit
more so let us go one by one draw is topic
beta i is your dirichlet distribution over
eta so ah so what i am doing here i have k
different topics so i am trying to draw the
proportion the the probability distributions
from my ah vocabulary so what i am saying
so i have k different topics topic t one t
two t three up to t k for these topic i am
drawing beta one beta two beta three and beta
capital k and what are these they are nothing
but the probability distribution over my ah
words in my vocabulary so it can be something
like yeah this is point zero one point zero
two point zero five so on this can be zero
zero point one so these distributions are
drawn by using a dirichlet over eta
so dirichlet it's a distribution over distributions
so it helps you decide what kind of distribution
will be preferred over another so that we
will again discuss so this we will discuss
later but the idea is which kind of distribution
you will prefer and this helps you draw some
distributions for all the k topics ok
now so this you have drawn now the next line
says for each document draw topic proportion
of theta d using dirichlet over alpha so now
these are your topics but in your collection
you have again capital e documents so document
ah one two ah small d capital d so they are
capital d documents in your collection now
what is it what are your drawing for each
document you are drawing theta d what is theta
d theta d is a probability distribution over
the topics so it will be something like ok
what is the probability of topic one what
is the probability of topic two what is the
probability up to topic capital d
so for each document you are drawing these
distributions and what are theta d theta d
are coming from the dirichlet over alpha so
again this alpha is telling me what kind of
topic distributions will i prefer over others
so these are my so first drawing the topics
then drawing the topic proportion for the
documents now what else now it says now suppose
i am going to this document then for each
word how do you ab[out]- words draw z d n
as in from a multinomial over theta d so theta
d is a probability distribution and it's a
multinomial distribution from there sample
one topic ok so this distribution k topics
suppose the z n is equal to five that is i
am taking topic five so for each what i will
draw one so it can be whatever that that comes
according to this multinomial distribution
suppose it is five now how do i generate the
word now i know the topic now i have to generate
a word so i go to so it says draw w d n from
multinomial of beta z d n what is z d n now
z d n knows my five that is the topic you
that you draw and now you take multinomial
over beta five so that means for beta five
fifth topic i will find out what is the so
i will have the distribution and from there
i will sample one word so i will sample about
from this probability distribution and that
is what i am generating
so this you will do for each of the capital
n words in my document and is the whole generative
model first you are generating your topics
then for each document topic proportions then
you are going to the individual topic going
to the individual word and generating that
word ok fine so that's what we were saying
in this slide
now so one interesting point here is why do
we name it at latent dirichlet allocation
ok so we are doing some allocation what why
latent and dirichlet coming so ah so latent
in this ah l d a say has a same sensing energy
latent semantic indexing so that is all these
topics are some some sort of latent variables
ok so there are some sort of hidden topics
some latent topics i do not know what are
these topics as such i cannot give them a
good maybe good labels also but there are
some distributions some hidden distributions
over my words and these are called latent
then what is dirichlet here so you you saw
the dirichlet distribution at two places so
that is the distribution that is used to draw
the per document topic distributions is a
dirichlet distribution ok so that is how am
i sampling topics for a given doc document
that is coming from a dirichlet distribution
and this result is used to allocate the words
of the documents to different topics and that's
why the word allocation is also coming ok
so you are having latent dirichlet and allocation
so now we will look at this dirichlet part
in bit more in bit more details so what are
the dirichlet distributions so if you ah think
about it so so if you incredibly try to understand
that this is a distribution over probability
distributions ok what do i mean by that so
dirichlet distribution is an exponential family
distribution over the simplex that is the
povasitive positive vectors that sum to one
ok
so when i talk about simplex so you can talk
about say one simplex one simplex would be
two elements say x one x two such that x one
plus x two is equal to one positive vectors
that added to one this is one simplex so you
can see that they are infinite solutions here
ok and you can read it as a line it's a line
and this might correspond to say zero one
this might be ah one zero so that is topic
one has zero topic to each or yeah x one is
zero x two is one here x one is one x two
is zero and any point you can accordingly
give some definition what are the values of
x one x two ok
so you can see that this will be a line simple
line x one plus x two is equal to one this
is my one simplex then you can have two simplex
then you are having three things x one plus
x two plus x three there are two one ok in
this would be some sort of triangle ok so
this point might correspond to say x one is
one x two is zero x three is zero so this
might be x one is zero x two is one x three
is zero this might be zero zero one and then
each point we will have some proportion such
that all three add up to one this is my two
simplex like that you can define of any and
simplex so if you are having k topics you
can think of it as k minus one simplex ok
so now what is my dirichlet distribution so
so now we are saying it's an exponential family
distribution over the simplex that is a positive
vectors that up add up to one so again let
us try to understand that intuitively first
so what i am i am saying here suppose i am
having a two simplex then lot of different
value is my three ah x one x two x three they
can take they can take a lot of different
values so i can take values like one zero
zero i can take values like point three three
point three three point three four and things
like that they can take a different values
like point five point two five point two five
etcetera
so what my dirichlet distribution does it
gives me a probability of these probability
distribution so what is the probability of
getting distribution like this what is the
probability of getting a distribution like
this ok so that is what kind of distributions
i will prefer so i can use that to say that
i will prefer distributions where one topic
one of the topics as a high probability and
others have very low probability or i will
like to have a distribution where all the
topics have a equal probability
so these kind of constraints you can put by
using your alpha ok so that's where the formulation
is so what is the probability of theta that
is a distribution over these ah topics given
my alpha that is some -[d]rawn function so
even if we forget about this term so this
is multiplication over theta i to the power
alpha i minus one ok so let's look at this
term only so ah what is being said here
so probability theta given alpha is multiplication
over theta i to the power alpha i minus one
ok so let's try to understand that suppose
my alpha i is say a point one versus alpha
i is equal to say two what would happen in
the two cases and let us say i took look at
two different thetas so my theta one is zero
point nine eight zero point zero one zero
point zero one ok one topic has a high probability
others have roughly zero and theta two is
say point three three point three three point
three four and now you can see what kind of
alpha will prefer one theta over another one
so let us take the case with zero point one
alpha i zero point one so what would you is
the probability of this getting this distribution
it will be ah zero point nine eight to the
power minus point nine zero point zero one
to the power minus point nine zero point zero
one to the power minus point nine ok and this
probability would be same point three to the
power minus point nine point three three to
the power minus point nine and so on on the
other hand if i take alpha i is equal to two
then this would be point nine eight times
so alpha i minus one will become become one
the power is one point zero one times point
zero one and this will become point three
three times point three three times point
three three
now what is your observation here so one thing
we see it that if you ah take alpha is equal
to two if you take alpha is equal to two then
the the topics where so the distribution where
one topic is having very small probability
we will get a over all very small probability
right your multiple point nine eight by point
zero one times point zero one this will become
very small only when this will be ok this
is like one by three times one by three times
one by three so as you increase alpha it will
prefer to have topics or or the distributions
where each topic the word probability is roughly
equal ok
so it will prefer this one but if you having
a smaller alpha then what you are seeing so
now point zero one to the power point nine
this will be now can written as ah hundred
to the power point nine ok this will become
very large and this will be ah ah roughly
this will not be large ok so so what will
happen as your alpha becomes small they will
prefer the probability distribution where
one topic is having high probability and others
are having low probability
so by tuning your alpha you can prefer one
topic probability one sort of distribution
over the distribution ok so so this is my
dirichlet distribution so now again to give
you some visualization so here are two different
sort of simplex ah so alphas as such you can
interpret it as some prior observation count
on the number of times a topic j is sampled
individual alpha j so that is how many times
this topic will be sampled but so so and you
can also think as some forces and higher alpha
will move the topics away from the corner
of the simplex so let me come back to this
point again so you are saying two different
simplex one where ah the topics are moved
away from the the corners ok these are being
moved away and here you are going towards
the corners and this is for because of higher
values of alpha and we will come back to this
again
so now when alpha is less than one there is
a bias to big topic distribution is favoring
just a few topics and this is what we saw
just now on paper that when alpha is equal
to is less than one it tends to prefer the
distributions where only a few topics as a
high probability and others have lower probability
now while in general you can take different
alphas for your different topics what is convenient
effect you take all help us to be rough to
be the same so you have a singular hyper parameter
alpha so i will all alphas are same now what
matters now is what is the value of this alpha
ok so the relatively they are the same all
alpha one to alpha ah and alpha capital d
all for all the documents they are the same
ah sorry alpha one to alpha call capital k
they are same but what is the relative number
is it like what is the number is it like point
one two five there will be a matter
so now if alpha is small what will happen
you will tend to prefer topics with ah way
which sorry you will tend to prefer distribution
where one topics will have a higher probability
so remember how do we define simplex so in
this case what this it is boundary means so
this colors denote what is the probability
distributions ok so black means a high dist
probability distribution and and so on and
as you as the ah as it diminishes so the the
color becomes ah so faded then you are seeing
that the the probability is decreasing
so in the left hand side figure the probability
is mostly centered for in the in the in the
center of the simplex by in right hand side
it is moving towards the corners ok so that
you can interpret it as if in this simplex
whenever all three topics have the same weight
it is given a higher probability here even
if one topic is having in in more proportions
than others it is getting a high probability
so this is not moving away from the center
of this simplex
so it is going towards the corner so if you
go to the corner that means one topic has
the high probability other two have the small
probabilities ok so this is favoring also
to have topics where sorry also to have distributions
where one topic has high probability than
others while this we favor the distributions
where all three topics have roughly equal
probability ok so now you can easily tell
which one is corresponding to higher alpha
lower alpha so the one that corresponds to
lower alpha will be like that it will favor
distributions where one topic is having a
high probability than others
now this is some some ah from simulation what
happens if you take different values of alpha
so if you take alpha is equal to one what
kind of distributions are preferred so there
are fifteen documents here that are being
shown and there are ten different topics so
we see the distributions are ok so you are
having some distribution for topic t two t
three and so on for these fifteen documents
they are different different distributions
but suppose you try to now increase the value
of alpha as you go to ten so as you increase
the value of alpha it will start favoring
those distributions where all the topics are
roughly same probability you see now this
is getting flattens so you are having you
are now seeing all the topics and if you try
to increase ah alpha to hundred you will see
all the topics have same probability and it's
not something that you will there
so it's not good that each document has all
the topics in same probability then if the
topic model is does not put in any sense so
ah is equal to one was looking ok so so this
kind of distribution we would like but now
suppose i want to i want to decrease the value
of alpha if suppose i go from one to point
one now what you are seeing it will start
favoring the distributions where one topic
has a high probability or one or maybe two
ok but suppose i increase i decrease it further
to point zero one
so most of the problems of probability zero
only one topic comes as a probability one
or here two topics are coming if you further
reduce this value to point zero one you get
only one topic in each document so that will
give you some idea of how if you modify or
change this parameter alpha how does this
effect the overall topic distribution in my
corpus ok certain kind of distribution we
will get reference over others
now for l d a there are a lot of interventions
that are available so ah and these are like
very very popular you can also use implementations
that are available in gensim so now so we
are again so we have discussed all the in
genetic part in but now i am full details
that how do we what is the generative model
of l d a but remember what is your problem
how do we infer all these probabilities so
that is i am given a correction of documents
and i want to infer per document topic assignment
z d n per document topic topic distributions
theta d and per corpus topic distributions
beta k i want to infer all this
now once i am able to infer all this i can
use this to find out say to use to for information
retrieval document similarity and many other
task but the question is once i am given these
observations of the of the words how do i
infer all these ah probability values ah so
so there are different ways of doing that
so we will discuss about one such method in
the next lecture
thank you