so hello everyone welcome to the third lecture
of this week so we are talking about topic
models and we have discussed what is the formulation
of latent dirichlet allocation and we say
that what are the different parameter that
we need to learn we need to learn ah mainly
three parameters that is what are my ah ah
topic distributions given a topic what is
the probability of each word what are my per
document topic proportion so that is my thetas
and then per document per word topic assignment
that is by z so this i have to compute so
this i have to compute the posterior distribution
of all this parameter given my observation
observation is all my corpus all the documents
that i am seeing so so in this lecture we
will discuss one ah interesting method for
doing that that is gibbs sampling and then
in the end we will also talk about some simple
applications that once we had learnt topic
models over a corpus what are the some of
the simple things that you can do ok so ah
so for approximating the posterior probabilities
of all these parameters the algorithm generally
fall in two categories
so one are sampling based algorithms so that
is from the posterior you try to collect the
samples of the distributions and then ah approximate
it with the empirical distribution and that's
what we will focus on in gibbs sampling and
there are also variational methods so where
we convert the inference problem to some sort
of optimization problem and try to learn the
parameters that we optimize that so so both
the methods are very ah very much used in
in the literature so we will see we will see
gibbs sampling that is an easier to understand
method that i will i will say
so ah so gibbs sampling are some sort of markov
chain ah monte carlo methods so what is the
idea so having a high dimensional distribution
so think about all the possible values that
that your parameter can take all your betas
ah theta inject they can take so huge number
of values ok so idea here is you sample on
an lower dimensional subset of variables and
each subset is conditioned on whatever as
it known ok so you do not computing the joint
probability of everything you are assuming
sum to be known and computing probability
for others and that you keep on doing in terms
for all the all the variables so sampling
is done sequentially and proceeds until the
sampled value is approximate my target distribution
and it directly estimates the posterior distribution
over z and uses this to provide estimates
for beta and theta
so will we will find out the distribution
over z and then use that to compute my theta
and beta and we will see how do we do that
so so what is the idea so assume that you
are you are having a corpus and in the corpus
you have some documents and words ok now take
so you will ah assume that in a in one of
the iteration you are at a particular word
that is ah the word token i and what you want
to find out what is the topic assignment probability
what's the probability that is ith token will
be assigned to topic j probability z i is
equal to j that's what you want to find out
so now how how do you do that now re you represent
the collection of documents by a set of word
indices w i and document indices d i for this
token i so it simply says that you has a lot
of words find out what is the corresponding
word token for this i that may be called w
i w i will give you the particular index and
similarly d i d i will be the particular document
where you are having this token
so now so what gibbs sampling does it consider
each word token in turn and estimates the
probability of assigning the current word
token to each topic conditioned on the topic
assignment of all other word tokens so what
it is saying that in the particular iteration
assume that given the topic assignment for
all the other words except this word now based
on this you try assign a topic to this word
so what will happen we are having a set of
documents ok so these are your documents and
suppose you know you unique words these are
the your words and here at a i th here at
a ith token so the corresponding document
will be called d i this is i token and the
corresponding word will be called w i ok so
now what you have to find out probability
that the topic assignment for this word will
be z that's what we have to find out and what
is assumed by is that in this iteration you
know the topic assigned for everything else
so you know what are the topics that assigned
for all different words involve that but you
want to estimate to find out the topic for
this particular i th word so you have to so
how do you do that you first estimate this
probability and this you do condition on everything
else so write it like this probability z i
at j given the topic assignment for all the
words other words minus sign is everything
other then this i and what is the word index
and what is the document index this is what
we want to find out
now intuitively what should it depend on so
what is the probability that this ith token
will be will be given assigned the topic j
what should it depend on so we think in terms
of topic models this probability that the
i th word should be assigned the topic z should
depend on two things one is so we say that
document consist of certain topics ok so if
this topic is prevalent in the document there
might be a high chance that this word is assigned
this topic j so that is how likely is topic
j to be assigned to d i what is the next thing
how likely is that this word occurs in topic
j ok is word w i for topic j so we have two
things i need to know now how do i know this
one how likely is topic j to be assigned to
document d i you see i am given the topic
assignment for all other words in this document
so i find out what section of words in this
document are assigned this topic j ok divide
by the number of words
so this i can computationally by this topic
assigned now how do you compute this how likely
each word w i for topic j i I will again see
in topic j what are the different words that
come and how many times word w i comes in
this topic j and this i can used to to compute
this probability and then i can multiply these
two to find out what is the probability of
a topic j been assigned to this word token
i and this i will do for all excuse me topics
j is equal to one to k so this will give me
a multinomial distribution then to give a
assignment to this word i will sample from
this multinomial distribution and then from
sampling i will assign one topic and i will
i will assign the topic here so suppose the
topic is five i will put this is five and
then i will move to the next word token and
then i will assume that this is not given
and i will take everything as given do that
find the topic assignment and that's what
i keep on doing
so now once the intuition clear let us go
back to the formulation so yes from this conditional
distribution we are sampling a topic and we
are storing it as the new topic assignment
for the word and this is written as this assignment
probability that ith word has the has a topic
j given everything else so so how do we achieve
this how do we compute all these values for
that i need to ah keep two different matrices
so one is c w t of dimensions w times t another
is c d t of dimensions d times t so ah so
what are these matrices so one is c w t w
times t and next is c d t d times t t is the
number of topics w is the number of words
and d is the number of documents so what do
they store so c w j w t that is i take the
word w and topic j so w j w t so this element
is called c w j w t this contains the number
of times word w is assigned to topic j not
including the current inst current instants
so we are taking at the current instants except
that how many times this word is assigned
this topic that you can find out from the
your whole ah data you will actually keep
this stable so we will just update the values
ok so let me give an point point you know
how many times this word is assigned topic
j so we will do that for all the values in
this matrix how many times this word is assigned
this topic yes similarly a volume at c d t
small d j this will contain for the document
d topic j number of times topic j is assigned
to some word token in document d that is how
many words in the document d are assigned
to topic j in that again you can you can have
all the values
so this will again be not included in the
current distance we will find out how many
times ah any word in document d is assigned
this topic and we will do it for all the documents
so this you will have these two matrices c
w t c d t and you are missing now what is
element missing now once you have these two
matrices how do i compute probability z i
is equal to j given z minus i w i d i and
research may depend on two different things
so let us see that so depends on two parts
one is ah what is the probability of word
w under topic j remember we are talking about
two parts so how what will depend on so we
are saying that it will depend on how likely
is this word to come under topic j second
is how likely is this topic to be assigned
to document d two thing's how likely is this
word to come on to topic j how likely is this
topic to come under document d now how do
i write this probabilities in terms of this
matrix ah elements how likely is word w w
to come under topic d j so that will be c
i th word topic j w t summation over all the
words so this will give p probability for
this word
summation over all words c w j w t ok similarly
for how likely is topic z to come on the document
d this would be c d i ok for the current ins
instance j d t summation over now for all
the topic that are assigned in this document
so this will be summation over all my topics
c d t c d t capital d t ok so this will be
the simple formulation now ah so there are
certain priors that you take here so you will
have some sort you can can these are some
sort of smoothing so here you have some smoothing
parameter eta similarly it will be plus w
times eta here alpha plus t times alpha so
smoothing parameters
and this will again to make it a probability
it is normalized so instead of calling it
equal to we will say proportional to this
so now this gives you the formulation probability
that the i th word token will be assigned
topic j given all this so now you can say
that what are these eta and alpha so this
is my digital parameters that that we were
seeing earlier and and you can also ah correlate
this with their values so suppose your alpha
is high if your alpha is high what would happen
this value will not matter and all the topics
will be assigned roughly equal probability
and that's what was happening if you keep
on increasing alpha you are going towards
a distribution where all topics have some
probabilities but if you alpha is very very
small then what will matter is only discount
and that's why you're going towards only a
few topics so these are some so these are
the intuitions same thing you can do with
eta
so if eta is high all the words will have
equal probability of coming into topic if
it is low then certain distributions will
be preferred so now so this is the formulation
for probability that z i is equal to j so
left part here is the probability of w word
w under the topic j so that is how likely
the word is for a topic and the right part
is the probability of topic j under the current
topic distribution for the topic and this
what we had seen also in the previous ah so
when we are doing it on the paper in in the
previous lecture now this will give you the
probability distribution over all the topics
given this stroke now what is the next thing
you have this multinomial distribution you
sample a topic from here
so these the whole algorithm in a nutshell
so is how do you start so each word token
is assigned to a pre defined so random topic
so a random topic in one to two so we have
this whole collection and you assign some
random topic random topic to each word now
you you compute your two matrices c d t and
c w t from that assignment now for each word
token so in this situation what you will do
for each word token you sample a new topic
as per this distribution and you have seen
that once you have the matrices formulated
you can find out this probability distribution
and you can sample a topic for sampling for
a multinomial distribution and when you will
sample a topic and put that topic in that
in that ah for that word accordingly adjust
your two matrices
so now then you make complete single pass
through all your words in your corpus that
is called one gibb sample so this is your
one gibb sample ok and then you will do it
again and again and again so what happens
is that initially for certain iterations you
can call it as a burnin period initially burnin
period so where you will not store those samples
u use them to update the values but you will
not store but after some word burnin period
you will start storing this values now you
will not store every conjugative values so
what might happen because you are just using
a previous values to compute the next one
they may be very very correlated so we will
have some regularly spaced at some regularly
expressed interval you will store this samples
so something like ah so you are doing this
iterations over the full ah corpus so there
will be some initial burinin period so you
are computing gibb sample ok after burnin
in period you will you will have reliable
gibb sample but what will happen those that
are very very close they will be highly correlated
so will say i will store some regularly space
intervals so say i'll store it up every hundred
after every hundred relations i will store
this so we have we will have cube multiple
gibb samples now so each sample contains all
your z ok all your z all your assignment is
consist con contain and then and from here
you can compute your beta and ah theta and
then finally you can take an ah expectation
over all these values and this will give your
ah one particular ah approximation of a parameters
if we take a expectation over various ah samples
that you are getting from from gibb sample
so once you have this z how do you compute
your ah betas and theta that is very easy
we were actually using that to compute z so
betas are the probability that a topic j is
assigned to the i th word so this will be
from the matrix c w t so i will take c i j
w t plus eta divide over all ah words c k
j w t where is w eta similarly what is theta
j d that is what is probability of topic j
under document d it will be c d j d t plus
alpha divide by summation over all topics
c d k d t plus t alpha so once we have the
z then we can compute here ah beta and theta
also
so yeah this values will correspond to the
distribution of sampling a new token of word
i from topic j and sampling a new token in
document d from topic j now o it's just an
example to explain what what it means to use
gibb sampling so what is an example so this
is like so we are taking in a artificial data
and for a known topic model and applying the
algorithm will check if we can come back to
the same topic ah same ah topic distribution
that we started with so what is done here
let us say we have two topics so we are doing
a generation now and then we will see whether
gibbs sampling can infer back the original
ah topic distributions so what is done in
in genetic part let us say i have two topics
topic one topic two and simply we are saying
topic one assigns equal probability to three
words money loan and bank and topic two assigns
equal probability word river steam and bank
so all these three are assigned the probability
of one by three each fine so these are topic
distributions
now by arbitrary mixture of these two topics
we are generating sixteen documents so thats
how these sixteen documents look like so black
means topic one and white means topic ah two
ok so there are two topics so each document
has some number of words from different topics
so i am sorry you should initial look at only
the number of ah number of balls that is how
many words are there in the document
now to apply gibb sampling so that is why
you generated all these documents so this
makes sense that you are generating documents
that are having bank money loan lot of documents
there is some document that contain only river
stream bank so this are documents from only
one topic these are document only from another
topic and there are some documents that are
mix in these two topics so that's how you're
doing generating sixteen documents
now your task is can you use gibbs sampling
to find out what are the two topic distributions
here so what is done for that initialize all
the words to some topic so randomly that's
why you're seeing the random assignments so
black is topic one and white is topic two
some random assignment from this random assignment
you can have the two matrices c w t c d t
and then what you will do in each iteration
you will go to each word find out what is
the probability that this word will be assigned
to topics j sample from the distribution update
a matrices and you get some gibb samples
so once you do that so this is what you see
after sixty four iterations of gibbs sampling
can you see that it it actually ah ah looks
very very in ah close to what we had initially
so all this words are assigned to topic one
and all these words are assigned to the next
topic ok and you can see that bank money loan
are been assigned the same topic in you say
in a in a given document and that makes co
ah lot of sense and from this ah particular
sample you can also compute your betas and
if you compute the betas they come out to
be very very close to what you started with
so started with each ah word having a probability
of one by three and that's what is roughly
what we obtain and this is just an explanation
that how gibbs sampling can help you to recover
what is a original topic distribution this
is from artificial data but now you can do
that for any real corpus we have the real
corpus and we want to find out what is the
topic distributions apply gibbs sampling and
find out that so there are various tool kits
available that i also disused in last lecture
so where you can give a corpus you can define
the number of topics and they can give you
the the all this values what are theta what
are betas what are vapor topic per per document
per word topic distribution
now once you have that what are sort of simple
ah tasks that you can do with this so for
example one very important task is can you
compute similarity between two documents and
how will you do that so suppose i have two
document given in d two to compute the similarity
between that i will see what is the topic
distributions for d one and d two so so how
if they are similar i will say that the two
documents are similar but if their topic distributions
are different i will say they are different
plus so i have two documents d one and t two
i find out what is theta for d one what is
theta for d two now i can say distance between
ah two distribution p q i can use the k l
divergence summation p i log p i by q i so
now i compute the k l divergence between the
two topic distributions for d one and d two
and that will get me how what is the distance
between the two documents that is one every
standard measure for finding out how how similar
two documents are
because this is asymmetric you can also do
something like one by two d p q plus d q p
so we can also use that as some sort of distance
symmetric so that is you have now the corpus
you find know the topic distributions now
you can use that to compare the similarity
between any pair of documents so that is one
very very important application of topic models
then you can find out what is similarity of
ah the document with reciprocal query ah what
is the probability that query is generated
from a document that is what we study in information
three rate that you have a lot of documents
you want to find out given a query which document
should be ah ranked higher this will be ah
computed using what is the probability that
the query is generated from this document
so whichever document give the highest probability
of generating the query is given the highest
ah score now whats the formulation you want
to find out probability of query given the
document the query is nothing but a set of
words so if we take it simply easily multiplication
over all the words in my query probability
w k given d i now how do i compute probability
of word given d i there i am using the l d
a ah the l d a model so i will say so i will
marginalize it over all the topics so this
will be covered all words in query summation
over all topics probability w t given topic
is j probability topic is j given document
d ok this is nothing that comes from your
beta directly that comes here from your theta
directly
and use that to find out what is the probability
of this query given this document this is
again a very interesting use then you can
also use it to find out these two words are
similar what is the probability of word w
two given w one that is nothing but again
you marginalize over all the topics and this
you will-- compute from ah either your beta
or by agent based here so this will give me
given a word w one what are some of the likely
words in my vocabulary
and this you can find from computing words
similarity and all that you have to using
doing using distributional similarity and
and other stuff so this is that's thy this
is i given a nice method for capturing ah
semantics between words documents even sentences
so ah how do you validate at this words so
that's we saw a simple experiment see at the
word play by using topic model find out which
words have the highest probability given the
word play so probability of x given play find
out some top top words then you ask some humans
who say that when you hear the word play what
words come into your mind that is humans so
words like fun ball game work ground mate
child etcetera they come to their mind then
you try to see whether these two lists are
similar and you find that many words are similar
like ball game they come on top even in topic
model so this is the interest interesting
way of ah evaluating whether a model is doing
well for capturing words in that so ok so
we we discussed how do we use gibbs sampling
to to estimate these parameters and some simple
applications next we will also talk about
some non para parametric base model and what
are the different applications they can be
used for
thank you