so welcome back for the final lecture of this
week so we are talking about different l d
a variants and what are their applications
and we talked about three different variations
like code rate topic models dynamo topic models
and sewage topic models and we saw how they
can model different assumptions we can also
be used to pair the ah response as as a observation
inside the model to to make nicer topic models
so we now see in this lecture we will also
see some two other variants so one is called
relational topic models another is ah some
sort of nonparametric bayesian models and
you will see what sort of applications they
can be used for so ah what is the idea of
relational topic models see so in so when
you are talking about data so many a times
this is simple text data so where they are
not related to each other sometimes this is
like a network also
so where different observations or different
data points are connected together by some
sort of graphic structure so for example think
about the scientific articles so as such you
can think of them as separate different different
articles ok this is one document another document
different observations in fit a topic model
there or you can think of this as these are
documents that are also connected what is
the connection between the scientific documents
with a citation network one paper might cite
another paper ok
so if it will be citing another paper there
is a link between them so you are seeing these
observations are also connected similarly
think about the web page one web page might
give a hyperlink to another web page so again
these ob these are observations that are connected
then you can talk about friends then they
are connected friends in the social network
profile with the profile is kind of the document
and the connection is like the ah so and you
are trying to model the connection
so now what we are seeing here that can be
adapt our l d a model where such that it can
take care of not only the content but also
also of the also of this link that is also
contained in connection both can this we can
this be handled by the topic models and that's
where you have this variation called a relational
topic models or r t m s so relational topic
models try to take care of this variation
that i have the content as well as a connection
now now so before going to the model how how
we will try to do that suppose we did not
have this relational topic models what we
are trying to to predict here i have this
whole set of observations now which two observations
will be connected to each other so or let
us say i am talking about the scientific articles
when i knew a person is writing a new article
what are the papers he will cite how will
i model this
so so i will think of it as a learning problem
i will say ok i have a dataset i know there
are lot of papers and some papers writing
another papers ok so i will say ok i have
observations document d one d two d three
and so on d n i know d three is citing d two
i know d n is citing d three d n a citing
d one so on i have these observations right
and i want to find out when a new able d n
plus one comes in what will it cite how will
i solve this problem is suppose using l d
a what i will do i will first in l d a over
this corpus and i will find out ok this topic
distributions theta d one theta d two up to
theta d n ok you find that out then i try
to model ok given that this is theta d two
theta d three will they link together or whether
d three will link to d two
how will i model this again you can use a
regression here right so you can say ok given
theta d three and theta d two predict the
link yes or no so i have some positive examples
where ever there is link and negative examples
there were where ever there is no link at
run time when i get a new new document using
l d a i get theta d n plus one now i try to
combine it with d one to d n find out which
one it is more likely to linked that is one
way it can be handled
now does that remind your something so that
will remind if the now last topic that we
discussed that was supervised l d a remember
there also we had the same problem we said
ok each document has a response so each document
might have a response r one r two and so on
so we said ok one way could be take theta
d one and run a regression from theta d one
to r one theta d two to r two that was one
possibility idea plus regression but we said
we can do something smarter than that that
is we take it as an observation within my
model and we say ok with each document with
z you are also sampling your response variable
with some eta n sigma
now can we use the same idea in this relational
topic model also so the ah right now the difference
is that we are working with the pairs ok so
what we can do here we can say that i had
document d one i have document d two now this
will have some z this will have some z now
can i model whether they will link to each
other given their individual topics and this
can now be in observation inside my model
ok so this is idea this is a simple and direct
extension of this over the topic ah l d a
that can i now use pairs and model the response
as my another observation sorry model the
connection as my another observation
so so this is how it is done so you are having
the same topic models sorry same model for
so beta k the topic probabilities over over
different observations but now you look at
different pairs so let us look at these pairs
ah document d i and d z so they have theta
n theta z variable so what you are modeling
given ah the z i n and z j n their individual
topic probabilities whether they will link
to each other so there it is per pair this
is a binary link variable and this is a indirect
analogous to what we written in the case sewage
topic models is eta times this into this ok
plus some variance and so this can also allow
prediction about new and unlinked data
so how is it acted so what what are the examples
so how it will be used to something like this
suppose i have a top paper markov chain monte
carlo convergence diagnostics a comparative
review so and i want to find out what are
the other papers it will link to or i can
say ok suppose i am reading this paper what
are the other paper that are relevant to it
like a recommendation problem so i can use
this idea let what is the other other papers
that it will link to win my r t m model
so here is some examples that this is what
your r t m model gives and these are actually
important papers that this document actually
linked to so r t m in general can allow the
predictions that given ah a document with
new words what what are the document will
link to ok this is one thing that can be done
also suppose you give a link that this document
gives links to another document what will
be the approximate distribution of the document
that also can be found using my r t m model
so links given the new words of the document
and words given the links of a new document
both can be handled so so coming back to the
model so this formulation what it ensures
is that the same latent topic assignment is
used to generate the content of the document
and it also generate their linked structure
so ah you are not separately learning the
linked structure you are learning it at the
same time when you are lot learning your topic
distributions so that is interesting in this
r t m model
so from this z i n and z j n you are trying
to predict what will be your y i j ok now
here is one problem ah so so this is your
simple model so this is your simp ah this
is what your lda model is draw your topic
proportions then for each word draw the topic
assignment and the draw the word ok
now for the relational part for each pair
document d and d prime what you are doing
you are trying to sample the variable y whether
they will link or not and this depends on
the z d and z d prime and what is the function
it's a psi of ah given z d z d prime and this
is model like this this is ah as an exponential
function over eta transpose a hadamard product
over z d and z d prime now what do i mean
by that so remember ah in the sewage l d a
module also we did eta transpose z bar right
and this gave me a scalar two vectors you
are multiplying this ah giving you a scalar
you have the same dimensions right now here
also you have eta transpose same dimensional
has the number of topics and you are multiplying
it with z d bar hadamard product with z d
prime bar
now what is what are z d and z z d prime z
d is what are the topic probability is doc
document d ok and this is in document d prime
again they are vectors had not probe probe
probe is nothing but element wise wise product
see you multiply this element with this element
this element with this element and so on and
then you add it and multiply with eta transpose
so this will again give me a scalar ok and
plus you might add some sort of ah bias or
valence this is a bias here so z d is nothing
but the topics of probabilities in each document
use it for the pair and and get a hadamard
product of those and plus with bias term gives
you ok whether the document is likely to ah
ah these two pairs are likely to link or not
right eta transpose and this total thing and
in in the paper they also use the sigmoid
function apart from the exponential function
and link function models each per pair binary
variable as a logistic regression and this
is by eta eta and mu ok
so ah so this is your relational topic model
what is your what is one problem with this
model so for each pair of documents you have
to define their response that is whether they
are linking together or not so why d one d
two is it one or zero then in my document
is giving a link to another document you can
always say to one but whenever document is
not giving a link to another document it is
not necessary that they are not related at
all it may be that he is not giving the link
or the link might occur in future there are
many other things depending on the data points
so one thing is that whenever there is a link
you take it as one whenever there is no link
you take it as an unobserved variables so
i do not know if there is a link or not so
that also helps you in ah being computationally
efficient it it avoids getting you so many
different pairs of document right
so so that is in especially in the case of
social networks whenever there is an absence
of link you cannot take it as if ah y d one
d two is equal to zero for example also you
can see from your like facebook profile so
you are taking the profile as your documents
and you are finding out if this person will
become a friend of another person so even
if they have not friends at this time it might
happen that they will be become friends in
future so absence of the link cannot be taken
for that their response should be zero so
it can be taken as in an unobserved variable
that is a better solution
so so this is done and and then so they tested
whether this words better than the model of
l d a plus regression this was the person
that we saw that you take the topics from
document d one document d two and learn a
regression over there that is one option another
is you take the pair which are linking as
an observed variable and also use it for learning
your topics inside the model itself and that
they found gives much better performance than
l d a plus regression model for this task
given any document what is the document it
were linked so this is a other examples like
for this document competitive environments
evolved better solutions for complex task
documents like coevolving high level representations
were coming out to be it at ah first position
in the r t m model but we were not coming
out from l d a plus regression model so this
was something interesting at the so from this
model
now finally we will wrap up this week by some
small some simple discussion on nonparametric
bayesian models so so what do we see in the
case of l d a models so in l d a what we are
having we are defining that this corpus consists
of certain topics ok and then each document
i find out what are the topic assignment is
what i find out what is the topic assignment
for that word so what is one problem here
i have to tell a priori how many topics that
are there in the data but that may not be
an easy parameter to always give right you
may not know should i use ten topics twenty
topics hundred topics in this data
so can my model itself find out what will
be the number of topics as such and that's
where we come to this topic of nonparametric
bayesian so this so this parameter goes away
you do not have this parameter of number of
topics and anymore ok so in many data analysis
settings you will not know what is the number
of topics a priori so in bayesian nonparametric
models what we assume is that there is an
so we are not fixing number of parameters
but that also means ok my um data can have
any number of param ah of parameters that
means any number of topics
so i have to a start with the assumption that
there are infinite number of topics ok and
my data can take any finite number of them
so it can take hundred five hundred thirty
whatever it means so in generally i have an
infinite number of topics so that is so that's
what is interesting about it it assumes that
there are there is an infinite number of latent
clusters or topics but only a finite number
of them is used to generate the observed data
but you do not give it as an input to your
model how many such questions we need this
is what model on it's own comes up when it
sees the observations
so the posterior provides the distribution
over the number of clusters the assignment
of data to clusters and the parameters of
each cluster all these are different different
parameters of hilarity model that can be learned
from the bayesian nonparametric models so
we will see so there are actually many ah
different variations variations of this bayesian
nonparametric models also known as hierarchical
dirichlet processes because this is a ah very
wide topic we will not cover this topic in
detail in this course we will just give you
some intuition that what how do you come up
with this infinite topics right in your setting
so and how does it model any finite number
of topics in the data even if you are starting
with infinite topics
so we will talk about one particular setting
that is a chinese restaurant process that
can be used for modeling the ah or grouping
your observation into some finite number of
groups the number is not told a priori so
what is this process is quite interesting
so so the chinese restaurant process so so
we are talking about the restaurant so we
have saying that suppose this is a restaurant
where there are infinite number of tables
ok when you see the here here the term infinite
immediately what comes to your mind ok these
are the latent clusters so i have infinite
tables in that restaurant and then there are
customers that are coming up so we are like
observations so we are fitting the observation
to top to different ah clusters
now the model says ok ah when the customers
are coming in the restaurant how are the seated
on the tables now one thing that it says is
that the tables are of infinite capacity so
they can they can hand each table can take
as many customer as as you want so there is
no limit on the number of customers that can
sit on a table ok so now how do we assign
customers to the tables in this process and
that's where so it's a says ok so i have some
tables infinite number of tables so customer
one is comes in and sits at the first table
ok table one fine so customer one is no problem
now now the customer two comes in so idea
is that customers who two now sits on table
one with the probability one divided by one
plus alpha and sits on a new table with a
probability alpha divided by one plus alpha
ok here c is add adds up to one ok fine so
it can sit at either table one or table two
now when a new customer comes in certain points
of c n it can sit of suppose this table this
table this table is occupied it can sit either
at the occupied tables or add a new table
so what they say it can sit on any of the
occ occupied tables with a probability proportional
to number of customers already there ok an
on a new table with the probability proportional
to alpha so that is so remember that's what
we did here this is proportional to one this
is proportional to alpha and then we normalize
we get one divided by one plus alpha alpha
divided by one plus alpha i have given any
given a point of time you will have certain
configuration different tables will have different
number of customers
so new customer comes in it can sit of any
other table with a probability proportional
to the number of customers already there or
it can choose a new table and that's how you
can fill in any number of customers on any
number of tables so you will see at the end
at the end of this process you can have any
number of tables right so random process you
might have five tables filled ten tables filled
fifteen tables filled so you can have any
number of clusters this is now just does not
have to be defined a priori right we ah from
your ah sampling you can choose any number
of topics or clusters
now one thing what will be the effect of the
parameter alpha suppose your alpha is large
versus alpha is a small if your alpha is large
what will happen if alpha is large when a
customer comes in it has a there is a large
probability that will choose a new table ok
so that means with large alpha you can get
large number of topics so is it gives you
some idea ok if you want more number of topics
and each topic having small number of observations
then you will choose a large alpha but if
you choose a smaller alpha you probably by
you will probably choose a small number of
topics because ah if the customer will have
a higher probability of sitting at any of
the tables that are previously occupied so
that will be the effect of these alpha
so so coming back so first customer enters
and sits at the first table second customer
enters and sits at the first table with the
probability of one by one plus alpha and the
or the next unoccupied table with the probability
alpha divided by one plus alpha and when the
another customer arrives she sits at any of
the occupied tables with a probability proportional
to the number of previous customers already
seated on the table and at the next unoccupied
table to the probability proportional to alpha
and that's how i can distribute all the customers
in a restaurant and we saw that if i have
a large value of alpha i will have more occupied
tables and fewer customers per table right
so we saw that
now so so ok it's looks interesting if i have
a document i can model so these tables as
my topics and these words these customers
as my words and i can say ok which words are
send to what topics but how do i model my
whole corpus you see i can model my one this
can be thought of as my one document d one
i know ok what are the topics and what are
the customers but suppose i have a corpus
right that so i i generally i wanted for my
corpus so corpus means i will have multiple
such documents
now one thing would be i i fill it independently
for each document but if i do that there is
no correlation between the assignment here
in d one and d two ok so it might happened
d one i have first table some words are filling
in here like government table two some words
like a sports something ok and document d
two the word is sports might start coming
here and there will be no correlation between
topics here in this document topics in this
document ok so i cannot run this chinese restaurant
process independently for different documents
that way i will not be able to ah have a correlation
ah between these so what is actually done
so we saw that chinese restaurant process
it helps in obtaining a random partition as
the sequence of customers sitting at tables
in a restaurant so we get a random partition
of words into various topics now we also sit
tables can be thought of as topics and customers
as word in the restaurant or restaurant can
be thought of as document
however it cannot model the entire corpus
for that we can extend c r p to a set of restaurants
so that it can be extended to defining each
document as a separate restaurant ok and this
is called chinese restaurant franchise so
now we are going from chinese restaurant process
to chinese restaurant franchise so so this
franchise has a lot of restaurant and that's
why we will try to ah connect the different
topics so let us see how do we connect the
different topics
so again so this is what is similar to c r
p so customer in the jth restaurant sits at
tables in the same manner as in c r p ok so
customer comes in a in the restaurant any
of the restaurant now it saw it sees which
tables already occupied how many customers
are there the probability proportional to
the number of customers is sits at that table
and the probability proportional to alpha
it sits at the next unoccupied table so that
remains the same as c r p
now where is this ah connection among topics
coming and that is coming in from the nice
idea about the franchise that is let us say
that they just franchise wide menu so now
you have a new term of menu there is a certain
dishes that are there in all the all the restaurants
and that is franchise wide
so whenever a customer comes at a given table
it orders a dish from that menu now whoever
comes in next we will have the same dish whoever
customer comes in next we will share the same
same dish now this dish is shared throughout
the restaurants so now this dish at a table
exercise the topic of that ah of the document
so you can have so now the dishes are same
across the across the different restaurants
and that's why you can model it the same topics
so so how do we achieve coupling among the
restaurants so this is achieved by a franchise
wide menu so so what we say that the first
customer to sit at a table in a restaurant
chooses a dish from the menu and all the customers
was sitting sitting at that table will share
the same menu and this is our chosen with
a probability proportional to the number of
tables which already have that that serve
that dish so if this dishes serve at many
different tables across the franchise then
this will have a higher probability
so that we are also giving you prior probability
on choosing a bulk condition on a given table
so it will look something like that so what
you are seeing you are seeing three different
restaurants in this franchise one two and
three now this psi on one tells for the restaurant
one what is the dish at table one so this
is five one this is from the global menu of
dishes five one five two and so on it is a
global menu
the second table has five two third table
has five one that means more than one tables
can order the same dish that is possible in
that ah model so why because you see when
a customer comes in it will first choose the
table right so it can either to choose one
of the table that is occupied on your a right
table then when you choose the table it chooses
one of the dishes so that means it can the
same dishes dish can be chosen at more than
one tables ok so that means this table also
the same dish was chosen and so on
next second restaurant first table choose
dish five three second table five one third
third table five three and so on ok so it
has certain different are choices and and
then the third restaurant first table choose
five and second table choose five two and
so on now you also seeing the customer assignments
so in this first ah restaurant customers are
coming in theta one one theta one ah two theta
one three and so on theta one one sits a table
one theta one two sits a table two theta one
three at table one one four table one one
eight at table one five six here seven here
and so on so there are certain assignments
that are given to these ah customers
similarly here theta two one two two sit here
and two three two four two six sit here now
similar to l l d a what we will have from
a ah when a customer chooses a ah dish it
will see what the other customers have chosen
ok that's where they will be coupling that
the words will be assigned similar sort of
topics across the different restaurants
so so you are seeing each restaurant is modeled
by a rectangle each customer are seated at
the tables and each each table you are serving
a dish from a glob global menu so this is
a table indicator ok so by modeling this now
you will know that what are the assignments
of your different words to different topics
in all these documents ok in interesting thing
is that you do not did not have to tell how
many topics do you need a priori what is the
model can itself learn from the observation
so so what we have seen we have seemed ok
so you have an l d a model you can use it
for very nice applications like ah finding
out similarity between documents words but
suppose you want to use some rich assumption
like topics are collated changing over time
so you can modify that model that's why it's
it has a lot of ah then the model is very
very strong it can use ah many different variations
then you say ok ok i this is unsupervised
model but suppose i want to model some responses
with that that is what is the rating of this
text or how many likes i can take it as an
observation variable inside response variable
and learn my topics according that it is sewage
topic model i can go further and say ok which
two documents are connected together that
i can again measure the link as an observation
ah so link can be as a response or observation
link two pair of document documents this was
very relational topic models and then we said
ok suppose we do not want to use any parameters
how many how many topics etcetera then you
go to bayesian non parametrics and they are
again there a lot of different models we talked
about in very briefly about chinese restaurant
process and chinese restaurant franchise but
they are the other variations also that can
be used and depending on your application
we can choose one of the other models and
they are tools available that will allow you
to model any of this
so that brings us to the end of this ninth
week where we discussed a lot about topic
models and also about semantics token semantics
from the next thing we will start talking
about different applications so we will talk
about entity linking information extraction
in the next week and there will go about other
applications in the subsequent weeks so
thank you and see you in the next week