so hello everyone welcome back to the we week
ten of this course so we have been doing a
lot of basics in this course and last week
we finished our discussions on semantics and
during semantics we also talked about various
applications where you can use topic models
and other ah things like distribution semantics
and semantics so starting from this week we
will focus mainly on applications so you will
use both the basics that we have covered and
some new methods for solving very specific
tasks and for this course we have chosen the
task that are very very popular in the field
of n l p and text panel so this week we will
start with ah so we will start the first two
lectures was entity linking and then we will
go towards information extraction
so today we are starting with entity linking
so so what is entity linking as such what
is the problem there so we we were discussing
sometimes in in in the starting and in some
lectures that when we ah encounter text data
lot of entities are mentioned there and it
would be helpful for a task if you what are
the different entities that are used in this
particular text data now there are various
knowledge basis and resources where you have
a good list of all these entities and some
descriptions of these available so suppose
you can find out from a text what are the
important entities here and if you can link
them to a knowledge base then you can do a
lot of further inferences over these for example
this entity is a person and there in the in
the database you will have ma lot of information
about this and you can make use of all these
information so this as if you are having some
background knowledge about various entities
given a text data when you encounter the entity
you try to link it to the knowledge base and
then you can extract the background knowledge
about it and use that for different task in
this particular data so this is a problem
of entity linking so we can define it in this
manner that entity linking is the task of
identifying all mentions in text of a specific
entity from a database or in ah ontology
so what we are assuming here we have a database
or we can also call it knowledge base ontology
where i know what are the different entities
that i that i need and with that inform with
that entity i will have sa some different
sort of information ah for example in wikipedia
think of all the wikipedia pages you have
you can call you can think of all these wikipedia
pages at the entity pages and you have lot
of information about the entities in each
page
so this is my knowledge base now when you
encounter a text there your problem is find
out if a particular ah n gram or a sequence
of phrases sequence of words together correspond
to an entity in the in the wikipedia and if
so then link it to that wikipedia page and
this is ah the overall i idea of entity linking
problem
so ah lot of different databases can be used
for example researchers have used wikipedia
lot then yago freebase etcetera and the task
of entity linking when you are doing you can
break it into two different phases so one
phase would be you find out from the text
what are the appropriate an candidates or
entities that should be ah linked so this
is called the entity ah mention detection
part identify what are the mentions of entities
that should be linked to the database and
once you found out what are the important
entities the next one would be to appropriately
link it to the database that's the second
from second part reference disambiguation
or entity resolution now why would that be
a problem see same as we discussed in the
case of words is disambiguation with the same
entity name there might be different reference
ok so so for example newyork it can be newyork
city and there might be movie with the name
newyork there might be t v serial with the
name newyork so when in a text you have a
mention of newyork you want to know whether
you want to link it to the newyork city or
the film or t v series or something else ok
so there is a problem of ah disambiguation
here and this is also to be handled when we
are solving the problem of entity linking
find out what are the appropriate entities
then appropriately link them to their ah entries
in the database
so what are the things your challenge is that
one needs to handle in this problem so one
is mean variations so the same entity can
be written in many different ways ok so for
example simple things like hilary clinton
so in a in a text you can all you might tried
it with only the name clinton with the last
name clinton ok or maybe there is a middle
name also involved here so you can write it
in different different manners so your problem
is you have to you have to handle all these
name variations and all these should map to
the appropriate entity in the knowledge base
and then the second challenge is entity ambiguity
that is the same string can refer to more
than one entities so this is also we discussed
newyork can refer to multiple entities so
both these challenges are to be handled in
the problem of entity linking
so now ah for for this course what we will
do we will take one particular database that
is wikipedia as our ah base database so so
we will always link a text to wikipedia so
this will be our database by default for this
lecture in the next lecture but in general
you can use any other database and you can
accordingly modify your approaches for that
so one particular terminology so if you are
using wikipedia as your knowledge base then
this task of entity linking is called wikification
or wikifying so you are taking a text and
you are trying to wikify that so that means
find out the entities that are important and
then linked them to ah their appropriate wikipedia
pages that's the problem of wikification
so now let us going detail about this problem
what are the different ah processing involved
and what are the different techniques you
can used so here is one example of ah entity
linking or wikification as such so on the
top what you are seen you are seeing a research
article ok from physics domain and you are
having ah so this like an abstract here so
you are having text such as degeneracy is
removed due to a geometric gradient onto a
metasurface and so on so there is a text involved
here now what what is the task you are trying
to wikify that so that means you are trying
to identify what are the encap ah important
entities and what are their ah pages in wikipedia
so if you see on the bottom so you are you
are finding various links so spin optics so
where optics is linked to some some different
page an an example is from a degeneracy so
link so this is linked to degenerate energy
levels that is a page in wikipedia and you
can also find out some specific content about
that page if you just ah take your mouse over
there and that is being done to many different
words here optics control light photon helicity
angular momentum and so on so that means these
words are the appropriate mentions and they
are then linked to their wikipedia pages so
this is the process of wikification
similarly here you are seeing a news article
and so a in the article so with the news you
are seeing various words are ah hyperlinks
so there you can click this word and go to
their appropriate wikipedia page also for
example here in baghdad so it will open the
wikipedia description of the word baghdad
and you might just want to read the summary
or if you want to know more you can click
on this opening wikipedia and go to the wikipedia
page so now so so we can also see why this
might be very important application so so
you can you can talk about reading news articles
or scientific articles also any other text
it can be tweet text so when you reading the
article there might be many different terms
that are very very specific domain and if
you are not in expert in the domain you will
not know what these terms stand for
so then what you would do you will take this
terms and try to search in the dictionary
or some on google or some or may be on wikipedia
and that will require a lot of time from your
side to fully understand that article so what
is wikification doing so it is helping you
in that given a text it will automatically
identify what are the important entities and
it will link the wikipedia ah pages so it
will avoid it will do all the tasks for you
and you can even see the description in the
same page or you can go to the wikipedia page
and read more about it so that helps a lot
in doing ah in in enhancing your reading for
a certain ah news article or scientific article
additionally it can also help if you are pla
planning two certain task on that text ok
you fo your own to get some semantics from
the text then also having this knowledge that
this entity corresponds to this wikipedia
entity might ah help you in getting some knowledge
from the wikipedia page and take it as a feature
for your task so this is also one other application
for this wikification
so we have seen for scientific articles and
news articles you can also do it for very
short text like tweets so tweets have very
little context so here you are seeing with
four different tweets go gators and here the
problem is what does this gator refer to so
in wikipedia there are two different mentions
that are possible florida gators football
of florida gators mens basketball in this
particular context it refers to florida gators
mens basketball and you want to link it to
that particular entity similarly here a stay
up hawk fans we are going through a slump
now but we have to stay positive go hawks
so here you have entities like fans slump
and hawks and they need to be linked to appropriate
entities again you are seeing their multiple
possibilities and you need to find out what
is the appropriate mention wikipedia same
with the other examples that you are seeing
here so you can do it for also for short text
like tweets with tweets there is a very little
information and you want to find out what
is the appropriate entity that this tweet
links to so and you can also think of many
other application on your own where this entity
linking is important
so now how is actually done so for that let
us try to understand what are the different
phrases again what do we need to ah do systematically
so what are the common steps so first step
is it will determine what are the linkable
phrases and this step is also called mention
detection that is from the text find out what
phrases what n grams are to be linked for
example we were seen words like baghdad and
here gators what the what the mentions that
word to be linked to the ah knowledge base
and this is this is this approach for detecting
these words is called mention detection now
once we have found out what are the appropriate
mentions for to be linked then what will be
the next step next step would be you have
to identify what are the possible candidates
to which it can be linked ah right like in
the previous slide we were seen gators can
link can link to two different ah entries
so identify what are the possible entries
and this will call this is called the link
generation part so you have to select what
are the candidate entity links and what are
the ah all the links you have to list somehow
this is called link generation part
now once you know what are all the links then
what will be the next step you have to find
out what is the most appropriate link for
all the all these set and this will call the
ah disambiguation part so this is use the
context to disambiguate what is the appropriate
link it this entity should be link to and
you might also want to filter you might want
to improve your whole task and we will see
some examples for all these how do you filter
and improve your task based on this
so these are three main steps sometimes you
might combine the first two steps also that
is when you are detecting the wan mentions
you also finding the candidates at the same
time so that is also possible
so now so let us let us see these steps again
in the context of wikification so so you are
having a text where you have this sentence
degeneracy is removed ok and there are some
words before and after so what is mention
detection find out that the word degeneracy
is to be linked is the appropriate mention
so that's in green in this slide so that is
a mention detection part then second part
would be link generation find out all the
appropriate all the possible phrases pages
in the wiki ah in my database so here you
can see the degeneracy ah occurs in mathematics
in biology in graph theory and degenerate
energy levels so there are four possible links
so then you have a task of disambiguation
that among the four links what should be the
appropriate ah ah page wa to which this entity
should be linked and that will be the third
step and that is the disambiguation and you
will say ok this is the fourth one degenerate
energy levels is the appropriate ah entity
page for my for my mention of degeneracy and
these are three steps for this entity linking
now so we might ah like to understand what
are the some of the vasi basic features of
wikipedia that can help us in designing an
algorithm for wikification so wikipedia all
of you know about wikipedia and you have been
reading wikipedia for many of your ah for
for knowing different concepts and all so
so what do you seen wikipedia there is a page
like that there is a title and certain texts
about the page and you see there are various
links also so there is an article then additionally
they can be some redirect pages so you might
have come across you are searching for something
in wikipedia and it it redirects you to some
other page in wikipedia so these are also
ill ah lot of redirect pages in wikipedia
then there are disambiguation pages we will
see an example in the next slide then there
are category template pages that allocate
what are the different categories in wikipedia
this category what are the subcategories and
then there are some admin pages now what is
important for our task is that there are lot
of hyperlinks in wikipedia ok so what hyperlinks
in wikipedia so different words and phrases
are linked within the wikipedia itself so
we will see that in wikipedia article certain
concepts have a hyperlink and you click on
the hyper hyperlink and you will go to the
corresponding wikipedia page so there are
lot of in links and out links that are going
on within wikipedia
so ah so united states for example whenever
you have a ah phrase like united states you
may have a link saying it is linking to the
united states t v serial or american t v show
etcetera so you will find if you will see
the source this will be like that of the hyperlink
so you will have a ah double parenthesis to
denote what is the appropriate entity inside
the source and that if you see the source
wise you can find out and these are various
hyperlinks that you have in wikipedia then
you have a lot of disambiguation pages for
some entities where a lot of different mentions
are available you might have also categories
in disambiguation that in the in the category
of entertainment what are the possibilities
in the in the category of politics what are
the possibilities and so on
so like here the you have for the entity newyork
disambiguation page so you will have h places
what are the possibilities then media entertain
entertainment and you will see that in each
category there are lot of entities that correspond
to this ah the main entity newyork so you
will see in in these cases is the same single
entity can map to may be fifteen twenty different
pages in wikipedia and they are nicely categorized
in this disambiguation page categories may
or may not be there in various pages so so
what are so what so what do we need to about
the whole architecture lot of pages in wikipedia
and each page has some hm name that will be
the identify you may be the identifier then
lot of text involved in the text you have
various hyperlinks where different phrases
are linked to their own wikipedia pages and
some entities will have their own disambiguation
page where you will find out what are the
different ah ways in which this entity can
be used this maybe also under various categories
so now so once you know about that so let's
say some small statistics so that is we talked
about word net for sense disambiguation sa
we given a sentence we want to find out each
word what is the appropriate sense in wordnet
it corresponds to so in wordnet how many entities
we had we had roughly eighty k eighty thousand
different entity definitions and one hundred
forty two thousand different sen senses on
the other hand wikipedia is much larger repository
so in wikipedia overall there are four million
entity defin definitions and this keeps on
increasing and there are twenty four million
different senses so is much much larger in
in compassion to ah wordnet so our task is
from all these twenty four million senses
find out given a text what are the entities
import that are important and what which of
the sense they they correspond to
so now let us see what are the simple measures
that we can think of for the three steps or
let us say only the two steps the mention
detection and disambiguation mention detection
that is in a text whether a given n gram is
in appropriate mention or not so so what we
will do initially we will see some sort of
measures that can be taken simply by the wikipedia
structure or wikipedia data so let us see
so let's talk about this mention detection
part whether a particular phrase is a good
candidate for a mention so so what will be
a good measure for this so so if you think
about using wikipedia structures we can say
that ok wikipedia has lot of pages suppose
i find out this particular n gram how many
times it occurs in wikipedia and among whatever
times it occurs what fraction of times it
is actually linked to something
ok so so what is the idea if an if a word
is linked much more number of times that means
it might be a good candidate for mention if
it is not linked many times that means this
may not be a very good candidate and this
a very simple criteria that you can used from
wikipedia so in this is called the keyphraseness
of a word or also a phrase so number of wikipedia
articles that use it as an anchor divided
by the number of articles that mention it
at all so that means i will take a word w
and i will find out what are all the wikipedia
pages where it occurs ok so it occurs suppose
in five [pedia/wikipedia] articles article
one article two article three four and five
and among the five articles say four and two
provide a link with this w so where w occurs
with the link to some wikipedia page and a
four also this w occurs with the link to a
wikipedia page but a one a three a five do
not provide a link so here w occurs without
a link
ok so now so what is this keyphraseness so
keyphraseness is what fraction of the page
in wikipedia is it linked wherever it occurs
so five linked to so keyphraseness will be
two by five ok and that is a good measure
in that it will tell me ok whenever encounter
a new phrase w how many times it is actually
linked in wikipedia and use that to detect
if it is a good mention at all so this is
a very simple measure so we will say ah how
many times it occurs and among whatever time
it occurs how many times it is linked to another
wikipedia article now here we do not worry
about whether it is linked always to the same
wikipedia article or multiple wikipedia articles
the only thing is it is linked to something
then we will considerate in the numerator
so this is the keyphraseness for a for a word
now what can be a good measure for disambiguation
so now let's again think about it can we use
wikipedia to to find out a good measure for
disambiguation so so what can be the simplest
measure that you can think of so i have a
word and it can correspond to multiple entities
ah so for example so let's say ah i have a
word w and in general it can link to three
wikipedia pages a one a two a three all are
possible reference for this wikipedia page
now what can be a good baseline to find out
what is an appropriate ah disambiguation page
so for that i can again use wikipedia so i
will see in the whole wikipedia whenever w
is link to something so link to these a one
a two a three what fraction of times it is
link to a a one suppose it link to a one ninety
percent of the time a two eight percent of
the time and a three two percent of the time
and this can be an a good measure to say ok
ninety percent of times w links to the article
a one so this so by default i will say ok
w will link to a one so that can be one simple
measure and this is ah called the commonness
so this is commonness so i will define the
commonness for a word and a concept concept
here are three concept three wikipedia concepts
and what is the definition so the fraction
of times a particular sense is used as a destination
in wikipedia so number of times word is link
to c divided by number of times word is link
to any c prime
ok so like here it will be ninety divided
by hundred suppose they are ninety eight and
two pages so ninety divided by hundred is
the ah commonness for w and a one eight by
hundred is commonness for w a two and two
by hundred is commonness for w and a three
so this is another simple measure
so so you have you have seen keyphraseness
and commonness ok and they are simple measures
it is direct from wikipedia so now let us
see one example so here is one text that is
like a report of a match and what you are
seeing you are seeing words the they are coloured
and colours depend on the kre keyphrasenesses
score that is from zero to one so dark green
is keyphraseness one that means it is always
linked in wikipedia so here like bulgaria
national football team is roughly always linked
to wikipedia is has a high keyphraseness some
words like here the knock out are not always
linked they have a very low keyphraseness
now what about the commonness so now you will
take a particular entity like here germany
and you will see what are the all candidate
candidates like germany germany national football
team nazi germany german empire similarly
for world cup it can be fifa world cup f i
s alpine ski world cup two thousand nine fina
swimming world cup world cup mens golf etcetera
these are a various can candidates and you
are computing com commonness by seeing how
many times this word is actually linked to
these ah these entities divided by any number
of time divided by the number of times it
is actually linked and this gives you the
commonness
so germany is linked to the germany the word
germany like ninety four percent of a time
germany national football team one point three
nine percent of the time and so on similarly
for fifa world world cup so now from there
you can choose by default the word the sense
with the highest commonness so like nineteen
ninety eight fifa world cup will come up here
fifa world cup will come up here but they
will a problem with this entity right the
germany will written the word germany ninety
four percent time but in this case the appropriate
mention is germany national football team
and it will not be able to detect this
so so this is the idea about keyphraseness
and commonness and clearly you can see if
there is a one there is one problem with this
approach ok so now so is it always the best
decision to use either the only the commonness
for linking their particular entity and ah
so what do you say so from whatever we saw
in the last page is it always the best deci
decision to use commonness ah it cannot be
right because what you are seeing whenever
a word w occurs in any context ok i will always
assign it to a one by default because it has
the highest commonness so that means i have
never using the context in which the word
w occurs by default i am assigning it to the
category or link a one so that means i will
always make some mistakes right there will
be some pages at least weight should link
to a two or a three and in those cases i will
link it to a one by default so i cannot design
a very good system by this approach i will
there is a like there is always the chance
of maching making mistakes because you are
taking the the the default case and this also
corresponds to the ah to the to one of the
baseline that you can use in words sense disambiguation
that is you take sense of a word that is most
ah probable sense that is like a baseline
but this will never help you in designing
a very good system because you are doing it
independent of the context you are always
linking it to this page
so now what we will see in the next lecture
is that can we also use the context to improve
this method instead of using commonness can
we use something from the context to find
out ok among the three what should be the
appropriate ah link for this particular entity
so so what did we see so commonness and keyphraseness
are simple measures they can help you to design
a good baseline that will work ah most of
the times but cannot help you build in accurate
system because you will always give some wrong
links and we can see why because there is
a default to the most probable link ok and
whenever the word is used in in not so probable
links it can never be correctly assigned so
we need to use the context and that's what
we will see in the next lecture that how do
we use the context from the word to disambiguate
the links
thank you