welcome back for the second lecture of this
week so we have started talking about entity
linking and we we talked about two different
approach so one approach where we use the
keyphraseness in commonness to find out what
are the appropriate mentions and how do you
link to them their ah corresponding reference
in the ah in the knowledge base and we were
considering wikipedia as our knowledge base
and we found out one particular problem with
using simple keyphraseness and commonness
so so what is the problem so so in in commonness
what we were doing we were always taking the
page that is having the highest ah commonness
so what will happen suppose i have word like
tree and the commonness and commonness to
the sense tree is ninety two point eight two
percent but the other concepts because they
occur rarely commonness is like two point
nine four percent two point five seven percent
and so on so what you are seeing wherever
the word tree occurs you will by default assign
it to the first sense of tree and you will
not look at the context at all
so in this case so you have it article about
depth first search and you have a sentence
where the word tree occurs and because of
using commonness you will always assign it
to the sense tree but the correct sense says
here is tree data structure but he it has
a very small commonness so only two point
five seven percent so what you need to do
for ah assigning it to the correct ah data
structure correct sense there is a tree data
structure for that you need to you you should
be able to use the context here that is what
are the referent words that i am seeing in
the context
now question is how best we can use the context
now i do not want to use some random words
in the context ok i want to use the words
in the context that are actually assign that
have actual correspondence to a wikipedia
page so that i can find out something about
the wikipedia page how common this wikipedia
page is to one of it's reference now there
we we fall into the same problem that how
do i use a wikipedia reference to any of it's
page when the disambiguation is not yet happened
so i am only at the ta at the stage of ah
disambiguation
so how do i use the actual entities entity
page and for that if a nice tree can be used
and idea is ok so with this word there are
many other words that are that are coming
in this article or is is if this piece of
text and some of these will be appropriate
mentions and they will into one or many ah
wikipedia pages now some of out of these at
least some will be there that have a unique
disambiguation page in wikipedia so there
is a unique page in wikipedia where they link
to and there i do not need to do any disambiguation
so why don't i use only those pages which
have a ah unique place in wikipedia to find
out what should be a good of a wikipedia page
for this entry tree so that's what is done
so so this is the hypothesis that if you have
a sufficiently long text you can find out
terms that do not require disambiguation at
all there will be some terms that have only
one mention or one referent in wikipedia now
use this unable un unambiguous link in the
document that context to disambiguate the
ambiguous ones so what is the idea here so
you are given this article and you want to
find out what is the appropriate ah sense
for this wordage
so in a sense i mean what is the appropriate
link in wikipedia is it tree tree graph theory
data structures set theory etcetera so what
i will do i will see what are the other mentions
in this page so what are the other things
you have seen algorithm tree structure graph
backtracking uninformed search tree backtracks
lifo stack and so on now among these there
will be some that have only one wikipedia
page as the referent so these are ah shown
as box search
so algorithm tree structure uninformed search
and lifo stack have only one wikipedia page
so i will take these unambiguous links and
try to find out how close these foldings are
to my all of these possible senses ok so how
close are these folding to this possible sense
and the one sense that is having the the is
the closest to these four will be called by
sense there should be the link to will to
which i will link my corresponding ah mention
so how do we compute the relatedness score
and this can be very simple so so you you
can initially start by ripping representing
each candidate sense and context term by a
single wikipedia article ok so for example
what is happening now so a word like tree
and tree corresponds to many different senses
and call them your article article one article
two article three article four ok and if you
remember your word sense disambiguation it's
like constructing various ah sense backs there
are four different senses they are like science
science x now you are having a context back
kind of context track where you are saying
ok in this context of tree i am finding four
different words word one word two word three
word four now what is the property of each
words they link to one page in wikipedia
ok so like a w one a w two a w three a w four
so now these are wikipedia articles and they
are also wikipedia articles now now the problem
is select the sense article that is the that
is most in common with all of the context
articles so that is among the four articles
which is most common with all these four articles
ok and you will see what is the art max that
is having the more similarity with these four
articles and this can be captured in many
different ways so we will talk about one particular
method so and one go to the method is you
just take the wikipedia link based method
that is two pages are similar if they are
having many incoming and outgoing lon links
common
ok so what is the idea so how do you find
out how similar a one is to a w one so i will
say ok i have two articles a one a w one and
wikipedia i find out what are the incoming
links to this article and what are the outgoing
links from here same i will do for this article
and now once i have found this out i can see
ok what are the common links so how many articles
in wikipedia article w a prime are linking
to both of these similarly what are the articles
to which both of these link to and these are
very good measures for finding out how similar
they are you see we can always do it by seeing
how similar they are by measuring their text
similarity
how much text similarities is there you can
capture cosine similarity and what or something
else but this is a nice link based measure
that says ok how many pages linked to both
of these so what are the common in links and
how many pages they both linked to that is
a common out links and this is again a nice
measure in that it says ok this article refers
to both of these that means they they need
to have something common similar they both
mentioned the same article again that means
they they need to have something in common
and you will find out how many what fraction
of incoming links are common
what fraction of for being links are common
and that you will take it as a measure for
computing how similar these two articles are
and this is also called by relatedness
ok so we talked about keyphraseness commonness
and this is relatedness and then you can find
out the relatedness of a candidate size sense
by taking a weighted average of it's relatedness
with all of the context articles so that is
to find out the relatedness of this sense
a one you will say ok it's relatedness with
a w one will a w two a w three a w four ok
by using this measure then you take a average
or a weighted average compute a weighted average
and this will be ok what is the relatedness
of this sat sense a one a two a three a four
whichever as the highest you take that ok
like if you see the previous slide so here
you were capturing showing relatedness of
various senses and this tree data structure
had the highest relatedness sixty three point
two six percent that uses the average of relatedness
with all these the four different context
articles now so there is one term here we
are taking a weighted average now what should
this weight depend on why should i weight
one of this higher than the other ones
so again if you think about it it can it can
depend on which context term is more important
than other another ok so what we have done
we have taken the context we have found out
to all the words that are that are mentions
and from there whichever are so these were
ah unambiguous whichever were an unambiguous
we are taking them as my context to find out
the relatedness but some of these might be
more important for this topic or the document
than others so so can i give a weight depending
on how important they are to the topic
now the question again comes how do i know
which one are more important to the topic
or the theme of this document and then you
see you can again use the idea of relatedness
ok that means one among these four context
art ah senses articles the one that is having
the highest relatedness with the others which
more which more appropriate to the theme of
the theme of the document yes because there
is a theme of the document and the words that
are appropriate should also be connected to
each other that means a word that is having
a high relatedness with other words is it
should be given a high values ok and that
is a nice method to also give a weight here
weight to different of these relatedness that
is how related these this context article
is to the other context articles
so in general there are so what are the things
that are used to give a weight to the context
term so one is called link probability so
what is link probability ah so so again in
your context you are finding say four or five
articles where the link is unambiguous there
is only one link now you can use the link
probability itself that is among the four
which one is like a keyword that is it always
links to something some words may not link
may not alwa always link some words always
link so the words it always link should be
given a high weightage because i know there
this is a more a specific term if a word is
somewhat sometimes links sometimes not linked
it may not be a very important keyword so
that can be one measure
what is the link probability probability that
it will be given a link in general wikipedia
that is same as my key phraseness measure
and certain thing we have already discussed
that is relatedness so find out how closely
it relates to the central document by computing
it's average relatedness to all other context
terms ok so i take for each word what is the
link probability or keyphraseness and relatedness
now i have two different majors so how do
i take these together to compute the rela
the weight of this word you can simply ah
take an average to provide the weight for
each context ok so is that clear now so you
have some words in the context they are ambiguous
sorry unambiguous for each word for each context
word you find out the relatedness of this
ah mention in your mention sense one of the
sense taken weighted average and this weight
depends on what is the link probability and
what is the relatedness with all the context
terms and and by doing doing this method you
can find out ah relatedness of each of the
four senses
now now the so so we have discussed ok we
can take some mentions by some method and
then once with the mentions we can also give
a link by ah finding out which of the candidates
are similar in in from with the context ah
mentions but here there is an interesting
question that by using all this when when
we are doing all this approach can i go back
and also improve my mention detection part
so how i was detecting the mentions so i was
gathering all the n grams in the document
and retaining only those whose probability
exceeds a very low threshold so that is i
start with a text document there i take various
n grams it can be ok i i take certain pattern
they are noun groups or something like there
is some patterns ah n grams i can say one
two three whatever and i take some n grams
ok and then see what is the keyphraseness
of each of these and whichever as ah if this
is above a threshold when i take it as a mention
and then i then it's a mention and then i
go to my link disambiguation part but see
what are you seeing that when i am finding
out the appropriate entities as mentions i
am not using the context at all i am just
seeing is it a good word for ah is it a good
key phrase or not does it have a good keyphraseness
or not overall so independent of a context
is it a good mention or not
so question is can i also use the context
to find out what are good mention and what
are not so good mentions and that's what we
will see so it is the best method so all the
remaining phrases are disambiguated using
the approach mentioned earlier yes so we have
whatever ah mentions we have found or whatever
phrases we have found we do disambiguation
using an approach that we have
so now by doing this approach you get to find
a lot of different things like what are the
links what are the appropriate ah mentions
here what are the wikipedia pages they link
to ok so you are getting some new wikipedia
pages also so now can you use this additional
information to find out are they good ah candidates
for mention at all so so that is can you use
that to find out which concepts should be
linked so here is one example ok so you are
having a ah a wikipedia page ah at so it's
like a news article so democrats deal is clinton
setback and you are having lot of ah so ah
various sentences are here now what is your
approach in your approach you you take a various
mentions like hilary clinton occurs at various
locations and try to find out what is the
entity in wikipedia it will link to similarly
here barack obama nomination vote michigan
all these are link to their various wikipedia
entities
so you get all this by your ah link disambiguation
phrase now my question is can i use that together
to find out what are good mentions also for
my text and for that we have to convert that
to some sort of a learning problem learning
problem where i run my algorithm on a on a
data and see what are the good ma ga what
are the mentions i am detecting what are the
links i am connecting to now once i have all
this information someone gives me gold standard
that what are the good links here what are
not the book links using that can i learn
what are my what are the good candidates to
be mentioned what are the good what are not
so good candidates to be mention so like coming
back to my example so i start with the text
data and i find out ok there are some mentions
they have driver key phrase above a threshold
ok
now i also link them to their wikipedia articles
some of these might be linked to the same
article ok so that i do for this whole document
now suppose someone tells me that actually
this is a good mention this is a good mention
this is a good mention but this is not so
good mention ok this is good mention this
is not so good mention so once i have all
this information can i develop a machine learning
method to detect ok given an article given
in mention and it's approved wikipedia page
all the context is it a good ah mention at
all so given a phrase with all these attributes
is it a good mention for this document or
not
so now so you can say that once you given
me the text all the all the steps that i have
taken are deterministic so i can apply ah
keyphraseness i can find out the mentions
i can link them to their wikipedia pages so
all this i can easily do but how would i get
these gold standards that doesn't inappropriate
ah mention this is not inappropriate mention
and this is one of the bat bottlenecks so
how do i get this ah actual links and not
so not good links and good mentions and not
so good mentions
for that so now what is interesting idea here
can you use wikipedia again so can use wikipedia
again so how would you use wikipedia for this
so if you think think a bit so how you can
use wikipedia and that's actually very very
easy so you take wikipedia and take some wikipedia
articles say a one a two a three a four a
five so on now each of the article now forget
the hyperlink structure here so take it as
a plain text and feed it to your algorithm
so algorithm takes a one as input plain text
and runs this ok so your algorithm will run
this it will tell tell you what are the mentions
what do they link to and so on
now because a one is already wikified so it's
already in wikipedia you know what mentions
are good what mentions are not good so from
there you can automatically construct your
gold standard ok and once you have the gold
standard you can apply a machine learning
method to say ok which given a feature around
this fridge is it a good mention in this context
or not and that will solve your problem so
this is like you are learning to ah link using
wikipedia so using the wikipedia data and
ah so very nicely you are taking it as a training
data and also constructing your gold standard
from this without having some manual efforts
of labeling because otherwise you will see
this labeling will take a huge amount of time
and this will help you do that automatically
so so what will i do so now once i have taken
the wikipedia as in as input i know ok whichever
phrases gave me a wikipedia article that was
actually there in the original article they
are possible examples and whatever was not
there becomes a negative example and so yeah
so you got the possible negative examples
and you feed it to your classifier and then
you use various features around these various
mentions and articles to detect whether it's
a good mention or not so you use various features
like like the places where they are mentioned
to inform the classifier ab about which topic
should and should not be linked
so now so now what are what can be these possible
features that you can use from a given n gram
phrase so so let's see some features some
of some of these features are what you have
already seen and some other features can depend
on how do people actually write ah a wikipedia
article so what are the good features so one
feature that we can use is link probability
ok so so that is for a given mention what
is the link probability now if it is occurring
at multiple places ok like hilary clinton
clinton so they are occurring at different
different ah variations
so what are they li their link probabilities
at each of these places take either the average
or the maximum of this link probability and
that can be one feature ok so this you are
doing jointly so hilary clinton and clinton
together should they will linked or not and
here you are trying to use ok what is a link
probability it at different places taking
average or also taking maximum both can be
a features then you can use the relatedness
so how related these ah phrases are to the
central theme of the document
so again you will find out what is the relatedness
of these mentions with different ah unambiguous
links in the entire article so this can be
another feature if they are very highly related
then only you will take them as your mentions
if they are not related to the entire theme
of the document that means they are not probably
not good ah candidates for mentions then you
can also use the disambiguation confidence
that is when you are trying to do a disambiguation
over this ah mention
how confident your classifiers if your classify
is not very confident that means you do not
have sufficient context in those document
and it may not be a good mention at all so
this confidence can also be one of the features
then you can use the generality that is when
you are trying to link some ah phrases in
in your text what is the idea you do not want
to link something that is very very generic
that all people already know about so you
want to link the phrases that are very specific
so how can you know about the jan is ah how
generic or specific a particular phrases further
you can use the the the category to your wikipedia
and there you can see at what what depth in
the tree this particular ah mention comes
in so if it comes at a very ah it's very top
label itself that means it is a ah it is a
very generic term but this coming very low
in the tree that means say a specific term
so specifi specific terms might be given a
high preference so this can also be ah like
your feature what is the depth in the wikipedia
hierarchy tree and then you can also see how
the documents are written that is where all
this entities mentioned so for example if
it is a good entity it will be mentioned in
the introduction similarly it will be mentioned
in the con conclusion of section of the of
article so if it is mentioned in the initial
full lines or the last few lines it might
be important
so you can simply measure the offset ah from
the beginning end and the end then you can
also see the spread that is what is the distance
between then you shall mention in the last
mention so that is how far does the response
across the document if the spread is high
that means ok it might be a good mention if
the spread is low that means very to only
cover very small topic of this document this
has been used
so this can again be a feature for this task
and you can think of many of other features
combine these features in your classifier
and then you are learning whether given this
phrase with all these features is it a good
ah ah candidate for mention or not and this
is like you are learning you are learning
to link using the wikipedia structure so as
such you you take many different methods but
this is the basic conceptual idea about entity
linking that how do you detect mentions different
methods
how once you detect mentions how do you link
them to their ah appropriate entries in the
wiki in the wikipedia or any other database
and can you use this task to also improve
your mentions ok and you can take it in different
different applications take different databases
and you can try out various variations for
this task so this so that's where we finish
our discussions on entity linking so in the
next lecture onwards we will start talking
about information extraction that is from
a from a document where there is a lot of
unstructured data text data how can you identify
various entities and the relations between
them
thank you