so welcome back for the third lecture of this
week so in this week we are doing some advanced
topics on text mining and so tutorial we will
so this lecture we will start with information
extraction so we will see what are the basic
ah so all the basic applications where information
extraction will be used what kind of techniques
you can used and we will focus our attention
to a specific task that is relational extraction
how do i find out relation between any two
entities by using the text corpus on the web
so what do i mean by ah information extraction
so so we can say that the goal of information
extraction is like machine reading so you
have a lot of text available on the web it's
all on the um unstruct unstructured form there
is no particular structure to that now from
that text can i obtain some structured knowledge
that can be used for various different applications
and tasks ok so this is like a ah some sort
of caricature to to to denote that that yes
we have a lot of knowledge available on the
web and machine is trying to go through the
knowledge and get some a structured content
that can be useful
so ah so what the information extraction systems
do they try to find and understand various
different relevant parts of the text data
so so what you will have you will have a lot
of text and you are trying to get a certain
important information from there and so we
will see what are the various ways in which
you can gather this information
so now now from this all this data that is
available what you want you want to get a
structured representation of some sort of
relevant information and it can be like various
relations in the sense of database so you
can find out what are the various entities
involved in this text and what are the relations
between those entities and can also be some
sort of knowledge base that you are constructing
from the data
so ah so the goal of information extraction
is that we organize information so that it
can be useful for two people for ah for doing
some of their tasks and we want to put information
in a very precise form that will allow um
need to make further inferences ok so remember
this was one of the things that we are talking
about in the introduction also that the natural
language text is not very precise so how do
you make how do you convert the information
to something precise that can be used for
doing various task and various inferences
and that's what we we doing in the in the
case of information extraction
so this is a simple definition that you can
get this is a sort of working def definition
you will say so so what is information extraction
so that is task of finding a structured information
from unstructured or semi structured text
so you have the corpus or data that you have
is either completely unstructured ok so i
can think of various treats various cora questions
answers and lot of web pages sort of unstructured
or it can be somewhat semi structured where
you have some more information like extraction
information ah headlines etcetera but this
is not completely structured so from this
unstructured or semi structured data i want
to find out a structure information and that's
what it's the definition of my information
extraction
so so now question comes in that what sort
of information do you want to extract from
here so information can be something very
very ah clear and factual like for example
this is this is ah this is something that
that is normally done so they should like
who did what to whom when and who is in what
relation to some other entity and and so on
so for example suppose you have some newspaper
text and they talk about various ah earnings
profit headquarters etcetera and this is one
one of the company report the headquarters
of b h p be billiton limited and the global
headquarters of the combined b h p billiton
group are located in melbourne australia ok
this is some sort of ah unstructured data
that you can say ah in the form of the sentence
now from this data you want to gather some
structure information so what kind of structured
information do you get from this um text so
you will see that so what are the headquarters
of b h p billiton limited so then you know
the location here melbourne australia and
this can be some sort of a structured information
that you are trying to gather from the simple
sentence and that is what your information
extraction system can do so from here suppose
you get this information headquarters of the
b h p billiton limited are in melbourne australia
since out of relation form there are two entities
and there is a relation between them and this
you are extracting by using information extraction
now what is the so what is the use of doing
this extraction so once you do this extraction
you will know all these tuples so you will
know this two entities are related are related
by this relation and so on and over there
you can do lot of queries you can do lot of
inferences and so on this can be very helpful
for many question task also another example
let us say we have the sentence in nineteen
ninety eight larry page and sergey brin founded
google ok
now from this sentence what kind of information
you can get so who are the founders of google
and when they find when they found found google
so all this information can be extracted from
here and put in a very a structured form so
like i can have a information like founder
of larry page google founder of sergey brin
google and founded in google in nineteen ninety
eight so all this information is there in
this text and this can be extracted by a using
information extraction systems
so now once you have this information it can
be used by various search engines and database
management systems to provide better services
to the end users it is not very trivial to
do it directly by using the text data but
once you have this in the database form you
can you can do a lot of different tasks and
look you can use a lot of different tools
to to make each of this information
so now what are the various applications of
information extraction for example biomedical
domain so in biomedical domain you have a
lot of ah research papers that are published
that give details about what about the various
experiments that were done using and using
various ah patients and what was the findings
of those experiments and what kind of drugs
work what kind of drugs does not work they
can be various clinic clinical clinical trials
they can be various patrons and all that lot
of information is there but this is already
very unstructured form so so suppose i need
to look for discoveries that are related to
various genes proteins or other biomedical
entities so and and then the problem here
could can be that these entities can have
various synonyms and there are lot of ambiguities
involved so what is the task i need to automatically
identify what are the mentions of biomedical
entities in the text i find out ok these are
that entities that has mentioned in the text
and then i want to link them to their corresponding
entries in the lexical database
suppose i have a database that says ok these
are all the all the different biomedical entities
now in a research paper i i need to find out
ok this entity talks about this is corresponding
to the per particular entity in the database
this is very similar to the entity relenting
problem that we discussed in this week itself
now once we find out various entities in in
the document other task here could be that
i want to find out how they are related to
each other so this is called relational extraction
that is one of the focus of ah the next three
lectures
so so this is an example so you have this
ah research paper in biomedical dome domain
and this is research paper you also get some
abstract now from this abstract can you extract
information in a structured format like p
fifty three is a protein bax is a protein
p fifty three has function of apoptosis and
so on now all this information is available
in the text data but not in this very nice
structured format so from from there can you
extract these are the entities and this is
the relation between them
so here so you find what are the entities
and with different ah between various pairs
of entities what is the relation and this
is called the structured knowledge extraction
and this the analogy is shown here so the
research paper extract can be thought of as
a as a if something for humans and this structured
knowledge means can be thought of as something
for machines so machines can make use of this
information for various tasks now
another example so this is like a report that
that you find on the web and from this report
can you extract various relations so here
you have the sentence american airlines the
unit of a m r immediately matched the move
a spokesman tim wagner said so from here you
can find out the tim wagner region is a spokesman
for american airlines and suppose your relation
is employee so we can say tim wagner is employee
of american airlines also american air airlines
is the unit of a m r so you can have this
relation american airlines is a subsidiary
of a m r ok and similarly here united a unit
of u a l you can find out this relation again
so from this huge amount of text data can
you find out this is a structured information
so that is the task of information extraction
find out the entities and what are the relations
between them another example so when the relation
can be were also very very generic so like
you can be personal relations like married
to mother of organization relations like a
spokesmans for president of artifactual owns
something invented something produces something
they can geospatial relations that this city
is near to this city this city in the on the
outskirts of the city and these kind of relations
might be very very helpful in ah replying
to various queries they talk about that need
geography information see you know what cities
are nearby other city so you can try to answer
these kind of questions and directional relation
this is southeast of and so on and they can
be part of relations so you need of something
parent of annexed acquired for this political
relations
so you can think of lot of lots and lots of
different relations that can be established
between entities now using these relations
you can do lot of different ah ah some sort
knowledge engineering you can do a lot of
inferencing you can try to answer questions
and and try to predict certain relations between
the entities there are lot of different tasks
that you can use once do you can do once you
have this structured information
so now so the topic here is how do we gather
this resea[rch]- information ok so there are
like ah i would say like in many different
n l p applications so here also there are
five different methods for doing this task
so one simple method is you choose your hand
built patterns then you get it bootstrapping
methods you know supervised methods distance
supervision is a very very nice idea that
you will see for this particular task and
then you can also use some unsupervised methods
so we will focus on the first four methods
and we will see ah clearly how you can use
one of these methods for the task of information
extraction so let us see what we do in the
hand built patterns so idea is you can use
various regular expressions for finding entities
and the relations between them so suppose
you want to find the entities so here so this
is ah for noun groups it's simple regular
expression so regular expression you can also
ah denote by using a finite automaton so here
you are seeing a finite automaton that is
denoting a regular expression and this so
what it is denoting any noun group
so let us try to follow this so you have this
ah phrase johns interest interesting book
with a nice cover this is a noun group so
how does this automatic capture this you say
a pronoun a personal noun john johns ok interesting
becomes an adjective book is a noun with is
a preposition a article nice adjective cover
noun and this is a it is a final state so
this becomes a noun group
so we will see even john is a noun group and
johns interest interesting book is also a
ah noun group so it is trying to capture nouns
group noun group in various sort of granularity
you can even have single word you can have
multiple words so you it is telling you what
is a noun group now you can further extend
it to find out ok i know what are the noun
groups now what is the relation between that
so suppose i want to find out which person
holds what position in what org organization
so what kind of patterns i can think of a
person x holding position y in organization
z so suppose i have to use some hand built
patterns how will i go about it so i will
first think about what are the various kind
of sentences where ah all these three entities
can can occur together so there will be a
person who is working in an organization so
and then once i have found some sentence is
i will try to abstract what is the normal
pattern that i am seeing here
so for example one pattern can be person comma
position of organization because you find
sentences like vuk draskovic is a person comma
position leader of the serbian renewal movement
ok so now what you are abstracting here there
is a person position and organization and
now you can think of many many many such ah
sentences where all these these three entities
will be there in this relation so once you
identified this pattern you will give this
pattern to the machine and from there corpus
it can ah extract all these entities for you
and you will know immediately that these entities
are connected by a particular relation
what can be other ah patterns so like organization
named appointed etcetera person preposition
office ok again they are all these entities
so nato appointed wesley clark as commander
in chief so we are finding again all the three
ah entities in a particular relation
so similarly suppose your task is to find
out where is an organization located so we
will think about what are the patterns something
like x located in y and or y is xs headquarters
so we will think of these patterns and using
these patterns you will try to extract these
pairs of x y like organization location nato
headquarters in brussels so we will extract
nato headquarters and brussels are the two
entities organization location and you can
say division branch headquarters like k f
o r kosovo headquarters so you know this is
the observation and it's a location
so like that you can think of various patterns
and extract these relations and this is one
of the very early examples on how these kind
of patterns for used for extracting hyponym
relation so hyponym which is you remember
it's a relation between sub concept and a
super concept when these words ah first um
given by hearst
so what is the basic intuition suppose you
are seeing this sentence agar is a substance
prepared from a mixture of red algae such
as gelidium for laboratory or industrial use
this is sentence now suppose i asked what
is gelidium and you can say ok ah gelidium
is some sort of algae or red algae from the
sentence yes now how do you know that gelidium
is a red algae see you are seeing some sort
of pattern here red algae such as gelidium
ok so this pattern is telling you that gelidium
is the kind of red algae
now you can try to abstract these pattern
in you say that whenever you are finding such
patterns x such as y there is a hyponym hyponym
relation between x and y and this is the idea
find out many such patterns and from these
patterns you try to extract these entities
so what has did he found out various search
patterns where you can have two entities connected
by hyponym relation ok
so ah y such as x is for hyponyms so what
are the other kind of patterns you can use
such y as x ok like such vehicle as car such
vehicle as bicycle ok x or other y yes car
or other vehicle car and other vehicle vehicles
including car and and so on ok vehicle especially
car so this i am given example with car and
vehicles but you can think of it as with any
hyponym hyponym pair so he found out freddy
such titles and from these patterns he tried
to extract the hyponym( Refer Time: 19:00)
hyponym relation from the text data
so here are some examples for these hearst
patterns and the what kind of example occurrences
you can see in the data so the pattern x and
other y you can see temples tragedies and
other important civic buildings so from this
sentence you can immediately see that ten
percent treasuries are sub concepts of civic
buildings so we can have this pair of hyp
hyponym hyponym civic build civic buildings
are the hyponym and temples is the hyponym
similarly treasure is the hyponym x or other
y so bruises won't broken bones or other injuries
so we can have all these as a hyponym of injuries
y such as x so the bow lute such as the bambara
ndang
so here you can see that ah bow lute is the
super concept this is the sub concept such
y as x such authors as herrick goldsmith and
shakespeare so immediately you will see there
is a relation here and so on y including x
y especially x
so hearst hearst manually found that all these
patterns and from these patterns he was trying
to extract a hyponym hyponym pair piar from
the data similarly ber berland and charniaks
they found out some patterns for meronym relation
that is part of relation basement is the part
of building so they were trying to find out
ah patterns for for meronyms so again you
can think of what are the patterns that come
to your mind so so like buildings basement
so you will think of some example and see
what kind of sentences they occurring buildings
basement basement of the building and so on
and you will try to make patterns out of these
so so let's take these two simple examples
so like i am seeing that i have an example
basement and building ok and this is my suppose
my x and this is my y and i want to find out
many such x y pairs that have the same meronym
relation so how will i start i say ok in the
sentences how will baseman in building occur
together something like basements building
sorry buildings basement so it will be y's
x buildings basement ok or basement of the
building x of the y and so on ok and these
are now my patterns ok and then you will try
to see in my corpus where do all these patterns
occur so example is cars wheel wheel of the
car so we will see ok these x y are related
by this meronym relation and that's how you
will try to so we are in these patterns we
will try together many such x x prime y prime
pairs ok
so what berland and charniaks did they selected
some initial patterns for finding all sentences
in the corpus that contain basement and building
ok that's a normal ah is a nice method of
finding these patterns so then they found
like buildings basement basement of a building
basement in a building basements of buildings
basements and buildings and so on now here
they were writing down the patterns so here
something like n n so they were writing in
terms of what is the parts of speech that
is coming and and so on so of preposition
so parts the plural noun of preposition wholes
n n it's a plural noun
so this is part in whole relation ok part
coming as n n in between there is the word
in as a preposition the or a as a determiner
and in some modifiers so there are now here
abstracting so what they are seeing ok ah
basement in a building but it might be basement
in a huge building right so how do i absolutely
better than i say ok there is in optionally
they can be in adjective here so that's why
they are saying j j or n n is star basement
in a civic building and so on all these can
be captured by slightly ah generalizing these
con these patterns
so that's what you are seeing here j j or
n n so you can have a civic building huge
building and all this will be captured here
so like that you try to find out these patterns
and using this patterns so once you have these
patterns you try to extract some other entity
pairs that are ah involved in this relation
so now so this is a nice method if you want
to sit down and and look at each and every
relation and and think about the patterns
and that's the that's also the problem with
this approach that some some persons who are
ah good with the data who are also language
they know how how the system work they can
they can they can try to get you some hand
built patterns so now question the problem
is that they are hard to write and hard to
maintain and there are like you can think
of zillions of patterns so we can think of
so many different ways in which people can
talk about hyponym hyponym pair in the in
the data
so how do i capture all of these patterns
manually and yeah there might be domain dependent
so every domain you might have different ways
of writing things and yes you you can do that
for some relations but suppose they are thousands
of relations how do you do for all these thousand
relations and yeah so we and these patterns
that hearst found or berland and charniaks
found they were giving ok kind of results
but they were not like giving very very accurate
results so for example hearst patterns give
the roughly sixty six percent accuracy on
hyponym extraction and berland and charniak
gave fifty five percent accuracy on meronyms
so we would like probably prefer to have better
accuracy than these numbers so so so that
is using hand built patterns you can only
go little so only small distance and there
there are also a lot of manual effort is required
so how can we avoid this manual effort and
that's what we will see in the other approaches
that we will be discussed it starting from
how do we do simple bootstrapping here ok
and that's all you will be discussing in the
next lecture
thank you