welcome back for the fourth lecture of this
week so we started talking about information
extraction and there we discussed about the
particular problem of relation extraction
and we discussed some ah so one approach that
is using hand built patterns so we can build
some patterns manually and we saw that by
using that we can extract certain relations
between entities and there there was some
limitations with that so we will now see some
other approaches apart from hand built patterns
so so you starting with a bootstrapping approaches
so we we had talked about bootstrapping approaches
in one of the earlier topic that is one word
sense disambiguation but let us see how do
we apply these approaches for the task of
relation extraction
so here so so you will use these approaches
only if you do not have a lot of annotated
data because if you have some annotations
already available then you can use some supervisor
approaches that might give you better else
but suppose you do not have annotated data
that means data where it is labeled entity
one is related to entity two by a particular
relation r if you do not have such data you
will use your bootstrapping approach
so so you do not have enough data but what
you have r some seed instances of the relation
and that is very easy now what they mean by
seed instances so remember ah we were talking
about hyponyms or meronyms see all you know
some seed relation so you know ok basement
and buildings are connected by the meronym
relation car and vehicles are connected by
the hyponym hyponym hyponym hyponym relation
so you know some seed instances ok then what
else do you need or you might have some patterns
that you know and lots and lots of unannotated
data so that means you should have a lot of
corpus where you have a lot of text data it
may be an an unannotated its a simple text
data so so idea is using some seed patterns
running running some idea over this whole
data you can try to bootstrap your your approach
for relation extraction
so ah so the questions here are so suppose
so here you have some seed instances so how
do you use them for doing something meaningful
or so that you can extract where is other
entities so you have some seed ah instances
how do you use that for extracting more more
such examples and so this can be consider
some sort of a semi supervised approach so
what do we do here so let us take some simple
example so ah here suppose i have my relation
is burial place so x is buried in place y
i want to find out all such entities that
are connected by this relation
so how do i go about it firstly i need to
see if i have some ah seed instances that
is some entities that are connected by this
relation suppose i have an instance that is
mark twain is and the burial place is elmira
new york so i have this seed tuple now how
do i start so remember what did we need we
need some seed instances and a lot of corpus
data
so now you can use the intuition that how
are you finding out ah the patterns in the
in the case of hand built patterns so again
we were starting with some hand with some
ah seed instance so like basement building
and we were trying to go to the corpus and
seeing wherever these two words occur what
is the ah what is the ah pattern in which
they occurring same thing you can do here
so you know ok i have two entities elmira
and mark twain now you can search your whole
corpus to find out where all all these two
entities occurred together any single sentence
or in some proximity
now wherever they occur you try to find out
in what pattern do they connect to each other
and these patterns you can generalize as your
gen generic patterns without having to manually
go through each of these so something like
so i have these and it is mark twain elmira
and maybe i can google this google this google
this entities mark twain elmira together and
let us see what do i what are the kind of
sentences do i get and suppose i get a sentences
like this excuse me mark twain is buried in
elmira new york this is the sentence and i
know what am i entities here mark twain is
x elmira is y so i can immediately from a
pattern x is buried in y in this becomes my
pattern
the next sentence the grave of mark twain
is in elmira so i can have this pattern the
grave of x is in y similarly elmira is mark
twins final resting place so i have this pattern
now y is x s final resting place and so on
so we are getting this sentence is from the
sentence you are extracting over you are entities
x and y and you are building patterns in terms
of x and y so what you saw here just by using
one seed instance and a lot of unannotated
data you can find out some patterns
now once you have patterns what you will do
you will you will use these patterns to find
out more and more such entity pairs that are
connected by this pattern and that will enhance
your seed seed tuples or seed instances then
you can again use this seed instances to again
such the corpus find out more such patterns
and this can be done in an iterative manner
until there is some convergence going on or
you are seeing that there is not helping much
so so now you have these patterns and you
use these to search for new tuples so describe
described by the simple flow chart that is
you are starting with this some sort of seed
tuples like mark twain elmira then you are
searching with tuples in the in the corpus
and you are finding various patterns and this
becomes your pattern set you might also have
some seed patterns already but you are getting
some patterns now now using this patterns
you are searching the corpus and finding more
tuples and i putting them in your relational
table and that is going to your tuple set
now using your tuple set you can search these
and find out more patterns and this can keep
on going in many many iterations and this
is in a very nice approach you can see that
you only need data that is ah freely available
everywhere and you need some very few seed
instances and you can apply this algorithm
and this does not require to do everything
manually
so yes but there are some problems with the
that approach the problems for example are
that the seed instance with which we start
should be a good instance such that there
are many occurrences of this seed in the corpus
if the seed ah pair does not arrange the corpus
you will not be able to extract many relations
many patterns from this so this is one problem
with this approach so this is sensitive to
the original set of seeds that you use for
your algorithm and in general there can be
many parameters to be tuned for example how
many top patterns will i take from from my
set how many iterations i will go through
and how many times i will send the same pattern
for my first search there can be many a many
parameters that you have to fix and yeah there
is no such probabilistic interpretation so
its difficult to know how confident you are
in each pattern or each tuple that you are
finding by this approach
so here some sort of problems with this approach
but it is a nice approach if you use to want
to ah to get get it done without ah without
building some sort of machine learning method
also so on you can use this approach very
ah for some simple ah and easy results but
we will see if you want to build a more over
system that what kind of approaches you can
you can use
so so for that we can talk about some supervised
approaches for relation extraction so what
is the idea so first you will ah define what
are the kind of relations you want to extract
so relations can be many like ok i want extract
ah family relations so parent of ah wife of
husband of and so on you can you can extract
some ah ah organization relation this is an
employee of and and subsidiary of and so on
so we will define a set of relations
now for each relation you will find data and
label the data so they should be some manual
labeling involved somebody has to label the
data that ok in this sentence these entities
are connected by this relation so you will
choose a representative corpus where you think
that there can be some instances of this relation
now you will label the named entities in the
corpus and hand label the relations between
the entities
so what will happen you have a corpus you
will find out sentence s one s two s three
s four and you say in the sentence this entity
one this entity two and you know what is the
relation between them similarly here you find
ok there is one entity one prime entity two
prime and there is some relation prime here
and this has to be hand labeled why do you
need hand labeling so once you have these
hand labels they are like your ah so this
is like your bold standard that you can you
as your training as well as testing data
so we will train train you are system using
ok in in this sentence if these are the entities
there is a relation between them so in a new
sentence suppose two entities are there is
there is the relation rel between them so
this can be some machine learning model that
you can built by using this gold standard
and then you will ah yeah break into training
development in text that is the usual practice
in machine learning and then you will train
a classifier on the training set
so now so so here it might be one problem
while you are using this approach in general
they can be hundreds of relations and so you
need to ah so so when in ah you are given
a sentence between two entities take they
can be many relations but they may not be
any relation at all it might happen that two
entities are occurring in a sentence but they
are not connected by any relation there is
no relation as such
so what you might do is to have the first
step that says ok in a sentence i know what
are all the entities and this first step tells
me which two entities are connected and which
two are not connected and once you have the
output of this step you know these two entities
are connected then you run your additional
classifier to find out what is the relation
between them among all the hundreds of relations
that you have
so this issue this is seemed to be working
in this in this area of relation extraction
that first you find out what entities are
connected second what is relation between
them so its a two stage approach so so you
find all pairs of named entities in a sentence
and the extra a step can be build a simple
binary classifier so that is says yes or no
and it decides whether two entities are related
or not and if you find an answer yes to this
is step use another classifier to find out
what is the relation between these two entities
and why will that help because in the first
step build itself you will be able to eliminate
a lot of extra pairs that are not involved
in any relation so we will not bother about
those you will only bother about those entities
that are probably connected by some relation
other advantage could be you can think of
the idea sort of features that you will used
for the first step that is finding out if
there is a relation or not and the second
step that is if this relation what is that
relation you can think of very set of features
that you can imply both for both of these
ah steps
so here is ah one visualization of what this
will look like so suppose you have this sentence
american airlines a unit of a m r immediately
matched the move a spokesman tim wagner said
ok so now suppose by using the first step
you found out that american airlines and tim
wagner are connected by a relation ok so now
you want to find out what is the relation
so here you have a sentence two entities you
need to find out what is the relation among
all these pos possibilities is family relation
citizen relation subsidiary relation founder
relation and so on so lot of relations are
there you want to find out what is the relation
between these two entities
now how do you solve this problem how would
you solve this problem so you will have a
lot of labeled data when you know these are
the entities here and this is the relation
between them so in classification what we
do from this labeled data we try to abstract
over some sort of features so we will say
ok so these are the features that i see in
this sentence and these features indicate
relation one other sentence i am seeing this
kind of features that indicating relation
two and so on so this is what i i will i will
have from my training data now attached data
again i will try to find out what are the
features and using these features i will try
to match with with one of this previous examples
i have seen in training data this is a simple
ah this is simple illustration but it is generally
more complex than that but this is the basic
idea
so the whole ah effort goes in deciding what
should be my ideal features by which i can
represent all my data points so so how do
i say ok these two are connected by this relation
what are the different things in the surrounding
in the context about these entities that i
should be using to to make this decision and
that is your task of each engineering find
out what are the features that will help you
in this task
in most of the application this is one of
the ah main challenges that for this for this
task find out what are the appropriate set
of features i can used so we will see some
examples at what so so here you can use all
the different concepts that are covered in
this course so its starting from simple ah
language models part of speech tags dependency
parse synthetic parse everything you can use
to do find out to define what are your features
in this task and you will see a lot of examples
here and and this is ah one ah so if you want
to build your own system you you might have
to start thinking in terms of what are the
important insight from data that i here use
use as in the form of my features
so remember features are something that that
you think can help me ah discriminate between
various relations here so it can help me tell
me tell if this is a family relation versus
if it is a citizen relation what are the different
things that can help a are these various words
that occur in the context are these part of
speech tags and or or this is a something
else so this you can abstract in terms of
here features
so let us see what are the kind of features
we can use for this task so i have the sentence
american airlines etcetera and my initial
features could be what are the words in my
mention m one and m two so m one is american
airlines m two is tim wagner so what are the
words that i used in these two mentions so
feature here can be bag of words features
so mention one use uses words like a american
airlines and mention two uses words like tim
wagner so these are simple features i can
also use what are the headwords of these two
mentions the headword mention of of of mention
one is airlines and for mention two it is
wagner and you can also see what is the headword
mention of one plus two airlines plus wagner
so why you are using this headword kind of
features so here you are having american airlines
but suppose there is something like indian
airlines or or some other air airlines so
by using the headwords using capture e one
a new ah new word that has the same headword
but the the initial word was different it
can be captured by using headwords same with
tim wagner so you are capturing the surname
here by headword but suppose if someone else
has a surname wagner so it can also be used
then i can use a what are the words that are
coming around the mentions so that is what
are the words are coming before american airlines
after tim wagner and what are the words in
between so what can be my features so words
or bigrams in particular positions left and
right of m one m two like what is the word
before m two so its a spokesman what is the
word next to ah m two that is said ok so what
you are abstracting here i have an entity
before which i have a word spokesman and next
word is said so the new context whenever i
see what is spokesman before what said afterwards
it might indicate that there might be this
relation ok a spokesman x said it might be
a good indicator of this relation
you can also use the back of words or bigrams
between the two entities that is what are
the different kind of words that occur between
the two entities here so we will say ok so
words like a m r immediately matched a spokesman
unit etcetera they are all occurring between
the two entities and they all go as you are
features
so you can have named entity type and mention
type features so for example what is the named
entity tag for the mention one so its like
american airlines organization so this you
can get by using various ah named entity recognition
tools you can run in any are and you can find
out what are the various named entities so
its say ok mention one is in organization
similarly mention two is a person so this
can be nice ah feature that can help you this
is in organization this is a person so what
can be a relation between them and yeah it
can be together also what is the named entity
for one in two together organization person
then you can also find out entity levels of
mentioned is the name nominal or pronoun so
here first one is a name second one is also
a name but suppose in the sentence you have
it he etcetera so we can call it as a pronoun
on the other hand if you have a word like
the company you will call it as a nominal
so all these can also be your features
now suppose you want to use the dependency
between them so you will see when you convert
the sentence to a dependency graph what is
the connection between the two entities what
are the different branch in that in the tree
are connected so suppose you find this dependency
graph so we will see ok so they are connected
by this path matched said and you are saying
going to wagner airlines matched said wagner
so now you will try to use certain features
based on this path also ok so it can be maybe
what are the words that occurring in this
path or what is the complete path altogether
so here what is the headword of of the dependence
the dependency headword for word one so you
had ah airlines matched airlines is the dependency
for the word one for headword two so we have
the dependency said and wagner this can be
a feature immediate dependency feature matched
airlines said wagner then what is the path
airlines matched said wagner and and you can
also think of some other features ok what
is the label they are at in that dependency
graph how many different words they are connected
to and so on
and then you can also do chunking and is use
used features like ok if you chunk them you
will find american airlines a unit of a m
r etcetera and your feature could be what
is the chunk in which it participates what
is the next chunk after this and so on you
can also use the constituency parse feature
so you have the two words here american airlines
and tim wagner and this is the party of the
sentence so you can use the the the path from
here for noun phrase to this particular noun
phrase that connects tim wagner so what is
the path here going to an noun phrase to a
sentence to a sentence to a noun phrase this
path can be helpful again here you can use
what is the label in the tree they are at
and what is the sibling and so on so these
can be your various features
then they can be some ah sort of features
that you can obtain from various gazetteer
and ah different terms kinship terms so if
your relations contain mother of and parents
of an all that so you can use some kinship
terms so like parents wife husband grandparent
etcetera and this can be obtained from various
electrical sources like wordnet also and then
you can use various gazetteer like what are
the cont country name list so you can see
ok
so the next word after the entity one is a
name of the country or the previous word after
the entity two any of a country similarly
for names of very famous celebrities or persons
all these can be used as your features so
so this is the idea that that you have this
task you have to find out the relations and
you you should be able to use whatever sort
of features you think will help in this task
so we are seeing we are using a lot of different
sort of features and so and they are using
all the different concepts and topics that
you have seen in the basics of this course
so you can have country name list others of
entries etcetera so now once you have identified
what are your features so what will happen
if youre training data each instance you can
convert in a feature vector so we know what
are the different features that are that are
involved in this particular sense and then
you have you can use various classifiers to
built ah to find out given a new sentence
how do i find out if the two entities have
a relation and what is the relation and then
you can you can use multiple classifiers like
naive bayes classifier or s p m or maxent
etcetera and this is the rule always you train
on the training set tune on development set
and test from the test sets
so you should never use your test set for
building your features or ah whatever ah patterns
so you should never use it as set you should
be kept separate so you will only tune on
your development set if you your training
set you run your classifier and ini initially
test on the development set if it doesnt work
keep on improving and once you are satisfied
then the on the test set and find the accuracy
and you might also have to compare with others
if you want to find out if you are doing something
better than what people have already done
so now how do i so once you have done this
classifier you will get your ah so classifier
will tag in this sentence these two entities
are connected by this relation and so on now
how do you find out how good your system is
performing ha and how we compare with the
system so for that we will talk about what
are the various ah evaluation measures or
evaluation metrics matrix how do i evaluate
it ok so in standard that evaluation metrics
are what is the precision what is the recall
and what is the f major
so how do i define these what is the precision
recall etcetera so here are the simple definitions
so precision is so for suppose i am doing
it for each relation separately so precision
would be what are the number of correctly
classified or extracted relations divided
by total number of extracted relations so
that is ah suppose my system ah is giving
ok so these entities these pair of entities
are connected by a relation r ok this is the
output of my system
now from a gold standard suppose i know that
this this and this is correct and this is
incorrect system will give four output three
are correct so precision here will be three
by four so this is one very important metric
that my system should have a high precision
it should be whatever relational predicting
should be correct what is the other criteria
so the criteria is recall recall is what are
the number of correctly extracted relations
but my system identified divided by total
number of gold relations now its important
to find the see the distinction between that
two so ah what we will do in re recall so
the system output in requires the see what
is the what are the gold standard relations
supposing my gold standard i had five entities
i know these entities are connected by this
relation and suppose my system has found out
so it has found out three it is found out
this this and this but my system could not
find out this and this so what is the recall
of my system my system could recall three
out of five possible relation so recall here
would be three by five ok and this i can do
for every relation independently and i can
show my system does work for this relation
with this precision this recall and so on
now there is also a a metric where you can
combine these two and that is called f measure
and what you do is to take a some sort of
harmonic means so this is two p r divided
by p plus r you will take a harmonic mean
of precision recall and that is called your
f measure so this is f measure two p r divided
by p plus r although there are variations
where you can give different weights to precision
and recall also but this is quite accepted
measure that you give a equal weightage to
precision recall and find out an f one measure
so now if we try to summarize the supervised
relations extraction task what we did here
so ah so in general it can achieve very high
accuracy for some relation and if we have
lots of hand labeled training data so for
most of the machine learning algorithms they
all depend on how much label data that you
have so if you have lots and lots of data
they can give you better better and better
accuracy so so that is one bottle neck also
so you need to label lot of data to be able
to get good accuracy and so this is the limitations
here so labeling large training set and the
entities mighty be very very expensive and
it may not generalize to different relation
so i have labeled for some relations but suppose
i want to now extract some new relation i
cannot use this label i need to get new labels
for the new relation
so whatever i have labeled the the model will
only be able to extract those relations a
new relation i have to do the labeling again
so this also does does not generalize so so
we sought to approaches in this lecture we
saw bootstrapping you have you do not want
to annotated lot of data here some seed instance
you go for that but you can if you can annotated
lot of data then you can use a supervised
approaches and they are the main problem is
ah after labeling find out interesting features
that can help with this task
now in in the in the final lecture for this
week you will see an interesting approach
that blends these two approaches together
bootstrapping and supervised approaches and
this can also generalize to many many different
relations that that you have so we so this
is take this approach is called distance super
provision so in the next lecture we will talk
about that approach
thank you